. >> GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYBODY.
WELCOME TO THE NOVEMBER 18TH, 2025 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. >> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL? THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER PRESENTS SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESIDENT
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN PRESIDENT MANDOLIN PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR
MELGAR MELGAR PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR SARDAR SARDAR
PRESIDENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR
WALTON WALTON PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT TEN MEMBERS ARE
PRESENT. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
>> THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT
WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE RAMAKRISHNA
LONEY WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA. AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF
THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE
ROMITA COLONY HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY. AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE
BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELAND.
WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS,
ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAMAKRISHNA LEARNING COMMUNITY
AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST
PEOPLES. >> COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME
IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF ALLEGIANCE?
>> I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG OF THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH IT STANDS ONE NATION
UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE, ABLE TO BE REDEEMED FROM US.
>> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF
AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY THAT'S ESPECIALLY EUGENE LABBADIA WHO
RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS
AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE .
MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR 2 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER.
>> YES, THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 2 P.M. IS THE APPEARANCE AT
TODAY'S MEETING BY THE HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL LURIE
PRESENT TO ENGAGE IN A FORMAL POLICY DISCUSSION WITH ELIGIBLE
BOARD MEMBERS. BEING ONE THROUGH FOUR PRIOR TO
THE DISCUSSION THE MAYOR MAY ADDRESS THE BOARD FOR UP TO
FIVE MINUTES. >> WELCOME, MR. MAYOR.
THERE WERE NO TOPICS SUBMITTED FOR TODAY SO WE HAVE THE
OPPORTUNITY TO HEAR FROM YOU FOR UP TO FIVE MINUTES.
>> THANK YOU FOR PRESIDENT. GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE.
I WANT TO START BY THANKING THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE
LAND USE COMMITTEE AS WE CONTINUE TO ADVANCE THE FAMILY
ZONING PLAN. WE WANT TO MAKE SURE THIS IS A
CITY WHERE POLICE OFFICERS, NURSES AND TEACHERS CAN AFFORD
TO RAISE THEIR CHILDREN AND GRANDCHILDREN.
MY OFFICE HAS BEEN WORKING CLOSELY WITH ALL OF YOU TO
ENSURE THAT SAN FRANCISCANS DECIDE WHAT GETS BUILT IN SAN
FRANCISCO. AS WE WORK TO BUILD A CITY THAT
SUPPORTS FAMILIES, WE RECEIVED ENCOURAGING NEWS ON ANOTHER
FRONT. IN OCTOBER WE RECORDED THE
LOWEST NUMBER OF OVERDOSE OVERDOSE DEATHS SINCE THE CITY
STARTED TRACKING IN 2020. IT'S THE SECOND MONTH IN A ROW
WITH FEWER THAN 40 OVERDOSE DEATHS.
NOW THAT IS PROGRESS BUT ONE DEATH IS ONE TOO MANY.
WE HAVE ALL SEEN PEOPLE STRUGGLING ON OUR STREETS
AND IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS. THAT'S WHY WE ARE BRINGING A
NEW LEVEL OF COORDINATION TO OUR PUBLIC SAFETY AND PUBLIC
HEALTH STRATEGIES. DISRUPTING OPEN AIR DRUG
MARKETS AND CONNECTING PEOPLE TO TREATMENT FASTER.
I AM PROUD OF THE WORK THAT WE HAVE DONE TOGETHER OVER THE
PAST 11 MONTHS TO CONFRONT THIS CRISIS WITH A SHARED SENSE OF
URGENCY AND PURPOSE. AND AS WE LOOK TO NEXT YEAR WE
ARE WORKING TO STAND UP A NEW CENTER WITH THE SUPPORT OF
SUPERVISOR DORSEY THAT WILL HELP US CONTINUE TO MOVE THAT
WORK FORWARD. >> NOW I MAY CLOSE WITH THIS.
I AM CONTINUING TO LEARN AND GROW AS A MAYOR.
AND AS I'VE SAID AND AS I SAID LAST WEEK TO SAN FRANCISCANS
AFTER SUPERVISOR ALVAREZ STEPPED DOWN I WISH I HAD DONE
MORE TO HELP HER SUCCEED. IT WAS NOT THE FIRST TIME THAT
I HAVE GOTTEN SOMETHING WRONG AND IT WON'T BE THE LAST.
BUT I WILL CONTINUE TO GET BETTER AT THIS JOB EVERY SINGLE
DAY. I'M DETERMINED TO APPOINT A
DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR WHO TRULY REPRESENTS THE SUNSET
AND WILL BE THE COLLEAGUE AND PARTNER THAT YOU ALL
DESERVE. I WANT TO THANK THOSE OF YOU ON
THE BOARD WHO HAVE REACHED OUT TO OFFER FEEDBACK AND SUPPORT
THROUGHOUT THIS PROCESS. YOUR JOBS ARE NOT EASY AND I AM
COMMITTED TO GETTING THIS RIGHT.
SO THANK YOU AND I'LL LET YOU GET BACK TO YOUR MEETING.
THANK YOU MR. MAYOR. >> THANK YOU.
APPRECIATE IT. ALL RIGHT.
AND WITH THAT, THIS MATTER HAS BEEN DISCUSSED AND HAS NOW
FILED. >> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO OUR
CONSENT TO AGENDA ITEMS ONE THROUGH 20 COMMUNICATIONS MR.
PRESIDENT. YOU ARE CORRECT.
THANK YOU. LET'S GO BACK TO COMMUNICATIONS
. THANK YOU.
I'LL JUST A FOLLOW UP FROM THE MAYOR ON NOVEMBER 13TH LAST
THURSDAY WE RECEIVED A MEMO FROM BAY ALCARAZ RESIGNING HER
DISTRICT FOUR SEAT HERE AT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS LEAVING A
VACANCY IN THE DISTRICT FOR OFFICE AND IT WILL REMAIN
VACANT UNTIL THE MAYOR MAKES HIS APPOINTMENT.
AND SO THE VOTE THRESHOLD WILL BE EITHER SIX OF 11 DESPITE THE
VACANCY OR UNLESS THE CHARTER OR OTHER ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
REQUIRES A HIGHER VOTE THRESHOLD.
>> AND THEN I HAVE TO ROUTINE COMMUNICATIONS TO MAKE THE
FIRST IS THAT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOUR
ATTENDANCE HERE IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER ROOM TWO
52ND FLOOR AND CITY HALL WHEN YOU CANNOT BE HERE WE ARE
STREAMING LIVE ON S.F. GOVEE TV'S CHANNEL 26 OR AT W W W DOT
SMG OR VTV.ORG. IF YOU HAVE PUBLIC COMMENT
YOU'D LIKE TO SUBMIT IN EITHER WRITING YOU CAN SEND IT TO BOSS
AT S.F. GOV DAWG OR THE U.S. POSTAL SERVICE SAN FRANCISCO
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B GOODLATTE
PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO CALIFORNIA 94102 IF
YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION AND FOR A FUTURE
MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT OR IF YOU
NEED TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE YOU SHOULD CALL THE
CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY
CALLING (415) 554-5184. >> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. >> LET'S GO TO APPROVAL OF OUR
MEETING MINUTES. YES, WE HAVE APPROVAL OF THE
OCTOBER 7TH 2025 BOARD MEETING MINUTES.
AND CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED AND MOVED BY CHERYL SECONDED BY WALTON.
>> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED? SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN. ALL RIGHT MANDEL MAN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EITHER
ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER
PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S NOW GO TO OUR
CONSENT AGENDA ITEMS ONE THROUGH 20 ITEMS ONE THROUGH 20
ARE ON CONSENT. THESE ITEMS ARE CONSIDERED TO
BE ROUTINE IF A MEMBER OBJECTS AN ITEM MAY BE REMOVED
AND CONSIDERED SEPARATELY AND I DON'T SEE ANYONE ON THE ROSTER
SO MADAM CLERK CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS ONE
THROUGH 20. SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EITHER ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION
THESE ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING AND FINALLY
PASSED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL
ITEM 21 ITEM 21 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATE OF CODE TO REQUIRE THE ARTS COMMISSION TO DEVELOP
AND ADMINISTER A CERTIFICATION PROCESS TO IDENTIFY ARTISTS
IN SAN FRANCISCO WHO MAY BE ELIGIBLE FOR AFFORDABLE HOUSING
FOR ARTISTS. AND I THINK WE CAN TAKE THIS
ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 22. ITEM 22 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO
EXEMPT THE HEALTH SERVICE SYSTEMS LIFE AND LONG TERM
DISABILITY INSURANCE SERVICES CONTRACT FROM THE REQUIREMENTS
OF ARTICLE 111 THE MINIMUM COMPENSATION AND ARTICLE 121
THE HEALTH CARE ACCOUNTABILITY ACT OF THE LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT
CODE AGAIN SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 23 ITEM 23 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE
TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CREATE THE SMALL
BUSINESS REZONING CONSTRUCTION RELIEF PROGRAM TO PROVIDE
FINANCIAL SUPPORT INCLUDING GRANTS AND LOANS TO BUSINESSES
IMPACTED BY CONSTRUCTION RELATING TO THE CITY'S
RESIDENTIAL REZONING PROGRAM ADOPTED IN 2025 THROUGH 26 TO
ESTABLISH THE SMALL BUSINESS REZONING CONSTRUCTION RELIEF
FUND TO RECEIVE MONEYS FOR THE PROGRAM TO DESIGNATE THE OFFICE
OF SMALL BUSINESS AND OFFICE OF ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE
DEVELOPMENT TO ADMINISTER THE FUND AND THE PROGRAM AND TO
PROMULGATE RULES AND REGULATIONS IN FURTHERANCE
OF THE PROGRAM AND TO AMEND THE BUSINESS AND TAX REGULATIONS
CODE TO ALLOW TAXPAYERS TO DESIGNATE A PORTION OF THEIR
GROSS RECEIPTS TAXES FOR DEPOSIT INTO THE FUND SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL N24
ITEM 24 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE 3.5 MILLION FROM
THE GENERAL RESERVE TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING
AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO EXPAND ACCESS TO EXISTING
COORDINATED SERVICES FOR IMMIGRATION, LEGAL DEFENSE
AND COMMUNITY RESPONSE SERVICES TO THE IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY
IN FISCAL YEAR 25 THROUGH 2026. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST
READING. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
25. >> ITEM 25.
THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE THE FOURTH AMENDMENT BETWEEN
THE CITY AND LIVESTOCK INTERNATIONAL LIMITED FOR CLASS
A BIOSOLIDS MANAGEMENT SERVICES FOR AN INCREASED AMOUNT OF 20.7
MILLION AND A TOTAL AMOUNT OF APPROXIMATELY 36.67 MILLION.
TO EXTEND THE TERM BY TWO YEARS FROM JUNE 30TH 2027 FOR A TOTAL
TERM OF JULY 1ST 2022 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2029.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
26. >> ITEM 26 RESOLUTION TO
AUTHORIZE THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE TO ENTER INTO A CONTRACT WITH
ARAMARK CORRECTIONAL SERVICES INC FOR JAIL FOOD SERVICES FOR
A TOTAL CONTRACT AMOUNT OF 22 MILLION AND A TERM OF FIVE
YEARS WITH TWO ONE YEAR OPTIONS TO RENEW.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 27 ITEM 27. THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE
THE THIRD AMENDMENT TO THE AIRPORT ADVERTISING LEASE
NUMBER 12 DASH ZERO 231 BETWEEN CLEAR CHANNEL OUTDOOR LLC DOING
BUSINESS AS CLEAR CHANNEL AIRPORTS FOR THE ADDITION OF
PREMISES SOLELY FOR THE PROMOTION OF LARGE SPORTING
EVENTS AND TO ESTABLISH A NEW RENT STRUCTURE FOR THOSE
LOCATIONS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 28 ITEM 28 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE THE POLICE DEPARTMENT TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND AN APPROXIMATE $654,000 GRANT FROM THE BOARD
OF STATE AND COMMUNITY CORRECTIONS FOR THE EDWARD
BYRNE MEMORIAL JUSTICE ASSISTANCE GRANT EQUIPMENT
AND TRAINING PROGRAM TO PROCURE EQUIPMENT AND SERVICES FOR THE
CRIMINOLOGY LABORATORY. WITH THE PROJECT PERIOD
BEGINNING ON OCTOBER 1ST, 2025 THROUGH SEPTEMBER 30TH 2026
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
29. >> ITEM 29.
THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF
HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT TO EXECUTE A
STANDARD AGREEMENT WITH CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF
HOUSING AND COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT UNDER THE INFILL
INFRASTRUCTURE GRANT PROGRAM CATALYTIC QUALIFYING INFILL
AREA FOR A TOTAL AWARD OF 45 MILLION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 30. ITEM 30 RESOLUTION TO APPROVE
FOR PURPOSES OF THE INTERNAL REVENUE CODE OF 1986 AS AMENDED
SECTION ONE FORCE SEVEN SUB F OF THE ISSUANCE AND SALE OF
REVENUE OBLIGATIONS BY THE CALIFORNIA ENTERPRISE
DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY IN AN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT OF 5
MILLION TO REFINANCE THE COST OF ACQUISITION REHABILITATION
IMPROVEMENT INSTALLATION AND EQUIPPING OF A PORTION OF
ADMINISTRATIVE FACILITIES OWNED AND OPERATED BY MICHIGAN
ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT AGENCY. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAME CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 31.
>> ITEM 31. THIS ITEM WAS REFERRED WITHOUT
RECOMMENDATION FROM THE BUDGET AND FINANCE COMMITTEE.
IT'S A RESOLUTION TO APPROVE A COMMERCIAL LEASE AGREEMENT
BETWEEN THE CITY AND SAN FRANCISCO.
C AND C DOING BUSINESS AS MILLS DRIVE-IN FOR THE RETAIL SPACE
LOCATED AT 801 MISSION STREET IN THE FIFTH AND MISSION GARAGE
FOR AN INITIAL FIVE YEAR TERM THAT WILL RESULT IN AN
ESTIMATED APPROXIMATE 1.9 MILLION IN REVENUE AND ONE FIVE
YEAR OPTION TO EXTEND THE LEASE .
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN.
COLLEAGUES, AS YOU KNOW YOUR BUDGET COMMITTEE COLLEAGUES
UNDER THE CAPABLE LEADERSHIP OF OUR CHAIR CONNIE CHAN
OCCASIONALLY REFER ITEMS OUT OF THAT COMMITTEE WITHOUT OUR
RECOMMENDATION. THAT'S NOT NECESSARILY TO
EMBARRASS CITY DEPARTMENTS BUT TYPICALLY TO FLAG ISSUES THAT
MERIT THE FULL BOARD'S AWARENESS BEFORE THE VOTE.
AND THAT IS THE CASE TODAY WITH ITEM 31.
I WON'T SPEAK FOR MY BUDGET COMMITTEE COLLEAGUES BUT I WILL
SAY I DON'T HAVE ANY ISSUES WITH THE PROPOSED LEASE FOR
THIS BUSINESS IN MY DISTRICT PER SE.
HOWEVER, IN THE PROCESS OF BRINGING THIS LEASE TO THE
BOARD THE BLR IDENTIFIED INTERNAL CONTROL WEAKNESSES
IN MTA'S LEASE MANAGEMENT PRACTICES.
THESE INCLUDE ISSUES WITH LEASE DOCUMENTATION, SOLICITATION
PRACTICE PROCESSES AND THE SUFFICIENCY OF WRITTEN
POLICIES. THESE ISSUES ARE LARGELY
ATTRIBUTABLE TO EXECUTIVE DIRECTORS DIRECTIVES FROM THE
COVID LOCKDOWN WHEN THEN-MAYOR BREED ORDERED RENT ABATEMENTS
WHERE POSSIBLE TO CITY TENANTS WHOSE BUSINESSES WERE ADVERSELY
IMPACTED BY THAT EMERGENCY. FOR S.F. MTA.
THERE WERE ABOUT 25 RETAIL LEASES THAT WERE VERBALLY
AMENDED FROM FIXED RENT TERMS TO RENTS BASED ON 8% OF GROSS
SALES. UNFORTUNATELY NONE OF THOSE
AMENDMENTS WAS DOCUMENTED. S.F. MTA HAS A PLAN TO ADDRESS
ALL OF THESE DEFICIENCIES IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE BLAZE
RECOMMENDATION. IT'S MY UNDERSTANDING THAT
THERE ARE ABOUT 25 LEASES THAT MTA VERBALLY AMENDED.
ONLY TWO OF THESE REQUIRE BOARD APPROVAL AND THAT IS TODAY'S
LEASE WITH MELS IN MY DISTRICT AND ANOTHER LEASE WITH TED'S
INC. IN SUPERVISOR SADR'S DISTRICT THAT WILL YOU CAN
EXPECT TO SEE IN JANUARY. MTA HAS AGREED TO WORK WITH THE
CITY ATTORNEY ON THE REMAINING LEASES NOT SUBJECT TO BOARD
APPROVAL AND THESE WILL BE FINALIZED BY THE END OF THE
FIRST QUARTER OF 2026. ACCORDING TO THE BILL, THE
RENTAL ADJUSTMENT OF TWO 8% OF GROSS SALES APPEARS TO HAVE
BEEN REASONABLE AS COMPARED TO SIMILAR RESTAURANT LEASES AT
THE AIRPORT AND PORT. SO THE DEFICIENCIES IN THIS
ITEM ARE NOT FINANCIAL BUT RATHER PROCEDURAL BECAUSE I A
TANG MTA'S REAL ESTATE DIVISION MANAGER WHO STARTED THIS PAST
SUMMER ASSURED US THAT SHE IS FULLY COMMITTED TO MODERNIZING
THE DIVISION'S POLICIES, PROCEDURES AND PRACTICES SO WE
DON'T HAVE ISSUES LIKE THIS BEFORE US IN THE FUTURE.
>> THAT'S IT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR DORSEY I
DON'T THINK ANYONE NEEDS A ROLL CALL FOR THIS.
I'M NOT SEEING OKAY. THEN WE WILL TAKE ITEM 31 SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEMS 32 AND 33 TOGETHER. >> ITEMS 32 AND 33 OR TO
ORDINANCE IS THAT PERTAIN TO THE AS HAVE GATEWAY PROJECT
ITEM 32. THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE
PLANNING CODE AND THE ZONING MAP TO ESTABLISH THE SAN
FRANCISCO GATEWAY SPECIAL USE DISTRICT TO GENERALLY BOUNDED
BY KIRKWOOD AVENUE TO THE NORTHEAST RANKIN STREET TO THE
NORTHEAST TO THE SOUTHEAST MCKINNON AVENUE TO THE
SOUTHWEST AND TOLLAND STREET TO THE NORTHWEST.
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
ITEM 33 THIS ORDINANCE APPROVES THE DEVELOPMENT AGREEMENT
BETWEEN THE CITY AND COUNTY AND PROLOGIS FOR THE
DEVELOPMENT OF AN APPROXIMATE 17.1 ACRE SITE LOCATED AT
TOLAND STREET AT KIRKWOOD AVENUE WITH TWO MULTI-STORY
PRODUCTION DISTRIBUTION AND REPAIR BUILDINGS IN A CORE
INDUSTRIAL AREA FOR RETAIL USES A ROOFTOP SOLAR ARRAY GROUND
FLOOR MAKERSPACE AND STREETS BUILT TO CITY STANDARD AND TO
MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS AND LET'S TAKE THESE ITEMS SAME
HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES ARE
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 34.
>> ITEM 34 THIS ORDINANCE AMENDS THE PLANNING CODE TO
DEFINE LEGACY BUSINESSES AND TO REQUIRE A CONDITIONAL USE
AUTHORIZATION PRIOR TO REPLACING A LEGACY BUSINESS
WITH A NEW NONRESIDENTIAL USE IN CERTAIN NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL NAMED NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL AND NEIGHBORHOOD
COMMERCIAL TRANSIT DISTRICTS AND IN THE CHINATOWN MIXED USE
DISTRICT TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO ALLOW A
BUSINESS THAT HAS BEEN OPERATING FOR 15 YEARS TO
QUALIFY AS A LEGACY BUSINESS TO AFFIRM THE SECOND DETERMINATION
AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS PURSUANT TO CHARTER
SECTION 4.105. THIS MATTER REQUIRES A VOTE OF
TWO THIRDS OR EIGHT VOTES OF THE ENTIRE MEMBERSHIP OF THE
BOARD TO REVERSE THE DISAPPROVAL OF A PLANNING
COMMISSION AND APPROVE THIS ORDINANCE FOR PASSAGE.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMANDA AND COLLEAGUES
THE ORDINANCE BEFORE YOU TODAY RECOGNIZES THAT LEGACY AND LONG
TIME BUSINESSES ARE NOT JUST BUSINESS ENTITIES THEY ARE
CULTURAL ASSETS AND ARE RECOGNIZED AS CONTRIBUTORS TO
THE NEIGHBORHOODS THAT PAVE THE WAY FOR OTHER SMALL BUSINESS TO
THRIVE. >> SMALL BUSINESSES CAN NO
LONGER RELY ON GOODWILL NEGOTIATION TRADITIONALLY
AFFORDED BY INDIVIDUAL OR FAMILY PROPERTY OWNERS AND THEY
ARE FACING INCREASING PRESSURE FROM CORPORATE LANDLORDS
AND DEVELOPERS WHO ONLY SEEK TO CAPITALIZE ON SPECULATIVE
MARKETS. THIS ORDINANCE PERFECTLY
ENCAPSULATES THE GOALS OF A NUMBER OF POLICY UNDER THE
CITY'S COMMERCE AND DOES THREE ELEMENTS OBJECTIVE ENHANCES THE
CITY'S SOCIAL, CULTURAL AND ECONOMIC VITALITY AND BOOST
EMPLOYEE PAYMENT OPPORTUNITIES. THE COMMERCE INDUSTRY ELEMENTS
OBJECTIVE 3.1 EVEN EXPLICITLY STATES THAT ONE EMPLOYMENT
SECTOR THAT OFTEN SERVES TO BE A SOURCE OF EMPLOYMENT
OPPORTUNITY TO MINORITIES AND LOW SKILLED WORKERS IS THE
SMALL BUSINESS SECTOR. HOWEVER SMALL NEWLY FORMED
BUSINESS SUFFER FROM A HIGH PERCENTAGE OF BUSINESS FAILURES
. THEREFORE PROTECTION OF
EXISTING SMALL BUSINESSES PARTICULARLY THOSE THAT HAVE
BEEN OPERATING FOR MORE THAN A DECADE DESERVES PROTECTION NOT
ONLY FOR THE BUSINESS BUT ALSO FOR THE PRESERVATION OF JOBS
FOR MINORITIES AND ECONOMIC ONLY DISADVANTAGED COMMUNITIES.
THAT IS WHY DISLODGES SATION INCLUDES EXEMPTION FOR MICRO
AND SMALL BUSINESSES FROM THE CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION
PROCESS AND EXEMPT STOREFRONTS THAT ARE AND HAVE BEEN VACANT
FOR THREE YEARS OR MORE. THIS IS TO ENSURE WE'RE ADDING
PROTECTION WITHOUT ADDING MORE BARRIERS TO NEW SMALL BUSINESS
OWNERS. IF WE CANNOT PROTECT THE
EXISTING SMALL BUSINESS, HOW CAN WE GIVE CONFIDENCE TO NEW
ENTREPRENEURS THAT THEY TOO CAN THRIVE IN SAN FRANCISCO?
BEFORE THE VOTE I WOULD LIKE TO ALSO MAKE A MOTION TO INTRODUCE
AMENDMENTS AND MAY AMEND MEANT TO THIS LEGISLATION.
THERE ARE NONE SUBSTANTIVE TO EXEMPT LEGACY BUSINESS FROM THE
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION PROCESS.
ALLOW LOAN WITH SMALL BUSINESS AND THAT IS ON PAGE NINE
COLLEAGUES AND LINES 17 TO 18 INSERTING TWO DEFINITION INTO
PLANNING CODE AND AGAIN ON PAGE TEN LINE 11 INSERTING THE TERM
LEGACY BUSINESS OR QUALIFIES AS A SMALL BUSINESS.
AND ON PAGE 11 LINE SEVEN AGAIN INSERTING LEGACY BUSINESS.
>> COLLEAGUES, WE IT'S A LONG JOURNEY TO BE HERE.
WE HAVE GOTTEN FEEDBACK FROM OUR SMALL BUSINESS COMMISSION
AND THAT'S A REASON WHY THAT THIS LEGISLATION IS DIFFERENT
THAN THE ONE THAT WAS PASSED UNANIMOUSLY LAST YEAR AS A
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION FOR INTERIM ZONING CONTROL FOR
18 MONTHS. AUTHORED BY BOARD PRESIDENT
FORMER BOARD PRESIDENT AARON PESKIN.
AND NOW WE ARE TURNING THIS INTO PERMANENT FOR A
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZED ZATION.
IN THE EVENT A LEGACY BUSINESS IS DISPLACED.
THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THAT LEGISLATION AND THIS IS THAT
WE'RE PROVIDING EXEMPTION FOR SMALL BUSINESS AND THIS
BUSINESS WILL NOT NEED TO GO THROUGH TO SEE YOU SHOULD THEY
MOVE INTO THAT SPACE. BOTH CURRENT MEANING THE
EXISTING SPACE OR A NEW DEVELOPED SPACE ALL WHICH IS TO
SAY IS RELEASED WITH A SIMPLE GOAL HOW CAN WE PROTECT OUR
SMALL BUSINESS WHEN THEY FACE DISPLACEMENT AND IS STILL NOT
COMPROMISING AND MAKING SURE THAT ANY EMPTY STOREFRONTS BOTH
EXISTING AND NEW ONE CAN STILL BE A WELCOMING SPACE FOR SMALL
BUSINESS INCLUDING LEGACY BUSINESS.
I HOPE TO HAVE YOUR SUPPORT COLLEAGUES AND THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
I VOTED AGAINST THIS ORDINANCE AT THE LAND USE COMMITTEE A FEW
WEEKS AGO AND WHILE I APPRECIATE THE NEW AMENDMENTS
AND I'LL BE VOTING IN SUPPORT OF THE AMENDMENTS, I'LL STILL
BE VOTING NO ON THE ORIGINAL ON THE OVERALL ORDINANCE HERE AT
THE FULL BOARD DUE TO FROM MY PERSPECTIVE NOT ADDRESSING THE
CONCERNS FULLY THAT WERE RAISED BY THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
AND THE SMALL BUSINESS COMMISSION.
BUT FIRSTLY I AM A SUPPORTER OF THE LEGACY BUSINESS PROGRAM.
I CHERISH THE SMALL BUSINESSES THAT HAVE LONG BEEN IN THE
FABRIC OF OUR NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE SOCAL HARDWARE
IN JAPANTOWN OR GAME SCAPE UNDER ISIDRO.
IT'S A WIN WIN THAT PROVIDES MARKETING GRANT OPPORTUNITIES
AND ASSISTANCE TO LONG RUNNING BUSINESSES TO HELP KEEP THEM
GOING AND TO KEEP OUR NEIGHBORHOODS AND STOREFRONTS
VIBRANT. BUT IT IS FOR THAT REASON THAT
I AM OPPOSED TO THIS LEGISLATION THIS ENTIRE YEAR AS
A BOARD AND IN THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AS WELL.
WE'VE BEEN FOCUSED ON CUTTING RED TAPE PERMIT S.F. GOOD
GOVERNANCE AND REMOVING OBSTACLES FOR BUSINESSES TO
FILL VACANT STOREFRONTS. >> OFTENTIMES THOSE VACANT
STOREFRONTS NEED TO BE FILLED BY GROCERY STORES
AND PHARMACIES AND THAT IS SOMETHING THAT WE ARE TRYING TO
DO ALL OVER THE CITY AT THIS TIME.
>> BUT BY REQUIRING A CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION
TO FILL A SPACE THAT WAS FORMERLY HELD BY A LEGACY
BUSINESS, IT CREATES NEGATIVE INCENTIVES TO BLOCK NEW LEGACY
BUSINESS DESIGNATIONS OR EVEN WORSE INCENTIVIZE LANDLORDS TO
KICK OUT A BUSINESS ONCE THEY APPROACH THEIR 30 YEAR
THRESHOLD OR 15 YEARS IF UNDER THREAT OF DISPLACEMENT.
UNDER THIS ORDINANCE. >> THIS ITEM IS MEANT TO
PROTECT AND IS WELL INTENDED AND PROTECTING LEGACY
BUSINESSES BUT THE LEGISLATION IN AND OF ITSELF DOES NOT
DISTINGUISH BETWEEN A BUSINESS THAT IS BEING KICKED OUT DUE TO
DISPLACEMENT BY THE LANDLORD OR THROUGH THEIR OWN VOLITION
AND IT STANDS TO IN TURN THREATEN THEIR POTENTIAL TO
MAINTAIN OR APPLY FOR LEGACY BUSINESS IN THAT CONTEXT.
WE HEARD AT THE COMMITTEE FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT THAT IT
HAS ALREADY CREATED ISSUES IN THE AREAS WHERE THIS PLACE
OR THIS POLICIES AND PLACE AS AN INTERIM ZONING CONTROL WHERE
A BUSINESS WAS ASKED TO LEAVE THE PROGRAM SO AS TO NOT MAKE
IT MORE DIFFICULT FOR THE LANDLORD.
>> OUR CONSTITUENTS WANT US TO KNOW WANT US TO MAKE GOVERNMENT
WORK BETTER FOR THEM. >> AND IT'S CLEAR TO ME THAT
THIS LEGISLATION IS NOT WORKING IN THAT DIRECTION.
>> AND I'M NOT ALONE. IT'S RARE FOR ANY ITEM LET
ALONE ONE THAT IS FOCUSED ON SMALL BUSINESS TO BE OPPOSED BY
THE SMALL BUSINESS COMMISSION, OPPOSED BY THE PLANNING
COMMISSION AND OPPOSED BY THE COUNCIL OF DISTRICT MERCHANTS
ASSOCIATION. >> THERE'S A CARVE OUT IN THIS
LEGISLATION FOR SMALL BUSINESSES THAT AGAIN WHILE
WELL INTENTIONED WOULD PREVENT THEM FROM NEEDING A CONDITIONAL
USE AUTHORIZATION. >> BUT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT
TOLD US AS WELL IN COMMITTEE THAT THIS WOULD BE SOMETHING
THAT THEY WOULD HAVE A HARD TIME IMPLEMENTING.
>> THE PLANNING COMMISSION ALSO NOTED THAT THIS IS NOT A
TYPICAL USE OF CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION WHICH IS INTENDED
TO HELP REGULATE LAND USE, NOT PROPERTY OWNERS.
THE PLANNING COMMISSION WOULD HAVE NO GROUNDS TO DENY A
CONDITIONAL USE AUTHORIZATION TO A NEW BUSINESS AND YET THEY
WOULD STILL HAVE TO JUMP THROUGH HOOPS TO FILL A VACANT
STOREFRONT. >> THERE ARE ALREADY FORMULA
RETAIL RESTRICTIONS ON THESE AREAS WHERE THIS ORDINANCE
WOULD APPLY. SO THIS DOES NOTHING TO PREVENT
CHAIN STORES FROM OPENING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> THIS LEGISLATION AND AGAIN WHILE WELL-INTENDED WILL HAVE
THE OPPOSITE EFFECT OF ITS INTENT WITH RESPECT TO LEGACY
BUSINESSES AND INSTEAD PUT A STRAIN ON THOSE INCENTIVES IT
CREATES PROCESS FOR NEW AND EXPANDED BUSINESSES
AND KEEPS STOREFRONTS VACANT AS THE NET EFFECT IN THE CITY'S
NEIGHBORHOOD COMMERCIAL DISTRICTS.
IT'S NOT GOOD GOVERNMENT AND FOR THAT REASON I'LL BE
VOTING NO BEFORE I CALL ON SUPERVISOR SÖDER.
THE CLERK HAS POINTED OUT TO ME THAT SUPERVISOR CHEN MADE A
MOTION IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY WALTON AND WE WILL
CONTINUE. >> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU
PRESENT GENTLEMEN. I APPRECIATE THE INTENTION OF
THIS ORDINANCE AND YOU KNOW I KNOW THAT WE ALL SHARE A
COMMITMENT FOR LEGACY BUSINESSES AND SMALL
BUSINESSES. I'M CONCERNED THAT THIS WILL
WORK AS INTENDED IN SOME CASES BUT IN JUST AS MANY CASES IF
NOT MORE IT WILL HAVE UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES
AND THAT IS NOT SOMETHING THAT IS JUST MY THOUGHT OR MY
OPINION. IT IS SOMETHING THAT HAS BEEN
FLAGGED AND SHARED BY THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S
RECOMMENDATION TO NOT APPROVE THIS BY THE SMALL BUSINESS
COMMISSION'S RECOMMENDATIONS AND I APPROVE THIS.
AND BY THE LARGEST CITYWIDE ORGANIZATION OF MERCHANTS THE
SAN FRANCISCO COUNCIL OF DISTRICT MERCHANTS I SEE A LOT
OF OTHER OPTIONS THAT WOULD BE MORE CLEAR AND WOULD BE MORE
IMPACTFUL FOR US TO SUPPORT LEGACY BUSINESSES AND SMALL
BUSINESSES. SO FOR THOSE REASONS I WILL NOT
BE SUPPORTING THIS PIECE OF LEGISLATION TODAY.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL I WON'T GO INTO THE DETAIL AND REPEAT WHAT
MY COLLEAGUES SUPERVISOR MAHMUD AND SAUDER MENTIONED BUT BY
AND LARGE I AGREE WITH EVERYTHING THAT THEY SAID.
AND WHAT TROUBLES ME MOST HERE IS THAT WE ARE ERECTING
BARRIERS WITHOUT CERTAINTY THAT THIS WOULD ACTUALLY BENEFIT OUR
LEGACY AND OUR SMALL BUSINESSES.
WE'VE SEEN EXAMPLES WHERE A CONDITIONAL USE REQUIREMENT IS
ALREADY IN PLACE FOR SPACES FORMERLY FILLED WITH LEGACY
BUSINESSES AND DISPLACEMENT STILL OCCURRED.
WE'VE HEARD DIRECTLY FROM THE SMALL BUSINESS COMMISSION THE
PLANNING COMMISSION WHO BOTH VOTED TO REJECT THIS ORDINANCE
AT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT WILL HAVE TROUBLE ADJUDICATING WHO
IS A SMALL BUSINESS TO FILL THESE VACANCIES AND YOU KNOW
WE'VE SEEN EXAMPLES OF LEGACY BUSINESSES WHO TO DELISTED
THEMSELVES FROM THE REGISTRY BECAUSE THIS REQUIREMENT WOULD
WORSEN THE BUSINESS RELATIONSHIP WITH THEIR
LANDLORD. I THINK WE SHOULD BE PROMOTING
SMALL BUSINESSES AS SMALL BUSINESSES.
I THINK WE SHOULD BE ENCOURAGING SMALL BUSINESSES TO
BECOME LEGACY BUSINESSES AND ANYTHING THAT CREATES
POTENTIAL DISINCENTIVE IS AROUND THAT WHETHER INTENDED OR
UNINTENDED OR SOMETHING WE MUST PREVENT.
AND SO I THINK I WILL BE VOTING AGAINST THIS THIS MEASURE AND I
WILL BE STANDING UP FOR OUR SMALL BUSINESSES AND SUPPORTING
OUR THRIVING NEIGHBORHOOD MERCHANT CORRIDORS AS SUCH.
>> SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU. I WANT TO CLARIFY A COUPLE OF
THINGS. I THINK THAT IT WOULD BE
MISLEADING TO THINK THAT FIRST AND FOREMOST I THINK SMALL
BUSINESS COMMISSION WHILE DID NOT RECOMMEND THIS LEGISLATION
. THIS IS BEFORE WE TAKING THE
FEEDBACK ABOUT HOW THIS COULD BE A BARRIER FOR SMALL
BUSINESS. AND SINCE THEN WE THEN WITH
THEIR FEEDBACK TO ADD THE EXEMPTION AND THAT'S REALLY THE
CLEAR DIFFERENCE THAN THE ONE THAT PREVIOUSLY WE PROPOSED.
AND WE TAKEN THAT FEEDBACK TO EXEMPT SMALL BUSINESSES
AND MICRO-BUSINESSES AND NOW EVEN THE LEGACY BUSINESS FOR
THEM TO MOVE IN TO THE EXISTING OR NEW VACANT STOREFRONT.
I DON'T THINK THAT IS IT'S ALSO MISLEADING TO THINK THAT
SOMEHOW THE PLANNING COMMISSION WHILE VOTED AGAINST IT THAT IT
WAS UNANIMOUS THAT IT WAS A42 WITH COMMISSIONER GILBERT
WILLIAMS ABSENT AGAINST THIS LEGISLATION.
I THINK THAT LET ME ALSO PUT THIS IN A CONTEXT ABOUT HOW
THIS IS IN THE CONTEXT OF THE UP ZONING LEGISLATION THAT'S
GOING TO COME BEFORE US IN DECEMBER TO REALLY THINK
ABOUT WHAT ARE THE MECHANISM THAT WE CAN PROVIDE TO PROTECT
THE EXISTING LEGACY BUSINESS AND SMALL BUSINESS.
WHAT I DO THINK THAT IT IS OUR RESPONSIBILITY TO UTILIZE EVERY
LEGISLATIVE TOOLS IN OUR TOOLBOX TO PROTECT OUR SMALL
BUSINESS TO DATE OTHER THAN SUPERVISOR MAL GARDEN
LEGISLATION TO PROVIDE A REALLY FUN AND WE STILL NEED TO WORK
ON A MECHANISM FOR THE FUNDING SOURCE.
WE HAVE NOT DONE MUCH TO PROTECT OUR SMALL BUSINESS.
I WE I BELIEVE WE NEED TO DO A LOT MORE THAN WHAT IS BEFORE US
TODAY. AND SHOULD THIS NOT BE APPROVED
? I THINK IT'S A MISSED
OPPORTUNITY GIVEN WHAT WE HAVE TO FACE VERY SOON IN DECEMBER.
THERE ARE SMALL BUSINESSES THAT ARE ALREADY FACING DIFFICULTY
AND BEING REALLY PUSHED OUT BY FORMULA RETAIL AND FOR ME AS A
DISTRICT SUPERVISOR FOR RICHMOND, OUR WE'RE ALREADY
SEEING SOME OF OUR SMALL BUSINESS INCLUDING LEGACY
BUSINESS FACING THOSE CHALLENGES.
SO I'M NOT GOING TO DELAY MY POINT BUT I'M GOING TO MAKE THE
MOTION TO AMEND WHICH THANK YOU SO MUCH TO THE SECOND BY
SUPERVISOR WALTON AND I DO WISH AT LEAST WE HAVE THAT VOTE TO
BE ABLE TO AMEND THIS LEGISLATION AND THEN BEFORE WE
CAST OUR FINAL VOTE. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER I'LL JUST KEEP IT SHORT.
IT HAS WORKED IN MY DISTRICT AND I WILL BE SUPPORTING THIS.
>> SUPERVISOR CHERYL I JUST WANT TO NOTE THAT I DO THINK
THIS BOARD HAS DONE A LOT TO SUPPORT SMALL BUSINESSES AND I
THINK THERE'S A DIFFERENCE IN PROTECTING AND SUPPORTING
AND WHEN WE TALK TO THE SMALL BUSINESSES IN MY DISTRICT, THE
NUMBER ONE THING THEY'RE STRUGGLING WITH HIS FOOT
TRAFFIC AND CUSTOMERS. WE NEED MORE CUSTOMERS.
THEY NEED MORE REVENUE. WE NEED TO SUPPORT THEM TO BE
CREATIVE. WE NEED TO SUPPORT OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD MERCHANT CORRIDORS TO HAVE NO VACANCIES, TO BE
ABSOLUTELY THRIVING. WE NEED TO MAKE IT EASIER TO DO
BUSINESS HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO. THERE'S NO QUESTION THAT
FORMULA RETAIL STORES IN CERTAIN CORRIDORS CAN DRIVE
UP COSTS THAT IS TRUE. BUT THIS LEGISLATION DOESN'T
TOUCH ON THAT FORMULA. RETAIL ALREADY HAS TO GO
THROUGH CONDITIONAL USE APPLICATIONS.
THERE ARE ALREADY PROTECTIONS IN PLACE THERE AND THIS WOULD
BE DUPLICATIVE IN MANY WAYS. I THINK WE NEED TO STAY FOCUSED
ON THE FACT THAT THE NUMBER ONE PROBLEM THAT OUR SMALL
BUSINESSES ARE FACING HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO IS A LACK OF
CUSTOMERS. SALES TAX RECEIPTS ARE DOWN
IN EVERY SINGLE NEIGHBORHOOD IN SAN FRANCISCO.
OTHER THAN MISSION BAY FROM PRE-COVID STATS SALES TAX
RECEIPTS THAT MEANS BUSINESS IS DOWN AND COSTS ARE UP.
WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE THEY'RE GETTING MORE CUSTOMERS.
WE HAVE TO INCREASE VIBRANCY AND WE HAVE TO SUPPORT THEM
IN EVERY WAY TO DO THIS. PROTECTIONS THAT COULD CAUSE
UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES AND I AND I DO THINK IT'S UNINTENDED.
I DON'T THINK ANYBODY'S TRYING TO HURT ANYBODY HERE.
SO I WOULDN'T SAY THAT. BUT WE HAVE TO CREATE MORE
VIBRANCY, MORE CUSTOMERS, MORE EXCITEMENT HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> SUPERVISOR CHAN, MY
APOLOGIES. PRESENT AMENDMENTS SINCE
AND WITH ALL DUE RESPECT TO A SUPERVISOR CHERYL, I MUST SAY
THAT THIS ACTUALLY CAME FROM YOU KNOW, BASED ON IN FACT
IN YOUR DISTRICT. >> LOT MEDITERRANEAN
AND ANOTHER JAPANESE RESTAURANTS THAT'S BEEN A
LEGACY BUSINESS 3040 YEARS ON FILLMORE AND WAS ACTUALLY
BOUGHT UP BY BILLIONAIRE. ON THE BLOCK AND CREATE A LOT
OF ANXIETY AND IN FACT BECAUSE OF THE INTERIM ZONING CONTROL
OF THIS VERY SAME LEGISLATION SEE YOU THAT ONE OF THEM GET TO
STAY AND BE ABLE TO HAVE THE LEVERAGE TO NEGOTIATE.
AND IT'S BEEN A GREAT BUSINESS ON THE BLOCK FOR A LONG TIME
AND YOU KNOW AND IN FACT THEY NOW HAVE A SECOND SHOP
SOMEWHERE YOU KNOW, SOMEWHERE ELSE IN THE CITY.
BUT SO IT HAS PROVEN THAT AS IT WORKED THERE'S NOTHING HERE TO
STOP. SMALL BUSINESS TO MOVE INTO THE
STORE FRONT AND YOU STILL ALSO HAVE FORMULA RETAIL CAN COME
IN IN FACT MANY FORMULA RETAIL HAS THE RESOURCES AND THE
LEVERAGE WHETHER IS ONCE YOU OR TO SEE YOU.
>> BUT AGAIN I THINK THERE'S VERY LITTLE AT ALL AT THIS
MOMENT. MECHANISM TO PROTECT SMALL
BUSINESS. AND LEGACY BUSINESS AND THERE'S
NOTHING TO STOP THE FOOT TRAFFIC OR SMALL BUSINESS TO
FILL UP THE STORE FRONT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU, PRESIDENT GENTLEMAN I JUST WANT
TO CENTER I'M SUPPORTING THIS ORDINANCE BUT WHAT I WANT TO
CENTER IT'S THERE'S BEEN A LOT OF GAPS IN BETWEEN PROTECTIONS
AND SUPPORT SO. >> SO OUR SMALL BUSINESS IS
DEFINITELY A VALUE TO SAN FRANCISCO BUT WHEN WE LOOK AT
THE BIGGER CONTEXT OF EVERYTHING THAT WE ARE TRYING
TO DO IN OUR CITY CURRENTLY, I THINK THIS LEGISLATION JUST
PROVIDES AN ADDITIONAL LAYER OF PROTECTION TO OUR LEGACY
BUSINESS. WE ARE TALKING ABOUT LEGACY
BUSINESS A BUSINESS THAT HAS INVESTED IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD
FOR HOW MANY YEARS? >> HOW MANY?
YES. DO YOU HAVE TO OPERATE AS A
BUSINESS TO QUALIFY TO BE A LEGACY BUSINESS?
>> SO I THINK THIS IS THE VALUE THE STORY.
>> WHAT? NEIGHBORHOOD LIGHT DISTRICT 11
IF WE CAN HAVE A LEGACY BUSINESS ITS CONTINUED
OPERATING AFTER 50 YEARS WE TOTALLY 100% CHERISH IT
AND ANYTHING THAT WE CAN DO AS MINIMAL AS A CEO TO MAKE SURE
THAT WE PROTECT THOSE BUSINESS .
>> I'M ALL FOR IT AND I THINK AND THIS IS WHAT MAKES MY
NEIGHBORHOOD THIS IS WHAT MAKES SAN FRANCISCO SPECIAL SO I AM
GOING TO SUPPORT THIS LEGISLATION.
>> THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, WE HAVE
A MOTION FROM SUPERVISOR CHAN SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR WALTON.
CAN WE TAKE THAT MOTION TO AMEND WITHOUT OBJECTION.
WITHOUT OBJECTION. >> THE MOTION PASSES AND THEN.
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU CALL THE ROLL ON THE AMENDED ORDINANCE
AND ITEM 30 FOUR AS AMENDED SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY NO.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER. FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD NO. SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I
RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR I MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER
SAUTER NO SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL NO SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
THERE ARE SIX EYES AND FOUR NOS WITH SUPERVISORS DORSEY MAHMOOD
SADR AND CHERYL. >> VOTING NO AND THE ORDINANCE
FAILS. ALL RIGHT LET'S GO TO OUR 230
SPECIAL ORDER YES AT 230 IT IS TIME FOR THE RECOGNITION OF
COMMENDATIONS FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY
OF SAN FRANCISCO AND FIRST UP DISTRICT NINE SUPERVISOR
FIELDER. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH,
PRESIDENT. GENTLEMEN, I'D LIKE TO INVITE
TO THE PODIUM THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR ONE OF THE CO-FOUNDERS
OF THE AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURE DISTRICT SHIRAZ SOUZA.
>> HE'S GOING UP IT IS AN HONOR DURING NATIVE AMERICAN HERITAGE
MONTH TO RECOGNIZE A POWERFUL WOMAN LEADER IN THE AMERICAN
INDIAN COMMUNITY. WHAT MAKES HER ACCOMPLISHMENT
EVEN MORE EXTRAORDINARY IS THAT SHE SUCCESSFULLY ORGANIZED
COMMUNITY MEMBERS, ADVANCE LEGISLATION AND LAY THE
FOUNDATION FOR A TRANSFORMATIVE CULTURE INSTITUTION AT A TIME
WHEN THE WORLD WAS SHUT DOWN DURING THE COVID 19 PANDEMIC
WHEN TRADITIONAL OUTREACH WAS NEARLY IMPOSSIBLE HER
DETERMINATION, CREATIVITY AND UNWAVERING COMMITMENT
ENSURED THAT SAN FRANCISCO'S FIRST EVER AMERICAN INDIAN
CULTURE DISTRICT NOT ONLY CAME TO LIFE BUT DID SO IN ONE OF
THE MOST CHALLENGING MOMENTS IN OUR CITY'S HISTORY.
AS A PROUD MEMBER OF THE TAOS PUEBLO YOU AND KIOWA PEOPLES
SHERIA HAS DEDICATED HER LIFE TO UPLIFTING AMERICAN INDIAN
COMMUNITIES AND ENSURING THAT NATIVE VOICES ARE HEARD,
RESPECTED AND REPRESENTED. SHE'S BEEN A CHAMPION FOR
FAIRNESS, EQUITABLE RESOURCE DISTRIBUTION FOR NATIVE
PEOPLES, PUSHING INSTITUTIONS TO RECOGNIZE THE LONG
OVERLOOKED NEEDS AND CONTRIBUTIONS OF OUR
COMMUNITIES IN OUR CITY INCLUDING ENSURING THAT WE ARE
RIGHTFULLY COUNTED. SHE WORKED CLOSELY WITH THE
CITY TO CORRECT YEARS OF UNDERCOUNTING THAT ONCE
REPORTED US AS ONLY 0.3% AND THEN 1.1% OF THE CITY'S
POPULATION. AFTER THE 2020 REDISTRICTING
DATA WAS REVIEWED IN THE WAKE OF HER ADVOCACY, THE TRUTH
EMERGED. NATIVE PEOPLE MAKE UP 2.1% OF
SAN FRANCISCO. THIS INCLUDES MORE THAN ABOUT
18,000 AMERICAN INDIANS WHO IDENTIFY AS NATIVE ALONG WITH
ANOTHER RACE AND 6475 WHO IDENTIFY AS NATIVE ALONE.
>> BECAUSE OF HER COMMITMENT OUR COMMUNITY IS NOW SEEN
ACKNOWLEDGED AND REPRESENTED WITH ACCURACY AND RESPECT.
SHE HAS WORKED TO ELEVATE NATIVE VOICES IN THE TECH
SECTOR, SUPPORT NATIVE YOUTH RETENTION, LED INSTITUTIONAL
AND NONPARTISAN RESEARCH AND GUIDED PROCESSES OF
CULTURE, TRIBAL CULTURAL RESOURCE PROTECTION
AND ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW AND LAND USE MEDIATION HER WORK
HAS HELPED NATIVE COMMUNITIES NAVIGATE TRIBAL CONSULTATION,
SEEK RECOGNITION AS NON FEDERALLY RECOGNIZED TRIBES
AND IDENTIFY MOST LIKELY DESCENDANTS IN THE SACRED TASK
OF REPATRIATING NATIVE AMERICAN ANCESTORS.
>> THROUGH HER LEADERSHIP SHE HAS INCREASED NATIVE VISIBILITY
AND POLITICAL REPRESENTATION ADVANCED PUBLIC ART
AND PLACEMAKING THROUGH INITIATIVES LIKE INDIGENOUS
S.F. AND HELPED ESTABLISH FORMAL LAND ACKNOWLEDGMENTS
LIKE THE ONE WE SAY AT THIS BOARD EVERY BOARD MEETING SHE
HAS EXPANDED COMMUNITY CENTER PROGRAMS LIKE THE CULTURAL
GARDENING AT BLACK POINT SUPPORT HISTORICAL TRUTH
TELLING THROUGH PROJECTS LIKE THE INDIGENOUS S.F. MAPPING
GENOCIDE PROJECT AND ADVOCATED FOR A CENTRAL COMMUNITY
INFRASTRUCTURE INCLUDING THE VILLAGE HOUSING VISION BY
SERVING ON NUMEROUS CITY ADVISORY GROUPS AND BUILDING
STRONG COALITIONS OF ELDERS YOUTH TO SPIRIT LEADERS
AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATIONS. SHREYA HAS HELPED CREATE
AND RECOGNIZE AND THRIVING CULTURAL DISTRICT THAT
PRESERVES HERITAGE, STRENGTHENS COMMUNITY AND ENSURES
AND INDIGENOUS VOICES ARE DEEPLY EMBEDDED IN THE FUTURE
OF SAN FRANCISCO. WHAT MAKES RAY'S LEADERSHIP SO
REMARKABLE IS NOT JUST THE BREADTH OF HER WORK BUT ALSO
THE SPIRIT BEHIND IT. >> SHE LEADS WITH CLARITY, WITH
COURAGE AND WITH A PROFOUND SENSE OF RESPONSIBILITY TO HER
ANCESTORS AND FUTURE GENERATIONS.
SHE REMINDS US THAT CULTURAL PRESERVATION IS NOT ONLY ABOUT
HONORING THE PAST BUT ABOUT BUILDING A JUST AND THRIVING
FUTURE. THANK YOU SHARON, FOR YOUR
UNWAVERING DEDICATION AND YOUR EXTRAORDINARY LEADERSHIP
AND YOUR LIFELONG COMMITMENT TO UPLIFTING OUR PEOPLE
AND CULTURES. BEFORE YOU GO AHEAD MY
COLLEAGUES WANT TO SING YOUR PRAISES AS WELL.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR. >> I THANK YOU SO MUCH.
FIRST, THANK YOU SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR RECOGNIZING AT
AWESOMENESS. AND I HAVE HAD THE GREAT
PLEASURE OF WORKING WITH SHREYA ON A COUPLE OF THINGS.
AND I HAVE LONG ADMIRED HER PARTICULAR COMBINATION OF GRACE
ELEGANCE AND FIERCENESS THE PASSION THAT SHE BRINGS TO YOU
UPLIFTING THE COMMUNITY. >> HER LEADERSHIP IN TRUTH
AND HEALING FOR THE COMMUNITY AND ALSO HER STICK TO ITIVENESS
IN MAKING SURE THAT GREAT DOLLARS END UP WITH THE
COMMUNITY. I HAVE SO MUCH ADMIRATION FOR
YOU SURYA HOW YOU ARE SHINING A LIGHT AND LEADING THE PATH FOR
OTHERS. IT IS SO IMPORTANT TO HAVE ROLE
MODELS AND PEOPLE SHINE AS BRIGHT AS YOU WITH SUCH
INTELLIGENCE AND GRACE. SO I AM SO GLAD THAT YOU'RE
HERE WITH US. LEADING THIS WORK IN SAN
FRANCISCO AND WILL ALWAYS SUPPORT YOUR EFFORTS.
AND I JUST SO ADMIRE YOU AND I'M GLAD THAT WE ARE DOING
THIS COMMENDATION. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUPERVISOR CHERYL DREA.
FIRST OF ALL, THANK YOU FOR BEING YOU AND FOR BEING THE
LEADER THAT YOU ARE. YOU MAKE OUR CITY BETTER EVERY
DAY AND SUPERVISOR FIELDER, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR
RECOGNIZING A LEADER LIKE SHREYA.
SUPERVISORS MELGAR AND FIELDER SPOKE A LOT ABOUT YOUR
LEADERSHIP ACROSS THE CITY BUT I JUST WANT TO SAY LEADERSHIP
TYPE ACTS OUT IN BIG WAYS ACROSS COMMUNITIES BUT ALSO
IN LITTLE WAYS AND THE COMMUNITY AT FORT MASON WHERE
YOU ARE BASED EACH AND EVERY DAY LOVES YOU.
AND I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU FOR BEING SUCH A WONDERFUL PART
OF DISTRICT TWO AND AND WHEN THE NEIGHBORS SPEAK OUT ABOUT
HOW MUCH JOY AND COMMUNITY YOU'VE BROUGHT TO EVEN JUST A
FEW OFFICERS AROUND YOU, I THINK THAT DESERVES JUST AS
MUCH CELEBRATION AS YOUR LEADERSHIP ACROSS OUR LARGER
COMMUNITY AND I THINK IT SPEAKS VOLUMES ABOUT WHO YOU ARE
AND THE ORGANIZATION THAT YOU BUILT AND THE MOVEMENT THAT
YOU'RE LEADING. SO THANK YOU SO MUCH.
AND I JUST WOULD LIKE TO ECHO THE COMMENTS OF MY COLLEAGUES
AND AS THE DISTRICT EIGHT SUPERVISOR WHO GETS TO HAVE A
LITTLE BIT OF A CULTURAL DISTRICT IN DISTRICT EIGHT
AND IT'S BEEN A GREAT PRIVILEGE TO BE ABLE TO WORK WITH YOU
AND THE CULTURAL DISTRICT THESE LAST HOWEVER MANY YEARS.
SO CONGRATULATIONS. >> WELL DESERVED AND THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER I DON'T KNOW HOW THIS THING WORKS BUT I'LL
DO THE PUEBLO RIGHT THING. THANK YOU SO MUCH SUPERVISOR
FIELDER IT'S AN HONOR TO HAVE ANOTHER NATIVE AMERICAN WOMAN
SUPERVISOR SITTING UP THERE AND GIVING THIS COMMENDATION IT
I'M TRULY GRATEFUL TO SEE YOU SITTING UP THERE AND ACTING,
YOU KNOW, AS AS AN EXAMPLE OF WHAT CAN BE FOR OUR YOUNG
PEOPLE AND FOR MYSELF EVEN THOUGH I WON'T BE SITTING UP
THERE AND SUPERVISOR MELGAR, YOU KNOW FOR AUTHORING THE
RESOLUTION ON TRUTH AND HEALING REPARATIONS ADVISORY COMMITTEE
WAS WAS REALLY STRONG AND REALLY POWERFUL AND I HOPE
WE CONTINUE TO BACK THAT AND CARRY THAT ON AND ALL
YOU'VE DONE TO BRING FORTH NATIVE AMERICAN COMMENDATIONS
LAST YEAR IN HONORING MARY AND JUST INCLUDING THE NATIVE
COMMUNITY TRULY APPRECIATE WORKING FOR AND BRING US OUT OF
TWIN PEAKS YOU KNOW TO TO RUN PROJECTS OUT THERE WITH OUR
STEWARDSHIP PROGRAM AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHERYL FOR
ACKNOWLEDGING MY WORK AS WELL. >> I JUST WANTED TO SAY AS
JACKIE KIND OF CENTERED IT WASN'T EASY STARTING OFF
AND DOING THE WORK THAT WE DID. >> YOU KNOW A LOT OF PEOPLE
ASKED IN FIVE YEARS AND A LOT OF OUR COMMUNITIES AND IT'S
SUCH AN HONOR TO SIT HERE TODAY WITH MANY OF THE LEADERS
AND THE ELDERS THAT ACTUALLY GUIDED THE WORK THAT WE DO
AND THE REASON WHY WE HAVE THIS CULTURAL DISTRICT WE STARTED
IN THE PANDEMIC I REMEMBER SITTING UP I HAD GOTTEN HERE I
WORKED FOR A NATIVE AMERICAN HERITAGE COMMISSION FOR ALMOST
FIVE YEARS WORKING ON TRIBAL CULTURAL RESOURCES AND HUMAN
REMAINS. >> AND WHEN I CAME TO THE CITY
I THOUGHT OH MY GOSH, I'M JUST GOING TO WORK IN TECH.
AND I WENT TO TWITTER AND STARTED THE FIRST
INDIGENOUS GROUP THERE AND STARTED THE FIRST NATIVE
HASHTAG EMOJI EAGLE FEATHER EMOJI AND BROUGHT AN APRIL
AND MORNING STAR TO DO THE FIRST EVER NATIVE AMERICAN
PANEL THAT WENT OFF AT TWITTER. SO I THINK IT WAS KIND OF
CALLING ME BACK AND I HAD A MET APRIL THROUGH THE CULTURAL
CENTER AS A NO NO NO I'LL JUST VOLUNTEER AND SHE GOES NO, COME
ON SAYS COME WORK WITH US AND STOOD BY MY SIDE SIDE BY
SIDE ALONG WITH DEBBIE, MARY JEAN AND A LOT OF OUR OTHER
COMMUNITY MEMBERS IN ORDER TO BUILD THE AMERICAN INDIAN
CULTURAL DISTRICT. >> BUT THIS HASN'T BEEN AN EASY
FEAT. WE DIDN'T START OUT LIKE MY
SISTERS JAPANTOWN OR CHI CULTURAL DISTRICT WHERE WE'VE
BEEN AROUND FOR 27 YEARS. WE HAD TO START OUT A LOT OF
OUR WORK LIKE THE SUPERVISOR SHARED, JUST PROVING THAT WE
WEREN'T 0.2% OF THE POPULATION YOU KNOW THAT WE HAD TO USE
NATIVE DATA TO IDENTIFY OVER 18,000 AMERICAN INDIANS.
>> WE HAD TO IDENTIFY IN THE HOUSING FOR THE VERY FIRST TIME
IN FIVE YEARS THAT AMERICAN INDIANS WERE THE THIRD.
THIS IS THE THIRD LARGEST RELOCATION CITY SAN FRANCISCO
IS AND IF YOU WERE TO RE HOUSE ALL AMERICAN INDIANS THAT ARE
UNHOUSED AT THE TIME WE DID THE DATA YOU WOULD INCREASE OUR
POPULATION BY 10%. WE HAD THE THIRD LARGEST
UNSOLVED MISSING MURDERED INDIGENOUS CASES PEOPLE IN THE
UNITED STATES RIGHT WE ARE RIGHT HERE ON ALAMO ON
RAMAKRISHNA LONELY LAND AND THERE ARE STILL SOURCES
THAT BELIEVE THAT AMERICAN INDIANS AREN'T ALIVE.
>> SO A LOT OF THAT EARLY WORK THIS GETTING TO THIS POINT WAS
SIX HOUR WEEKS. IT WAS IT WAS BEING BEAT DOWN.
IT WAS BEING HUMBLED. IT WASN'T EASY AND FACING OVER
250 K BUDGET CUTS AND WORKING THIS YEAR WITH TWO STAFF
CURRENTLY ON A BUDGET OF LESS THAN 700,000 TO DO WHAT WE DO
HAS BEEN A KICK IN THE GUTS TO THE WORK AND THE PROGRESS THAT
WE'VE MADE. >> SO THIS WORK HAS NOT BEEN
EASY RIGHT AND WHERE WE GOT HAS NOT BEEN EASY AND WE SPENT THE
FIRST FIVE YEARS I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK GOODNESS TO THE
COMMITTEE MEMBERS AND THE LEADERS HERE IN THIS ROOM.
THE FIRST FIVE YEARS WE SPENT DOING THE NATIVE AMERICAN
HERITAGE MONTH RESOLUTION AS WAS NOTED WITH THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WORKING WITH THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION ON THE
FIRST EVER LAND ACKNOWLEDGMENT RESOLUTION AND NOW IT'S GONE
THROUGHOUT THE CITY AS WELL IN LEADERSHIP WITH THE
ASSOCIATION OF RHEUMATOLOGY WORKED WITH SUPERVISOR MELGAR
AND THE TRUTH AND HEALING REPARATIONS ADVISORY COMMITTEE
INITIATIVE. WHAT IS THAT?
THE IDEA IS TO DEVELOP A COMMITTEE THAT CREATES A TEN
YEAR COMPREHENSIVE PLAN TO ADDRESS THE INEQUITIES THAT
EXIST WITHIN THE AMERICAN INDIAN COMMUNITY IN SAN
FRANCISCO WE ALSO WORKED ON A HEALTH DISPARITIES RESOLUTION
WITH ALL OF THE HEALTH ORGS, THE CULTURAL CENTER
AND FRIENDSHIP HOUSE, THE AMERICA HEALTH CENTER,
INDIGENOUS JUSTICE MANY, MANY OTHERS ON OUR LEADERSHIP
COUNCIL AS WELL AS TWO CULTURAL DISTRICTS EXPANSIONS AND MORE
RECENTLY THANK YOU FOR THE SUPERVISORS THAT WERE ABLE TO
JOIN US. WE WERE NOMINATED AS
SEMIFINALIST FOR STATE RECOGNITION FOR THE CALIFORNIA
ARTS COUNCIL PROGRAM. >> SO IN FIVE YEARS A LOT OF
THAT WORK THAT WE HAVE DONE HAS BEEN AROUND RECOGNITION
AND JUST BEING YOU KNOW, HAVING TO SAY AGAIN WE'RE STILL HERE
AS AMERICAN INDIANS AND FIGHT THAT FIGHT.
>> SO THE LAST THING I JUST WANTED TO SHARE IS OUR
INDIGENOUS ASSET PROGRAM. WE'VE BEEN RUNNING WITH THE
AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL CENTER, OUR MAPPING GENOCIDE
PROJECT WHICH WE'RE EXCITED TO KICK OFF OUR GALA WITH THE SAN
FRANCISCO ARTS COMMISSION TOMORROW NOVEMBER 19TH TO BRING
AWARENESS TO SAN FRANCISCO, THE SAN FRANCISCO ARTS COMMISSION
ON THAT WORK AND ALSO OUR COMMUNITY LAND STEWARDS
PROGRAM. WE HAVE A LOT OF OUR STEWARDS
HERE. >> WE'VE BEEN SUPPORTING BLACK
POINT FOR NEARLY FIVE YEARS NOW AS WELL AS OTHER AREAS SUCH AS
THE PRESIDIO THROUGHOUT THE CITY AND DOING THE COMMUNITY
AMBASSADORS FOOD PROGRAM AS WELL AS OUR AMERICAN INDIAN
CULTURAL DISTRICT YOUNG LEADERS COUNCIL AND THAT'S JUST SOME OF
THE ACHIEVEMENTS THAT SOME OF MY LEADERSHIP MEMBERS HERE HAVE
BEEN ABLE TO COME TOGETHER AND DO IN THE LAST FIVE YEARS.
AND I JUST WANT TO DO A QUICK SPECIAL THANK YOU TO APRIL
MCGILL WHO'S IN HERE WHO'S THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE
AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL CENTER FOR BELIEVING ME AND BEING
CRAZY ENOUGH TO EXPLAIN CRAZY TO TO TRUST ME TO BE HERE
BECAUSE WHEN I CAME HERE IN 2019 AND I FIRST SAT
IN THESE CHAMBERS AND I CAME WITH HER MEETING AFTER MEETING
SHE SAT UP HERE PROTESTING AND PROTESTING AND I SAID
APRIL, WHERE IS EVERYBODY? AND SHE NEVER MISSED A MEETING
AND SHE NEVER, YOU KNOW, MISSED AN OPPORTUNITY TO HOLD PEOPLE
ACCOUNTABLE AND SHE STOOD AS A ROLE MODEL FOR ME AND WHY I'M
ABLE TO DO THAT TODAY. AND I ALSO WANT TO THANK JOYA
WHO IS FROM THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING COMMITTEE
DEVELOPMENT IN 2019 WHEN WE STARTED IT WAS THE PANDEMIC
AND EVERYBODY SAID NO DON'T YOU DON'T HAVE A CHANCE.
>> WE EVEN HAD A SUPERVISOR UP HERE WHO WAS NATIVE WHO SAID
DON'T DO IT. IT'S NOT LIKELY I DON'T THINK
THERE'S MANY OTHER THINGS THAT ARE HAPPENING IN THE CITY RIGHT
NOW AND I DON'T THINK YOU STAND A CHANCE BUT YOU SHOULD TRY
NEXT YEAR WHEN IT COMES OUT AND THINGS ARE IN BETTER
POSITION. I CALLED JULIA SHE SAID NO
SINCE YOU NEED THIS, YOUR PEOPLE NEED THIS, YOU DESERVE
THIS. >> AND EVEN THOUGH WE LINED UP
36 PEOPLE ON THE LINE AND IT WAS THE VERY FIRST DAY OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MEETING IN THE PANDEMIC AND THEY SAID
NOBODY WAS ON THE LINE BECAUSE THEY DIDN'T EVEN KNOW HOW TO
USE THE PHONE DURING THAT TIME .
BUT SOMEHOW BY THE GRACE OF CREATOR IT PASSED AND ALSO THE
HARD WORK OF PEOPLE. AND THANK YOU ALSO TO MARY
TRAVIS ALLEN. MY LEADERSHIP COUNCIL PRESIDENT
WHO EVEN THROUGH TIMES WHEN SHE DIDN'T THINK I LISTENED TO HER
AGREED SHE STOOD BY MY SIDE AND GUIDED ME TO DO THINGS
IN THE RIGHT WAY. >> THANK YOU MARY, WHEREVER YOU
ARE AND ALSO TO MARY JEAN ROBERTSON CARPIO NATIVE VOICES
OF 50 YEARS WHO CAME TOGETHER AND PUT THE MAP TOGETHER FOR
THE AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL DISTRICT AND I KNOW RIGHT NOW
SHE'S SAYING TALK SLOWER SO I CAN HEAR YOU OR SLOW IT DOWN
AND BUT I'M TRYING TO GO FASTER SO I CAN GET YOU ALL IN THERE
AND DEBBIE IS WELL, DEBBIE HAS BEEN COMING OUT AND REACHING
OUT TO OUR COMMUNITY AND ACTUALLY PUT TOGETHER THE
INFORMATION WHEN I CAME IN IN 2019 THAT CREATED THE
LEGISLATION FOR THE AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL DISTRICT AND NO
MATTER WHAT, SHE ALWAYS MAKES SURE THAT ALL THESE COMMUNITY
MEMBERS SHOW UP TO ALL OF OUR EVENT.
AND LAST BUT NOT LEAST THE LAST YEAR I'D LIKE TO RECOGNIZE OUR
GREG CASTER OR ASSOCIATION OR TRICIA LONEY RELATIVE AND THE
ARROW FOR ALLOWING US TO DO THIS IN A GOOD WAY.
IT IS VERY ODD TO HAVE AN AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL
DISTRICT ON NATIVE AMERICAN LAND AND NOT DO IT IN A GOOD
WAY IN PARTNERSHIP. >> AND LAST BUT NOT LEAST I
JUST WANT TO RECOGNIZE ALL OF MY AICD LEADERSHIP COUNCIL
MEMBERS. I WILL NOT READ WELL I DON'T
KNOW WHAT MY TIME IS BUT I WILL NOT READ ALL OF THEIR NAMES BUT
I COULD NOT DO THAT WITHOUT ALL 15 OF THEM INCLUDING FOLKS
IN THE CULTURAL CONSERVANCY. BARRY AMERICAN INDIAN TWO
SPIRITS AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL CENTER WE HAVE CRYSTAL
WALLPAPER FROM WALLPAPERS KITCHEN WE HAVE NATIVE AMERICAN
HEALTH CENTER ASSOCIATION, BRITISH COLONIAL SAN FRANCISCO
U.S. INDIAN EDUCATION PROGRAM, FRIENDSHIP HOUSE ASSOCIATION OF
AMERICAN INDIANS. WE HAVE OUR YOUNG LEADERS
COUNCIL WE HAVE OUR ELECTED ELDER CHAIR ARE TO SPIRIT
AND AN LGBTQ CHAIR AND OUR ELDER ELECTED CHAIR AND SO I
COULD NOT DO IT WITHOUT ALL OF THOSE PEOPLE AND I JUST THANK
YOU VERY MUCH FOR COMING TOGETHER AND LAST BUT NOT
LEAST, I DON'T KNOW IF ALL OF YOU KNOW THIS AND WHAT WE'VE
ACHIEVED. I HAVE TO STAFF THEY'VE BEEN
HERE FIVE MONTHS AND THEY ARE COMPLETE ROCK STARS AND I
REALLY HOPE I CAN GET THE SUPPORT OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS TO GROW IT TO A THIRD BECAUSE WE CAN'T CONTINUE
TO DO WHAT WE DO AND MAKE THIS WORK HAPPEN WITHOUT THAT
SUPPORT. ONE OF MY STAFF TODAY COULDN'T
EVEN BE HERE BECAUSE SHE WAS JUST OVERWHELMED BY THE AMOUNT
OF STUFF THAT SHE HAD. SHE HAD TO LEAVE AND GO HOME
AND SO IT'S REALLY SAD TO SEE THAT HAPPEN AND THAT WE HAVE TO
COME TOGETHER AND SAY YOU ALL NEED A PLAN TO GIVE THAT
SUPPORT. BUT I REALLY HOPE YOU CONSIDER
THAT WHEN YOU LOOK AT FUNDING FOR A CULTURAL DISTRICT.
>> SO THANK YOU TO EACH AND EVERY ONE OF THESE ELDERS
AND LEADERS HERE TODAY THAT HAVE HAVE BACKED US FOR THE
SUPPORT IN ORDER TO BE HERE AND WE ARE EXCITED AND HONORED
THAT WE HAVE THIS LEVEL OF SUPPORT FOR NATIVE AMERICAN
HERITAGE MONTH. >> SO THANK YOU.
>> LOOKS LIKE THERE'S A PHOTO GOING ON IN THE ROTUNDA, I AM
GUESSING. ALL RIGHT.
SO WE'RE GOING TO LET THE CULTURAL DISTRICT FOLKS MAYBE
WORK THEIR WAY OUT AND THEN WE'LL CALL OUR NEXT HONOREE.
ALL RIGHT. AND FOR FOLKS WHO MAY BE HERE
FOR OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER, WE GOT A LOT OF COMMENDATIONS
TO GET THERE SO IT'S GOING TO BE A LITTLE WHILE.
>> DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, PRESIDENT
MADAM IN I WOULD LIKE TO CALL UP PHIL ANDREOTTI.
>> THERE HE IS. >> COLLEAGUES, TODAY I AM
HONORED TO RECOGNIZE A TRUE SAN FRANCISCO INSTITUTION ONE THAT
HAS FOR GENERATIONS BROUGHT NEIGHBORS TOGETHER AND HELPED
SHAPE THE CULTURE AND CHARACTER OF OUR CITY FOR HALF A CENTURY.
WE ARE HERE TO CELEBRATE GOAT HILL PIZZA ON HIS 50TH
ANNIVERSARY, GOAT HILL PIZZA OPENED ITS DOORS IN 1975
AND PETRILLO HILL LONG BEFORE MANY OF THE CHANGES WE'VE SEEN
ACROSS THE CITY. BUT THROUGH EVERY SHIFT
AND CHALLENGE GOLD HILL HAS REMAINED A CONSTANT A PLACE
ROOTED IN COMMUNITY TRADITION AND THE SAN FRANCISCO WE ALL
KNOW AND LOVE FOR 50 YEARS. GOLDHILL PIZZA HAS BEEN MORE
THAN A RESTAURANT. IT HAS BEEN A GATHERING PLACE,
A FAMILY SPOT, A NEIGHBORHOOD STAPLE THAT HAS WELCOMED
LONGTIME RESIDENTS, NEW FAMILIES AND VISITORS WITH THAT
UNMISTAKABLE SALVADOR CRUST THAT ONLY SAN FRANCISCO CAN
CLAIM. BUT WHAT MAKES GOLDHILL SPECIAL
ISN'T JUST THE FOOD. IT'S THE COMMITMENT TO
COMMUNITY FROM SUPPORTING LOCAL SCHOOLS AND NONPROFITS TO
SHOWING UP FOR NEIGHBORHOOD EVENTS.
GOLDHILL PIZZA HAS ALWAYS GIVEN BACK TO THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE
KEPT THEM THRIVING. THEIR WORK REFLECTS THE VALUES
THAT MAKE OUR NEIGHBORHOODS STRONG WITH CONNECTION,
CONSISTENCY AND CARE. SMALL BUSINESSES LIKE GOLD HILL
PIZZA ARE THE HEART OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THEY HOLD OUR STORIES AND OUR NEIGHBORHOODS AND REMIND US
WHAT COMMUNITY TRULY LOOKS LIKE.
REACHING 50 YEARS AND STILL BEING FAMILY FRIENDLY COMMUNITY
CENTERED AND PROUDLY LOCAL IS AN INCREDIBLE ACHIEVEMENT.
SO TODAY I WANT TO EXTEND OUR DEEPEST APPRECIATION
AND CONGRATULATE GOLD HILL PIZZA ON THIS MILESTONE
ANNIVERSARY. THANK YOU FOR YOUR DEDICATION
FOR YOUR SERVICE AND FOR CONTINUING TO REPRESENT WHAT
MAKES SAN FRANCISCO SO SPECIAL. HERE'S TO 50 YEARS OF SOUR
DOUGH SERVICE AND COMMUNITY AND MANY MORE TO GO.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SURPRISE WALTON MEMBERS.
WELL, THANK YOU FOR THIS HONOR AND RECOGNITION.
AS YOU KNOW, WE ARE A LEGACY BUSINESS AND WE THANK YOU ALSO
FOR THE GREAT NATION OF THAT PROGRAM WHICH HAS BEEN A GREAT
HELP TO US IN SERVING THE COMMUNITY AND BEING RECOGNIZED
BY OUR COMMUNITY. >> I WANT TO INTRODUCE TO YOU
MY PARTNERS WHO ARE WITH ME JOEL LIPSKI, MICHAEL MAHONEY
AND DEBBIE HUDSON. >> RIGHT.
WE ARE IN SOME FORM OR ANOTHER THE SAME FIVE PEOPLE THAT
STARTED THE RESTAURANT 50 YEARS AGO AND WE'RE JUST THRILLED TO
HAVE BEEN ABLE TO BE OF SERVICE AND USE TO THIS CITY AND COUNTY
OF SAN FRANCISCO. WE THANK OF COURSE THE BOARD
AND WE THANK SPEAKER EMERITA NANCY PELOSI WHO CAME LAST WEEK
TO HONOR US DURING OUR HILL HISTORY NIGHT WHICH SOME OF YOU
MAY HAVE HEARD ABOUT THAT APPEARS 70 A NEW AREA FOR
GROWTH IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> AND WE WERE HONORED THERE BY
THE PORTER HILL ARCHIVE PROJECT FOR OUR 50 YEARS AND SPEAKER
EMERITA AND HER HUSBAND CAME TO CELEBRATE WITH US AND FOR THAT
WE WERE MOST GRATEFUL AND HONORED.
>> WE ARE GRATEFUL ALSO TO OUR PARTNERS IN THE POTRERO HILL
NEIGHBORHOOD IN BUSINESS THE MERCHANT COMMUNITY WHICH AS A
COMMUNITY IS SUPPORTIVE OF EACH OTHER THROUGH OUR PETRO
DOGPATCH MERCHANT ORGANIZATION WHICH ENABLES US TO WORK
TOGETHER TO SUPPORT BUSINESSES IN THE DOGPATCH POTRERO
COMMUNITY. FURTHERMORE, I'D LIKE TO THANK
THE STAFF OF GOAT HILL PIZZA FOR ALL OF THE INCREDIBLE WORK
THEY'VE DONE OVER THE 50 YEARS OF OUR EXISTENCE AND PROBABLY
AND MOST IMPORTANTLY I WANT TO THANK THE COMMUNITY OF POTRERO
HILL DOGPATCH AND THE REST OF SAN FRANCISCO WHO SUPPORTED US
THROUGHOUT OUR 50 YEARS AND IN 20 12 WE MOVED IN TO WEST
PORTAL FOR A SECOND BRANCH OF OUR OPERATION.
AND WE THANK THE WEST PORTAL COMMUNITY FOR THE SUPPORT IT'S
GIVEN US SINCE THAT TIME. >> THANK YOU.
RISE OR MELT. >> SO WITHOUT THANK YOU.
THAT'S ALL I CAN SAY. WE'RE HAPPY TO BE HERE
AND GRATEFUL TO YOU FOR YOUR SUPPORT OF SMALL BUSINESS
AND LEGACY BUSINESS. >> THANK YOU.
>> THAT'S IT. THAT'S.
CONGRATULATIONS. >> THANK.
>> NEXT UP. DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR CHEN.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT. >> AND MAY I HAVE MR. SASSY
COMES TO THE PODIUM PLEASE? >> THANK YOU.
CAN SASSY IS A NOVEL TINY FROM NEW MEXICO.
>> HE SAID DISTRICT 11 RESIDENTS AND CITY EMPLOYEES AS
SAN FRANCISCO SFO SAN FRANCISCO AIRPORT MUSEUM.
>> HE GREW UP IN FARMINGTON, A BORDER TOWN OFF THE RESERVATION
WHERE HIS PARENTS WERE BORN AND RAISED TRADITIONAL AND THEN
NAVAJO ON THE NAVAJO RESERVATION.
THEY DECIDED TO RAISE THEIR CHILDREN NONTRADITIONAL BECAUSE
OF THEIR BOARDING SCHOOL EXPERIENCE.
>> BEFORE MOVING TO SAN FRANCISCO, AL CAN WORK AT THE
SMITHSONIAN INSTITUTION IN WASHINGTON DC AND THE
NATIONAL MUSEUM OF AMERICAN INDIAN IN NEW YORK CITY.
SINCE 1998 HE HAS WORKED AT SFO MUSEUM MANAGED MANAGING KNOWN
OBJECTS FOR EXHIBITIONS THROUGHOUT THE AIRPORT
TERMINALS. IN 2005.
>> HE BECAME THE REGISTRAR FOR THE AVIATION COLLECTIONS
UTILIZING HIS VAST KNOWLEDGE OF AVIATION HISTORY AND AIRLINE
CORPORATE IDENTITY TO CATALOG AND PRESERVE SFO MUSEUM'S
COLLECTION FOR OVER TWO HUNDRED 80,000 OBJECTS SPANNING THE
DEVELOPMENT OF COMMERCIAL AVIATION ACROSS THE PACIFIC RIM
AND BEYOND IN COMMUNITY. >> KEN HAS SUPPORTED THE
AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL CENTER FRIENDSHIP HOUSE AND THE NATIVE
AMERICAN HEALTH CENTER. HE PARTICIPATED IN THE REMOVAL
OF THE PIONEER MONUMENT AND ATTENDED THE SUNRISE
CEREMONIES ON OUR TRACKS IN REMEMBRANCE OF THE OCCUPIED
OCCUPATIONS OF ACT OCCUPATIONS OF ALCATRAZ AND IN SOLIDARITY
WITH THE MURDER AND MISSING INDIGENOUS WOMAN.
>> AT SFO HE SPEARHEADED EFFORTS TO RECOGNIZE
AND CELEBRATE THE CONTRIBUTIONS OF NATIVE AND INDIGENOUS
COMMUNITY TO EMPLOYEE RESOURCES GROUP EVENTS.
WHAT S.F. OWES LAND RECOGNITION CEREMONY AFTER ROMA TISHA ALONI
. IT IS MY GREAT HONOR TODAY TO
RECOGNIZE KENYA AZIZ. >> LONGSTANDING COMMITMENT
AND DEDICATION AND DEDICATION TOWARDS HONORING THE LEGACY OF
NATIVE AMERICANS IN THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY AREA BAY AREA.
>> THROUGHOUT PRESERVING CULTURE, VOLUNTEERING AND YOUR
GENEROUS SUPPORT AND CULTURAL AND CULTURAL EVENTS.
>> THANK YOU. >> AND BEFORE YOU SPEAK
SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU PRESIDENT MENEM AND I JUST
REALLY QUICKLY WANTED TO TO THANK YOU FOR ALL OF YOUR
SERVICE AND THANK YOU FOR MAKING OUR AMERICAN INDIAN
COMMUNITY PROUD FOR YOUR MANY CONTRIBUTIONS.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. CONGRATULATIONS.
>> THANK YOU. MY NAME IS KEN.
YES. AND YOU KNOW, I'VE WHEN I MOVED
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO BACK IN 98, I HAD NO IDEA WHAT WAS
ALL INTEL FOR ME TO BE PART OF ESPECIALLY WORKING AT SFO.
AND FIRST OF ALL, I WAS VERY, VERY HONORED AND PRIVILEGED
THAT I WAS SENT SETTING FOOT ON A REALLY VAST BUILDING AT THAT
TIME. AND SO I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR TEN I REALLY APPRECIATE YOU NOMINATING ME
AND ALSO THE COMMUNITY THAT THAT YOU HERE CLAPPING
AND BECAUSE WE NEED WE NATIVES ARE STILL HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO
AND AND IN CALIFORNIA AND WE STAND FOR WHO WE ARE AND IT
DOESN'T MATTER IF WE WERE BROUGHT UP TRADITIONALLY OR
NONTRADITIONAL. WE'RE STILL HERE.
AND YOU KNOW, I IT WAS HARD FOR ME TO TO GROWING UP IT WAS
REALLY HARD FOR ME TO SEE HOW THE NATIVE WAS BROUGHT.
THE NATIVE PERSON WAS SEEN ESPECIALLY AS A LITTLE KID
BECAUSE THE TV WAS MY BABYSITTER AND AND SO I SAW THE
NATIVE AS THE SAVAGE THE ALCOHOLIC, THE SIDEKICK YOU
KNOW, ALWAYS THE SECOND PLACE KIND OF STANCE, YOU KNOW YOU
KNOW ALL THESE CHARACTERS AND SO NOW BEING BEING THIS
INDIVIDUAL HERE STANDING IN FRONT OF YOU I AM NAVAJO
AND SAN FRANCISCO OF ALL PLACES IS THE ONLY PLACE THAT I HAD TO
STAND THAT THE QUESTION WAS ARE YOU 100%?
I'M FROM NEW MEXICO OR I GRADUATED FROM UNIVERSITY OF
COLORADO IN BOULDER, COLORADO. I TRANSFERRED OVER TO AN
INTERNSHIP IN WASHINGTON D.C. THEN I WENT UP TO NEW YORK CITY
OF ALL THE DIFFERENT PLACES I, I CAME FROM LIVED AT THAT TIME
IN MY YOUNG LIFE WHEN I SAID I WAS NAVAJO THEY THEY THEY SAID
OH OKAY GREAT. YOU KNOW, THAT'S GREAT.
YOU KNOW, THANK YOU FOR COMING. YOU KNOW IT'S GREAT TO BE WITH
YOU KIND OF THING. BUT HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO NOT
ALL THE TIME THOUGH I WAS MISTAKEN AS ASIAN AND IT WAS
REALLY HARD. I MEAN BECAUSE EVERYONE THOUGHT
I WAS FILIPINO AND I SPOKE THAT I WAS TOO FRIENDLY.
I OPENED DOORS FOR THE LADIES. I SAID PLEASE, I THINK YOU
AND IT'S LIKE YOU KNOW WHEN I HEARD THAT ARE YOU 100% IT
REALLY BOTHERED ME AND EVERY ONCE IN A WHILE I GET THAT
QUESTION AGAIN ARE YOU 100%? AND NOW MY ANSWER IS I USED TO
BE 100% BECAUSE NOW I HAVE TO KNEE REPLACEMENT AND I HAVE
SOME CROWNS SO I'M LIKE 88 POINT 9%.
>> SO AT ANY RATE I REALLY BUT I'M STILL NAVAJO.
>> I JUST WANT TO SAY THANK YOU FOR THE MUSEUM SFO MUSEUM
BECAUSE I'VE LEARNED SO MUCH FROM BEING INVOLVED IN THE
COLLECTION OF THE MUSEUM. I DON'T KNOW.
I WISH THE MAYOR WAS STILL HERE.
I WANTED TO INVITE HIM TO SEE THE BACK ROOMS.
EVERYONE'S SEEN THE FRONT THE FOREFRONT, THE THE YOU KNOW,
INTERNATIONAL TERMINAL. BUT IF YOU GO INTO THE BACK
ROOM YOU SEE WHERE WE DO OUR WORK WHERE THE YOU KNOW HOW WE
PUT THESE EXHIBITS UP IN ALL THE DIFFERENT AREAS OF OF THE
AIRPORT AND WHERE I WORK IN THE PERMANENT COLLECTION OF
AIRLINES WHO WOULD WHO WOULD THINK A NATIVE WORKING IN THE
AIRLINE AREA OF HISTORY AND AND BE IN AND JUST LIKE I'M A
LITTLE KID IN A CANDY STORE I MEAN IT'S LIKE OH WOW THAT'S
PANAM THAT'S THAT'S UNITED YOU KNOW THAT AIR CAL OH MY GOSH WE
YOU KNOW GOT TO HAVE THAT YOU KNOW AND SO WITH THIS AND I
REALLY LOVE AIRLINE AND I AM NOW IN SEARCH OF NATIVES WHO
ARE AND WHO USED TO WORK FOR AIRLINES TODAY WE'RE UNITED YOU
KNOW AIR CAL ON AND SO FORTH. >> BUT IT'S LIKE THERE WE ARE
STILL A POPULATION THAT IS IN PROGRESS OF WANTING TO
CONTINUE OUR HERITAGE AND I WOULD LIKE TO BE PART OF THAT
AND TO CONTINUE THAT AND IT'S REALLY GREAT TO BE PART OF ALL
THE DIFFERENT AREAS WHERE I CAN SUPPORT AND I ENCOURAGE EACH
AND EVERY ONE OF US TO SUPPORT THESE AREAS BECAUSE IT IS
NEEDED BECAUSE YOU KNOW, THE AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURE CENTER
NEEDS TO CONTINUE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND I WANT TO JUST
ENCOURAGE YOU TO LOOK IN THESE AREAS AND TO DISCUSS AMONGST
YOURSELVES AND YOUR AREA, YOUR FAMILIES, YOUR FRIENDS HEY,
THERE'S TO BE SOME THERE ARE SOME INDIANS HERE, THERE'S SOME
NAVAJOS HERE THERE SOME YOU KNOW YOU KNOW THIS LAND THAT WE
LIVE ON IT'S IT WASN'T OURS. YOU KNOW THAT HISTORY NEEDS TO
BE SAID OVER AND OVER AND OVER .
SO AGAIN, I DO APPRECIATE THIS THIS TIME THAT I CAN EXPRESS
YOU KNOW, MY AND JUST REALLY GRATEFUL TO BE HERE AND THANK
YOU AGAIN FOR THE AWESOME LUNCH.
YOU KNOW IT'S REALLY GOOD TO BE AROUND IN A SMALL ROOM WITH
OTHER NATIVES LIKE YEAH YOU KNOW SO IT'S REALLY COOL.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. THANK YOU
. DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR CHERYL
OOPS EXCUSE ME. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
HONORED TO COMMEND MARIANNE SPENCER HARVEY IN CELEBRATION
OF NATIVE AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH.
MARIANNE WOULD YOU PLEASE COME FORWARD TO THE PODIUM?
HELLO MARIANNE. >> WELCOME.
I AM SO HONORED TO HAVE YOU HERE AND NOT ONLY BECAUSE
EARLIER WE TALKED ABOUT OUR SHARED BACKYARD OF THE PRESIDIO
BUT THE WAY THAT YOU SPOKE ABOUT THE PRESIDIO AS YOUR
BACKYARD IS OUR BACKYARD I THOUGHT REALLY SPOKE VOLUMES
ABOUT YOUR VIEW ON THE WORLD, YOUR VIEW ON COMMUNITY AND YOUR
VIEW ON STEWARDSHIP FOR ALL OF US NOW FOR THOSE WHO HAVEN'T
HAD THE PLEASURE OF MEETING MARIANNE SHE'S A PROUD ELDER
IN THE NATIVE AMERICAN COMMUNITY HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO, SHE TAKES GREAT PRIDE IN HER DNA, HERITAGE
AND MEMBERSHIP IN THE NAVAJO NATION.
RAISED IN ARIZONA CLOSE TO HER ROOTS, HER FATHER WAS A
SILVERSMITH AND HER MOTHER A DIETICIAN BEING RAISED SO CLOSE
TO THE NAVAJO NATION HER UPBRINGING SHAPED HER STRONG
SENSE OF CULTURAL RESPONSIBILITY AND CARE FOR
OTHERS AND NOW SHE BRINGS HER HERITAGE INTO HER SERVICE AS AN
ELDER COMMUNITY VOLUNTEER CULTURE BEARER.
>> SINCE MOVING TO SAN FRANCISCO, MARIANNE HAS BEEN A
COMPASSIONATE NEIGHBOR AND AN ACTIVE VOLUNTEER WITH THE
AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL DISTRICT'S CULTURE AND LAND
STEWARDSHIP PROGRAM WHICH ORIGINATED AT BLACK POINT
HISTORIC GARDEN. FOR THOSE WHO DON'T KNOW, THE
BLACK POINT GARDEN IS SREE I MENTIONED IS A ONE ACRE
HILLSIDE THAT CONNECTS THE AQUATIC PARK WITH FORT MASON
AND IT'S ONE OF THE MANY AREAS OF SPECIAL CULTURAL
AND HISTORICAL SIGNIFICANCE FOR THE NATIVE COMMUNITY IN FORT
MASON. >> MARIAN HAS BEEN A DEDICATED
STEWARD OF THIS GARDEN HELPING WEED, PRUNE AND PLANT THE
GARDEN WITH A MIX OF NATIVE SPECIES AND HORTICULTURAL
SPECIES. BUT BEYOND JUST HER
VOLUNTEERING MARIAN IS ALSO KNOWN FOR HER COMPASSION FOR
FELLOW SENIORS AND NEIGHBORS OFTEN CONVERSING WITH THOSE
IN HER NEIGHBORHOOD OFFERING SUPPORT AND BUILDING
CONNECTIONS ROOTED IN THE NAVAJO VALUE OF CARING FOR ALL
PEOPLE. MARIAN STORY REFLECTS THE
BROADER NATIVE HISTORY OF OUR CITY.
THE LANDS WE STAND ON ARE THE HOMELANDS OF THE ROMA TO SALONI
AND SITES THROUGHOUT DISTRICT TWO INCLUDING FORT MASON
AND THE GIGI AND ARE A CARRY THE HISTORY, KNOWLEDGE
AND STEWARDSHIP OF NATIVE PEOPLES WHO HAVE LIVED IN THIS
REGION FOR THOUSANDS OF YEARS. >> I'M EXTREMELY GRATEFUL THAT
THE AMERICAN INDIAN CULTURAL DISTRICT IS HEADQUARTERED
IN DISTRICT TWO AND I ESPECIALLY ENJOY TOURING
TOURING THEIR OFFICES TO SEE THE WORK THAT LEADERS LIKE
SHREYA AND OTHERS AND HER TEAM DO TO STRENGTHEN VISIBILITY,
CULTURAL PROGRAMING AND COMMUNITY SUPPORT FOR
NATIVE PEOPLE CITYWIDE MARIAN SERVICE EXEMPLIFY AS THIS WORK
HELPS KEEPS NATIVE HISTORY VISIBLE AND HONORS IN OUR CITY
WHERE INDIGENOUS PEOPLES HAVE LIVED, CARED FOR THE LAND
AND SHAPED THE REGION FOR THOUSANDS OF YEARS.
SO TODAY MARIAN WE RECOGNIZE YOU FOR YOUR STEWARDSHIP, FOR
YOUR CULTURAL LEADERSHIP, FOR YOUR DEDICATION TO COMMUNITY.
SO THANK YOU FOR SERVING OUR COMMUNITY AND CONGRATULATIONS
AND I INVITE YOU TO SAY A FEW WORDS THANK YOU.
>> HE I'M DUMBFOUNDED BUT I'M SORRY.
>> HOLD ON ONE SECOND. >> SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANKS,
PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN. THANK YOU SO MUCH, SUPERVISOR
CHERYL FOR THIS WELL DESERVED COMMENDATION.
AND MARIAN, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR CONTINUING TO STEWARD BLACK
POINT AND ESPECIALLY FOR MY GENERATION FOR FUTURE
GENERATIONS AS THIS KIND OF STEWARDSHIP CONTINUES TO
SUPPORT THE LEGACY OF OUR PEOPLES.
AND I JUST WANT TO THANK YOU FOR MAKING THAT POSSIBLE FOR
ALL SAN FRANCISCO NATIVES. THANK YOU SO MUCH
AND CONGRATULATIONS. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
AND YOU'RE SO OVERWHELMED RIGHT NOW EXCEPT FOR ONE THING AND MY
FRIEND KNOWS THIS ABOUT WE HAVE ALWAYS BEEN KNOWN AS THE FIRST
PEOPLE. THAT'S OUR WAY.
WE'RE A COMMUNITY. NO PERSON IS FIRST.
THE SAN FRANCISCO LIBRARY HAS ALWAYS BEEN IN THE PAST FIRST
PEOPLE WHEN IT GOT OUR NEWSLETTER OUT ABOUT US FIRST
PEOPLE THIS YEAR BECAME CHANGED TO FIRST PERSON WHEN I SAW THAT
I WAS SO INSULTED I DON'T EVEN GO TO THE LIBRARY ANYMORE.
IT'S NOT THE WAY WE ARE. WE ARE NOT FIRST PERSON.
WE ARE FIRST PEOPLE AND MY FRIEND AND I WE WHEN WE SPOKE
TO THEM ABOUT IT AT ALCATRAZ AND IT WAS TO A BLANK WALL SO
WE NEED TO CHANGE THAT TO MAKE IT CLEAR TO EVERYONE BECAUSE
IT'S DEFENDING THE ELDERS WE'VE BEEN HERE FOR A LONG WHILE.
WE TAUGHT OUR YOUNG PEOPLE WE'RE A WHOLE PEOPLE.
>> THANK YOU
. OKAY SO YEAH, VERY, VERY
DISTRICT ONE SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MAN DOMAIN
I WOULD LIKE TO INVITE MY NEIGHBOR JULIE FISHER AND SEIU
2015 MEMBERS TO THE PODIUM COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
COMMENDING SEIU 2015 THE IN-HOME SUPPORTIVE SERVICE
PROVIDERS NOVEMBER IS NATIONAL FAMILY CAREGIVERS MONTH
AND WE'RE DECLARING TODAY NOVEMBER 18TH IN HOME
SUPPORTIVE SERVICE PROVIDERS DAY IN SAN FRANCISCO IN-HOME
SUPPORTIVE SERVICE I ASK PROVIDERS PLAY A VITAL ROLE
IN SUPPORTING SENIORS AND PEOPLE WITH DISABILITIES
IN SAN FRANCISCO AND GREATER BAY AREA AS WELL AS CALIFORNIA
AND ACROSS THIS COUNTRY OUR IN-HOME SUPPORTIVE SERVICE
PROVIDERS ENSURING THAT OUR LOVED ONES CAN LIVE WITH
DIGNITY AND INDEPENDENCE IN THE COMFORT OF THEIR OWN HOMES.
>> THE PROVIDERS AND WORKERS DEVOTE THEIR TIME, COMPASSION
AND EXPERTISE TO ASSIST THOSE IN NEED WITH A SPECTRUM OF
SUPPORT FROM ESSENTIALLY ESSENTIAL DAILY ACTIVITIES TO
CRITICAL AND INTIMATE CARE SERVICE TO DILIGENT WORK OF
IN-HOME CAREGIVERS THE MAJORITY OF WHOM ARE WOMEN AND WOMEN OF
COLOR AND IMMIGRANT OFTEN GOES UNNOTICED ALONG WITH THE
FINANCIAL STRUGGLES THEY AND THEIR FAMILIES ENDURE TO
PROVIDE THIS ESSENTIAL SERVICE AND CARE TO THOSE IN NEED, WE
ARE JUST SO GRATEFUL FOR THEM. IT IS AMAZING JUST JUST HOW
GREAT THEY ARE. >> I AM JUST IN ODD OF HOW
RESILIENT AND AMAZING AND COMMITTED THEY ARE NOT JUST
TO CARE FOR OUR LOVED ONES AND BUT ALSO OUR COMMUNITY
AND OFTEN TIME YOU SEE SEIU 2015 MEMBERS EVERYWHERE IN A
LOT OF COMMUNITY EVENTS SUPPORTING OUR COMMUNITY
MEMBERS NOT JUST AT THEIR HOMES BUT ALSO COMMUNITIES ALL ACROSS
SAN FRANCISCO. AND IF I MAY I WANT TO JUST SAY
A FEW WORDS IN CHINESE AS WELL. HASAN THOUGHT I HOPE WITH ALL
THEY GO WILL THEY GO? I WILL GO YOUNG DURING THOSE
EARLY WHEN I THINK I SAY SAID QUICK A GONG HING KNOW
AND BEFORE YOU SPEAK SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU PRESIDENT
MENDOZA THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR UPLIFTING SEIU 2015
THANK YOU. >> THEY ARE MY FAMILY MEMBERS.
>> THEY WATCH ME GO UP. I I I YOU KNOW ESPECIALLY I
WANT TO SHOUT OUT TO MAY CHEN YOU KNOW ME IT'S DEFINITELY A
COMMUNITY LEADER FOR SAN FRANCISCO IN OUR COMMUNITY YOU
KNOW VOLUNTARY PARTICIPATED A LOT OF THE MEETING NOT ONLY FOR
THE LABOR FOR SEIU 2015 BUT IT'S ALSO VERY ACTIVE IN THE
COMMUNITY AND GIVING BACK AND MAKING SURE THAT OUR
COMMUNITY CONTINUE TO BE STRONG AND I DON'T WANT TO TAKE MY
TIME BUT I JUST WANT TO SAY HOME CARE SAVES LIVES.
>> THANK YOU. AND I WANT TO ALSO SAY THAT
HOME CARE PROVIDES DIGNITY IN OUR COMMUNITY, ESPECIALLY
FOR THE ONES THAT THE LOVED ONES THAT WE ALL CARE AND THAT
ONES THAT YOU CARE. I ALSO WANT TO SAY A LOT TO THE
WORKERS AND I THINK THAT'S OUR SAY AND CHINESE WHICH I'M GOING
TO DO IT IT'S THE WHAT ARE YOU DO YOU WE CANNOT USE MONEY TO
MEASURE SO THIS IS WHY I'M SO PROUD THAT I AM YOUR CHAMPION
FIGHTING TO MAKE SURE THAT NOT ONLY WE HAVE WE PROVIDE QUALITY
CARE BUT WE ALSO PROVIDE QUALITY JOBS.
HIJO MILES ON CONGREGATE TO HIRE A HOTEL JAKE I WILL GO
TONIGHT DOJO HAPPY NOW TEACHING LIGHTS HIGH SING DANG ALAMEDA
YEAH $1 TONY I WANT
AND I WILL JUST ADD THANKS TO THE MEMBERS OF SEIU 2015 FOR
ALL YOU DO TO CARE FOR OUR MOST VULNERABLE FOLKS
AND CONGRATULATIONS AND THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN FOR THIS
COMMENDATION. DEAR ESTEEMED COLLEAGUES
AND SUPERVISORS I WANT TO EXPRESS MY DEEPEST GRATITUDE
FOR THE OPPORTUNITY TO SERVE IN THE IHS PROGRAM WORKING WITH
YOU AND FOR THE PEOPLE WHO TRUST OUR SERVICES HAS BEEN AN
IMMENSE HONOR AND PRIVILEGE. EVERY DAY WE STRIVE TO PROVIDE
THE BEST CARE AND ATTENTION TO THOSE WHO NEED IT MOST.
I GREATLY APPRECIATE THE TRUST PLACED IN EACH OF US AND I
SINCERELY VALUE THE DEDICATION OF EACH PERSON INVOLVED IN THIS
NOBLE WORK TOGETHER WE MAKE A SIGNIFICANT DIFFERENCE IN THE
LIVES OF THOSE WE SERVE. THANK YOU FOR YOUR CONTINUED
SUPPORT AND FOR BEING A FUNDAMENT A PART OF THIS
INVALUABLE WORK. >> YOU DON'T GET IT.
OKAY. OKAY GO AHEAD.
>> I GOT WHITE SHE'S HAMACHI ISLAND GIRL TYPE YOU ARE THEY
DON'T GOT YANG FAT LINK UP
IT'S JOHNNY RODRIGUEZ IN THE CHAMBER COME ON UP.
>> COLLEAGUES IT IS MY HONOR TODAY TO PRESENT FROM DISTRICT
EIGHT A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO JOHNNY RODRIGUEZ.
JOHNNY HAS IMPROVED COUNTLESS LIVES THROUGH HIS WORK WITH THE
SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY HEALTH CENTER AND AS AN OUTSPOKEN
ADVOCATE FOR INDIGENOUS AND LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITIES.
>> CURRENTLY HE WORKS AS THE CLINICAL PROGRAM MANAGER
CLINICAL PROGRAM MANAGER FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO COMMUNITY
HEALTH CENTER WHERE HE USES HIS ANCESTRAL MEDICINE TO HELP
COMMUNITY MEMBERS ALONG THEIR HEALING JOURNEYS THROUGH
TALKING CIRCLES, CEREMONIES, COMMUNITY GATHERINGS AND A
DECOLONIZED APPROACH TO MENTAL HEALTH.
JOHNNY IS COMMITTED TO CREATING SPACES FOR HEALING JUSTICE
AND CONNECTION OUTSIDE OF HIS WORK AT S.F. CHC.
JOHNNY WORKS WITH ORGANIZATIONS THAT LIFT UP INDIGENOUS AND
PEOPLE IN SAN FRANCISCO INCLUDING THE ANNUAL BAY AREA
AMERICAN INDIAN TO SPIRITS POWWOW ONE OF THE LARGEST
GATHERINGS OF TO SPIRIT AND INDIGENT PEOPLE IN THE
COUNTRY THE BAY AREA MECCA TRANS AND TWO SPIRIT COLLECTIVE
A COLLECTIVE THAT WORKS TO CREATE WELCOMING SPACES FOR
AND TRANS PEOPLE IN THE MEXICA OR AZTEC TRADITIONS AND THE
INDIGENOUS PEOPLES COMMUNITY CHURCH.
RECENTLY JOHNNY WAS ELECTED TO SERVE ON THE BOARD OF THE OF
THE LEATHER AND LGBTQ CULTURAL DISTRICT.
JOHNNY IDENTIFIES AS A TWO SPIRIT ELDER IN TRAINING HIS
ANCESTRAL ROOTS COME FROM THE NORTE SPEAKING PEOPLE OF
NORTHERN MEXICO AND SOUTHERN TEXAS WHILE WORKING TOWARD A
MASTER OF SOCIAL WORK AT CALIFORNIA STATE UNIVERSITY
LONG BEACH. JOHNNY WORKS CLOSELY WITH
STUDENTS AND YOUTH COMMUNITIES PROVIDING GUIDANCE
AND MENTORSHIP AFTER GRADUATING .
JOHNNY CONTINUED TO WORK AS A COMMUNITY ORGANIZER FOR KHMER
GIRLS IN ACTION AND AS A YOUTH SERVICES MANAGER FOR THE S.F.
LGBT CENTER. THOSE WHO'VE WORKED WITH JOHNNY
PRAISED HIS ABILITY TO CONNECT WITH OTHERS AND WORK ETHIC
AND DESCRIBED JOHNNY AS AN EXTRAORDINARY ADVOCATE AND AN
INVALUABLE ASSET TO HIS COMMUNITIES.
WITH IMMENSE GRATITUDE, GRATITUDE AND APPRECIATE WE
THANK YOU JOHNNY FOR YOUR SERVICE TO OUR CITY.
AND NOW THE FLOOR IS YOURS. >> THANK YOU.
I ALWAYS LIKE TO START WITH GIVING DEEP GRATITUDE THE
ANCESTORS AND GUARDIANS OF THIS PLACE TO DRAMATIST SALONI.
THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN AND THE REST OF THE BOARD FOR
THIS OPPORTUNITY AND THANK YOU FOR LANCE TOM ART, MY BOSS, MY
CEO WHO WHO SAID MY NAME AND ALLOW ME TO BE HERE TODAY.
>> I WANTED TO SHARE SOME OF THE TEACHING.
IT'S A REALLY NICE BIBLE AND I WAS LIKE OH WELL I FORGOT ABOUT
SOME OF THOSE THINGS. BUT ONE OF THE TEACHINGS THAT I
LEARNED EARLY ON AND THAT I CARRY WITH ME IS THAT WHEN THE
COMMUNITY NEEDS YOU YOU SHOW UP.
AND SO THROUGHOUT MY LIFE SINCE I WAS A TEENAGER PROBABLY ANY
TIME I HEARD PEOPLE NEEDED HELP, THEY NEEDED FOOD, THEY
NEEDED GUIDANCE. I WAS THERE AND I CONTINUE THAT
TEACHING TODAY WITH ALL OF THE THINGS NOW HAVE BEEN LISTED
TODAY LIKE IT'S A LOT OF STUFF BUT BUT I DO IT BECAUSE I
BECAUSE I CARE ABOUT THE COMMUNITY, BECAUSE I CARE ABOUT
THE CITY. SAN FRANCISCO IS THE CITY I
LOVE AND I'M HERE TO DO THE WORK TO CARE FOR PEOPLE WHEN
THEY NEED IT. AND AS LONG AS I'M CAPABLE I
WILL CONTINUE LIVING THAT TEACHING OF TAKING CARE OF
PEOPLE WHEN THEY NEED IT. I ALSO WANT TO SAY JUST JUST TO
GIVE RECOGNITION THAT THROUGHOUT HISTORY TRANS
AND TO SPIRIT PEOPLE HAVE LED ALL OF OUR COMMUNITIES SO WE
ALWAYS WANT TO MAKE SPACE TO HONOR THEM, HONOR THOSE
ANCESTORS AND TRANS SISTERS WHO HAVE LED THE WAY FOR US AND IN
THE PAST AND EVEN CURRENTLY TODAY.
AND THE LAST THING I WANT TO SAY IS TO ALL MY RELATIONS
MARTY, MY KATHLEEN, THANK YOU AND MAYOR HARVEY PRESENT
. >> ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR FIELDER FOR ORGANIZING US TO TO DO THAT
AND HONOR HONOR THOSE AMAZING FOLKS.
NOW WE SHOULD GET TO OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER MADAM CLERK YEAH,
3 P.M. 3 P.M. SPECIAL. >> YES, THE FIRST 3 P.M.
SPECIAL ORDER THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAS CONVENED A
COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE APPROVAL FROM RESCHEDULED SEPTEMBER 22ND
2020 THROUGH NOVEMBER 18TH 2025 ITEM 37 THIS IS A HEARING OF
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS CONVENING A COMMITTEE OF THE
WHOLE OR FOR THE MEMBERS OF THE BOARD TO HEAR AND RECEIVE
UPDATES ON THE PROGRESS AND IMPLEMENTATION STATUS OF
THE UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE RECOMMENDATIONS
PERTAINING TO REFORMS WITHIN THE POLICE DEPARTMENT.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT, MADAM AND COLLEAGUES
THIS IS THE LAST TIME WE WILL ASK FOR A CONTINUANCE ON THIS
ITEM AND WE ASK THAT WE CONTINUE THIS ITEM TO DECEMBER
SECOND. >> ALL RIGHT.
THERE'S A MOTION TO CONTINUE THIS HEARING TO DECEMBER 2ND.
>> IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY FIELDER BEFORE WE CAN ACT ON
THAT MOTION WE NEED TO TAKE PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE
CONTINUANCE IF ANYONE WANTS TO TALK ABOUT THE CONTINUANCE.
THIS IS NOT GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT.
IF ANYBODY WANTS TO TALK ABOUT THE CONTINUANCE COME FORWARD
AND IF NOT PUBLIC COMMENTS ON THE CONTINUANCE IS CLOSED
AND MY COLLEAGUES AS I SAID, WE HAVE A MOTION TO CONTINUE THIS
HEARING TO DECEMBER 2ND, 2025 BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MEETING.
CAN WE TAKE THAT MOTION WITHOUT OBJECTION AND I'M GOING TO SAY
THERE OKAY, MR. PRESIDENT, WE NEED A ROLL CALL.
>> ALL RIGHT. LET'S DO A ROLL CALL ON THE
MOTION TO CONTINUE ITEM 37 TO DECEMBER 2ND.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN MY
MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SUTTER
SAUTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
THERE ARE TONIGHT WITHOUT OBJECTION THIS HEARING IS
CONTINUED TO DECEMBER SECOND 2025 MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
OUR NEXT 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER PLEASE CALL ITEM 38 THROUGH 41
TOGETHER ITEMS 38 THROUGH 41 COMPRISE THE PUBLIC HEARING OF
PERSONS INTERESTED IN THE APPROVAL OF A FINAL MITIGATED
NEGATIVE DECLARATION UNDER THE CALIFORNIA ENVIRONMENTAL
QUALITY ACT FOR THE PROPOSED PROJECT AT 570 MARKET STREET
ITEM 39 AFFIRMS THE APPROVAL BY THE PLANNING COMMISSION OF
UNDER UNDER THE SECURE FOR THE PROPOSED PROJECT ITEM 40 THIS
CONDITIONALLY REVERSES THE APPROVAL OF THE PLANNING
COMMISSION AND ITEM 41 IS THE MOTION TO DIRECT THE
PREPARATION OF FINDINGS REVERSING THE APPROVAL.
>> ALL RIGHT, SO COLLEAGUES, WE HAVE BEFORE US AS THE CLERK
INDICATED AN APPEAL OF THE FINAL MITIGATED NEGATIVE
DECLARATION FOR THE PROPOSED PROJECT AT 570 MARKET STREET.
I HAVE AFTER THE HEARING THE BOARD WILL VOTE ON WHETHER TO
AFFIRM OR CONDITIONALLY REVERSE THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S
APPROVAL. WE HAVE TWO APPELLANTS FOR THIS
PROJECT AND SO UNLESS THERE'S AN OBJECTION GOING FORWARD
IN THIS WAY WILL DIVIDE THE PRESENTATION TIME BETWEEN THEM
AND WE WILL PROCEED AS FOLLOWS UP TO FIVE MINUTES FOR EACH
APPELLANT FOR A TOTAL OF TEN MINUTES THEN PUBLIC COMMENT
IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL TWO MINUTES PER SPEAKER THEN UP TO
TEN MINUTES FOR A PRESENTATION FROM THE CITY DEPARTMENTS THEN
UP TO TEN MINUTES FOR THE PROJECT SPONSOR, THEN BACK TO
PUBLIC COMMENT WITH TWO MINUTES PER SPEAKER IN OPPOSITION TO
THE APPEAL AND FINALLY UP TO TWO MINUTES FOR EACH APPELLANT
TO MAKE A REBUTTAL FOR A TOTAL OF FOUR MINUTES IF ANYONE
OBJECTS LET ME KNOW IF WE DON'T WE WILL PROCEED WITH THE PUBLIC
HEARING WHICH IS NOW OPEN AND BEFORE WE BEFORE WE HEAR
FROM THE FROM THE APPELLANTS APPELLANTS SUPERVISOR SAUTER
YES. >> THANK YOU PRESENT GENTLEMEN,
I WANT TO BEGIN BY THANKING THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT, THE
PROJECT SPONSORS AND THE APPELLANTS FOR ALL YOUR WORK ON
THIS APPEAL. IT IS IN MY DISTRICT
IN DISTRICT THREE BY JUST A FEW FEET ON THE NORTH SIDE OF
MARKET AND SINCE THIS APPEAL WAS FILED MY OFFICE AND I HAVE
MET WITH THE PROJECT SPONSORS OF 570 MARKET APPELLANTS FROM
44 MONTGOMERY AND THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT ON THIS MATTER.
SO I WANT US TO BE SURE THAT WE'RE CLEAR ABOUT THE QUESTION
BEFORE US TODAY WHICH IS NOT ABOUT THE PROJECT'S DESIGN OR
MERITS WHICH WILL BE CONSIDERED AT LATER STAGES.
BUT TODAY THE QUESTION BEFORE US RATHER IS SIMPLY THE IF THE
ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW THAT HAS BEEN DONE IS ADEQUATE.
AND SO WITH THAT VERY BRIEF INTRODUCTION BE HAPPY TO TURN
IT BACK TO YOU PRESENT GENTLEMEN TO BEGIN OUR
PROCEEDINGS. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SADER
SO WE'RE GOING TO INVITE EACH OF THE APPELLANTS TO COME
FORWARD AND PRESENT THEIR CASE EACH HAVING FIVE MINUTES AND I
BELIEVE WE'RE GOING TO START WITH REPRESENTATIVES FROM FOR
BE 44 MONTGOMERY PROPERTY LLC BRIAN FLYNN LET'S GET THAT
WONKY GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT AMEN.
AMEN. HONORABLE SUPERVISORS MY NAME
IS BRIAN FLYNN. I'M A SCHOOL ATTORNEY WITH THE
LAW FIRM LOWE'S. OUR JURY HERE THIS AFTERNOON ON
BEHALF OF THE APPELLANT BE CALLE 40 MONTGOMERY PROPERTY OR
THE OWNERS OF 44 MONTGOMERY STREET 41ST MONTGOMERY'S
POSITION IN THIS APPEAL IS THAT THE PROJECTS MITIGATED NEGATIVE
DECLARATION WHICH IS ONE OF THE LOWEST TIERS OF SKILL REVIEW
WAS IMPROPER AND THAT A FULL ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT IS
REQUIRED FOR THIS PROJECT. SEQUA HAS A STRONG PREFERENCE
FOR THE PREPARATION OF AN AIR OVER AN MANDY.
THIS IS REFLECTED IN WHAT IS KNOWN AS THE FAIR ARGUMENT
STANDARD UNDER THE FAIR ARGUMENT STANDARD YOU NEED TO
PREPARE AN AIR IF THERE IS ANY SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE IN THE
RECORD THAT THE PROJECT MAY HAVE A SIGNIFICANT IMPACT
AND IMPORTANTLY IF THERE'S EVIDENCE OF SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS
YOU NEED TO PREPARE AN AIR EVEN IF THERE'S CONTRARY EVIDENCE ON
THE OTHER SIDE. >> SO AS A SUPERVISOR SOUDER
POINTED OUT, THE LIMITED QUESTION IN FRONT OF THE BOARD
IS NOT THAT YOU'RE NOT BEING ASKED TO TAKE A POSITION ON THE
PROJECT BUT ONLY ON WHETHER THIS PROJECT MEETS THE LOW
SQUAT THRESHOLD FOR PREPARATION OF ANY AIR AND EVIDENCE THAT
HAS BEEN PROVIDED BY 44 MONTGOMERY AND THE OTHER
APPELLANT AFFIRMATIVE AFFIRMATIVELY ESTABLISH THAT
THIS PROJECT MAY RESULT IN SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS IN THE
LIMITED TIME I HAVE I CAN'T GO INTO EVERY IMPACT IN DETAIL BUT
I'D LIKE TO GIVE A SUMMARY FOR NOISE IMPACTS WE'VE SUBMITTED
WRITTEN COMMENTS THAT INCLUDED AN EXPERT REVIEW OF THIS
PROJECT AND AMANDA, ONE OF THE MAIN ISSUES THEY FOUND WITH
THIS MANDY IS THAT THE MANDY ASSUMED THAT SOUND WOULD
ATTENUATE AT A DISTANT OVER DISTANCE AT A RATE OF SIX
DECIBELS. >> OUR EXPERT POINTED OUT THAT
DOES NOT ACCURATELY REFLECT THE CONDITIONS IN THE FINANCIAL
DISTRICT WHERE YOU HAVE LOTS OF TALL BUILDINGS REFLECTING SOUND
AND CREATING CANYON LIKE ENVIRONMENTS.
OUR EXPERT CONCLUDED THAT A THREE DECIBEL RATE WAS MORE
PROPER AND ACCURATE AND THAT THAT WOULD RESULT
IN SIGNIFICANT NOISE IMPACTS AT THE NEAREST RESIDENCES ON BUSH
STREET AND THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT AND THE APPLICANT
HAVE TRIED AND WILL TRY TO REFUTE THAT EXPERT TONIGHT.
BUT THE BOARD'S JOB HERE IS NOT TO WEIGH CONFLICTING EVIDENCE
UNDER THAT FAIR ARGUMENT STANDARD OUR EXPERT HAS
PROVIDED CREDIBLE EVIDENCE OF POSSIBLE SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS SO
AN AIR IS REQUIRED EVEN IF SOMEONE ELSE DISAGREES.
OUR NOISE EXPERT ALSO FOUND THAT THE MANDY ONLY ANALYZED
ABSOLUTE NOISE THRESHOLDS FOR THE IMPACTS TO 44 MONTGOMERY
STREET THE CHANCERY BUILDING FINANCE BUILDING AND OTHERS.
BUT IN ADDITION TO ABSOLUTE NOISE THRESHOLD SCALE REQUIRES
AN ANALYSIS OF THE RELATIVE INCREASE IN NOISE OVER EXISTING
AMBIENT LEVELS. OUR EXPERT FOUND THAT EVEN IF
YOU USED A CONSERVATIVE 20 DECIBEL INCREASE OVER OVER OVER
AMBIENT TEMPERATURES THAT'S DOUBLE WHAT THE RESIDENTIAL
THRESHOLD WOULD BE. >> THE PROJECT WOULD RESULT
IN SIGNIFICANT NOISE IMPACTS TO 44 MONTGOMERY AND OTHERS AGAIN
UNDER THAT FAIR ARGUMENT STANDARD THE EXPERTS PROVIDED
CREDIBLE EVIDENCE AND SO THE AIR HOURS REQUIRED EVEN IF
OTHERS DISAGREE THERE ARE ALSO ISSUES WITH VIBRATION IMPACTS.
I WANT TO PREFACE THE DISCUSSION WITH THE FACT THAT
FOR FOR MONTGOMERY THE CHANCERY BUILDING THE FINANCE BUILDING
ARE ALL RECOGNIZED HISTORICAL RESOURCES THEY ALL DIRECTLY
ABOVE THE PROPOSED HOTEL THEY'RE AS CLOSE AS A FOOT
AWAY. THE MANDY CONCLUDED THAT THE
INCORPORATION OF MITIGATION MEASURES WOULD REDUCE THE
VIBRATION IMPACTS TO LESS THAN SIGNIFICANT BUT THOSE MEASURES
ARE INSUFFICIENT TO CONCLUDE THAT THE IMPACTS WON'T BE
SIGNIFICANT. THE MEASURES PRIMARILY CONSIST
OF A SERIES OF ACTIONS AND MEASURES TO BE TAKEN AFTER
VIBRATION EXCEEDANCES OCCUR. IN OTHER WORDS, THE MEASURES DO
NOT ACTUALLY MITIGATE THE IMPACTS FROM HAPPENING BUT ONLY
PRESCRIBE WHAT TO DO AFTER DAMAGE HAS BEEN DONE AGAIN
UNDER THAT FAIR ARGUMENT STANDARD THE FACT THAT THE
MOODY'S OWN VIBRATION MITIGATION FOR ALL PURPOSES
ASSUMES THAT THE NEIGHBORING BUILDINGS MAY BE DAMAGED,
ESTABLISHES THE FAIR ARGUMENT THAT AN AIR IS REQUIRED.
VERY BRIEFLY WE ALSO SUBMITTED EVIDENCE FROM A HISTORICAL
RESOURCES EXPERT WHO CONCLUDED THAT THE IMPACTS OF THIS
PROJECT WOULD BE SIGNIFICANT DUE TO ITS SIZE AND MASSING ON
NEARBY HISTORICAL RESOURCES INCLUDING FOR MONTGOMERY, THE
CHANCERY BUILDING AND FINANCE BUILDING WE ALSO SUBMITTED
PHOTOS SHOWING COMMERCIAL CONGESTION ON SUTTER STREET
THAT'S ONLY GOING TO BE CONGESTED BY THIS HOTEL WHICH
IS GOING TO HAVE ALL OF ITS COMMERCIAL DELIVERIES DROP OFFS
FOR HOTEL GUESTS AND EMPLOYEES WOULD ALL HAPPEN ON SUTTER
STREET, NOT ON MARKET STREET. SO FOR THOSE REASONS THE
REASONS WE'VE DISCUSSED ALSO IN OUR WRITTEN CORRESPONDENCE I
DIDN'T HAVE TIME FOR AND THE REASONS YOU'LL HEAR FROM THE
OTHER APPELLANT 44 MONTGOMERY'S RESPECTFULLY REQUESTING THAT
THE BOARD GRANT THESE APPEALS TO ENSURE THAT THIS PROJECT
GOES THROUGH THE PROPER AMOUNT OF ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW PRIOR
TO APPROVAL AS REQUIRED BY SEQUOIA.
THANK YOU. WE I DON'T SEE ANY QUESTIONS SO
WE WILL NOW HEAR FROM THE REPRESENTATIVE FOR THE SECOND
APPELLANT CP H564 LP AND THAT IS OH I THOUGHT IT WAS ENGINE
CO BUT IT'S NOT IN A SIMCOE HELLO.
>> OKAY SORRY GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS ZACK FADI WE OWN THE
CHANCERY BUILDING WHICH IS ADJACENT TO THE PROPOSED HOTEL.
WE HAVE A SMALL FAMILY BUSINESS THAT WE BUILT THROUGH MANY
YEARS OF HARD WORK AND THE ECONOMIC VIABILITY OF OUR
BUILDING IS CRITICAL FOR US. WE HAVE JUST SUFFERED ABOUT
FIVE YEARS OF EXTREME ECONOMIC HARDSHIP STEMMING FROM COVID
AND ITS AFTER EFFECTS AND NOW THAT WE'RE JUST COMING UP FOR
AIR THE PROPOSED HOTEL DEVELOPMENT WILL UNNECESSARILY
DAMAGE US AND CAUSE US ANOTHER 2 OR 3 YEARS OF ECONOMIC
HARDSHIP WHICH CAN BE AVOIDED IF THE PROJECT IS PROPERLY
EVALUATED. THIS IS NOT A TYPICAL BUILDING
SITE WITH ADJACENT SOLID WALL CONCRETE WALLED BUILDINGS.
WE HAVE A HISTORIC BUILDING WITH 141 WINDOWS ALONG
AND DIRECTLY FRONTING THE CONSTRUCTION AREA.
MUCH OF THE PROPOSED BUILDING IS 12IN FROM OUR BUILDING
AND THE HOTEL LOT IS AN AVERAGE OF 45FT WIDE WHICH IS A LITTLE
MORE THAN TWO CAR LENGTHS WIDE. SO ALL CONSTRUCTION WORK WILL
BE FELT IN OUR BUILDING. OUR BUILDING DOES NOT HAVE
MECHANICAL VENTILATION AND THE ONLY WAY TO GET FRESH AIR TO
OPEN THE WINDOWS THE WINDOWS ARE SINGLE PANE GLASS SO EVEN
WHEN THEY'RE CLOSED YOU ACTUALLY HEAR A LOT OF LOUD
SOUNDS FROM OUTSIDE THE MAIN DECONSTRUCTION THE AMENDED
CONSTRUCTION NOISE ESTIMATES WHICH RANGE BETWEEN 92DB
AND 99DB ARE CALCULATED FOR SOURCES AT A DISTANCE OF 20FT.
HOWEVER, ABOUT HALF OF THE PROPOSED HOTEL IS ONE FOOT FROM
OUR BUILDING AND THE OTHER HALF IS ABOUT 7 OR 8FT FROM OUR
BUILDING. SO THE CONSTRUCTION NOISE
LEVELS WILL EXCEED THE ESTIMATED LEVELS FOR CONTEXT,
92DB IS EQUIVALENT TO THE SOUND OF A LAWNMOWER AT THREE FOOT
DISTANCE 95DB IS EQUAL TO THE SOUND OF A JACKHAMMER AT 50
FOOT DISTANCE AND 99DB IS EQUAL TO A CAR HORN AT 16 FOOT
DISTANCE AND CAUSES EAR DAMAGE AFTER 30 MINUTES EXPOSURE.
THESE NOISE LEVELS WHICH AGAIN ARE THE M AND D CALCULATED
LEVELS FOR 20 FOOT DISTANCES AND WHICH WILL BE EXCEEDED DUE
TO THE PROXIMITY OF THE WORK TO OUR BUILDING WILL MAKE OUR
BUILDING VERY DIFFICULT TO WORK IN DURING PERIODS OF
CONSTRUCTION AND WILL UNNECESSARILY CREATES A
FINANCIAL DISASTER FOR US. ONE CANNOT WITH A STRAIGHT FACE
SAY THAT 2 TO 3 YEARS OF NOISE LEVELS THAT VARY BETWEEN THE
NOISE OF A LAWNMOWER OR A JACKHAMMER AND A CAR HORN ARE
NOT SIGNIFICANT ENOUGH TO JUSTIFY AN AIR STUDY WHICH
WOULD IDENTIFY AND PROVIDE MITIGATION PLAN FOR SUCH NOISE
. IT'S A CERTAIN AS VERIFIED BY
EXPERTS THAT OUR BUILDING WILL SUFFER FROM EXPOSURE TO
EXCESSIVE NOISE VIBRATION AND CONSTRUCTION DUST AND WE
WILL SUFFER OTHER DAMAGES THAT OUR LAWYER WILL COVER.
THE CURRENT SECURE DOCUMENT DOES NOT RECOGNIZE AND MITIGATE
SUCH SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS AND THUS DOES NOT MEET LEGAL
STANDARDS. PLEASE DIRECT THAT A FULL EIA
BE PREPARED SO THE ENVIRONMENTAL AND HEALTH
IMPACTS CAN BE PROPERLY EXAMINED AND CONSIDERED
AND EFFECTIVE MITIGATION STRATEGIES CAN BE EVALUATED.
>> THANK YOU AND A CO COUNSEL FOR THE APPELLANT MR. FLYNN
ARTICULATED THE LEGAL STANDARD QUITE WELL.
THE MMD ACKNOWLEDGE IS THAT THE PROJECT'S VIBRATION IMPACTS
WILL BE SIGNIFICANT THAT WILL ESPECIALLY BE TRUE TO OUR
CLIENT'S HISTORIC BUILDING. THE FLOOR OF THE MD IS THE
CONCLUSION THAT THE MITIGATION MEASURE WILL OVERCOME THIS
SIGNIFICANT VIBRATION IMPACT. >> OUR STRUCTURAL ENGINEER
OPINED THAT THE CHANCERY BUILDINGS OLD FOUNDATION IS
EXTREMELY SENSITIVE TO VIBRATION FROM CONSTRUCTION
ACTIVITY NEARBY AND THERE COULD BE CATASTROPHIC EFFECTS THAT IS
AN EXPERT OPINION THAT MUST BE GIVEN WEIGHT IN THIS PROCESS.
>> THE MEASURE ORDERS PERIODIC INSPECTIONS TO SEE IF DAMAGE
HAS OCCURRED IN WHICH CASE THE IMPACT WAS ALREADY SIGNIFICANT
AND UNAVOIDABLE REQUIRING THAT DAMAGE BE FIXED LATER DOESN'T
AVOID DAMAGE. >> THE MITIGATION MEASURE ALSO
RELIES ON BUFFER DISTANCES FROM CONSTRUCTION ACTIVITIES.
THAT'S NOT FEASIBLE BECAUSE THE PROJECT SITE ITSELF IS NARROW
AT ONLY 40FT WIDE AND THE PROJECT WALLS WOULD BE BUILT AS
NEAR AS ONE FOOT TWO THE CHANCE TO REBUILDING.
SO IT'S NOT POSSIBLE TO BE FOR INSTANCE 20FT AWAY.
>> FINALLY THE MITIGATION MEASURE ENVISIONS THAT
ALTERNATIVE CONSTRUCTION EQUIPMENT AND TECHNIQUES CAN BE
USED IF VIBRATION EXCEEDS THE THRESHOLD IN FLAGRANT VIOLATION
OF ESTABLISHED SKILL REQUIREMENTS ABOUT PERFORMANCE
STANDARDS AND DEFERRED MITIGATION MEASURES.
THE MMD FAILS ENTIRELY TO SHOW WHETHER SUCH ALTERNATIVES
ACTUALLY EXIST OR WHICH EQUIPMENT OR TECHNIQUES WOULD
COMPRISE THOSE ALTERNATIVES. THAT IMPACT REMAINS SIGNIFICANT
AND UNAVOIDABLE. THE MITIGATION MEASURE IS
INADEQUATE. THERE ARE ALSO IMPACTS WITH
RESPECT TO NOISE AIR QUALITY DUST, HISTORIC ESTHETIC ALL
DOCUMENTED IN THE RECORD THAT COMPEL THE PREPARATION OF ANY
AIR IN THIS CIRCUMSTANCE. THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT. I DO NOT SEE ANYONE IN THE
QUEUE TO ASK QUESTIONS OF THE APPELLANTS.
AND SO LET'S OPEN UP PUBLIC COMMENT SPECIFICALLY FOR THOSE
WHO'D LIKE TO SPEAK IN SUPPORT OF THE APPEAL AND IN OPPOSITION
TO THE PROJECT. MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU CALL THE
FIRST SPEAKER IF WE HAVE ANY GREAT.
>> IF YOU WOULDN'T MIND COMING ON UP TO THE FRONT IF YOU ARE
HERE TO PROVIDE PUBLIC COMMENT ON BEHALF OF THE APPELLANT OR
THE APPELLANT'S REPRESENTATIVE .
>> ALL RIGHT. MR. PRESIDENT, PUBLIC COMMENT
IS NOW CLOSED. NOW WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TEN
MINUTES FOR REPRESENTATIVES OF THE CITY DEPARTMENTS.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN AND SUPERVISORS.
I'M RYAN SHUM, SENIOR PLANNER AND FOR THE PROPOSED 517 MARKET
STREET PROJECT. THE DECISION BEFORE YOU IS
WHETHER TO AFFIRM OR REVERSE THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S
DECISION TO APPROVE THE AMENDED .
AS NOTED THE PLANNING COMMISSION APPROVED THE
PRELIMINARY AMENDED AND REJECTED THE PM THE APPEALS
ON MAY 1ST AND ON OCTOBER 10TH THE SAME TWO APPELLANTS FILED
SEPARATE APPEALS OF THE AMENDED .
THE DEPARTMENT CLEARLY REVIEWED ALL MATERIALS SUBMITTED BY THE
APPELLANTS AND THEY DO NOT ALTER OUR CONCLUSION THAT AN
AMENDED IS THE APPROPRIATE LEVEL OF ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW.
>> THE PROJECT WOULD REPLACE TWO EXISTING TWO STOREY
COMMERCIAL BUILDINGS WITH A 29 STOREY HOTEL AND A 40 200
SQUARE FOOT PUBLIC OPEN SPACE ON THE 15TH FLOOR.
THE NEW HOTEL WOULD NOT INCLUDE ANY OFF STREET VEHICLE PARKING
AND WOULD REPLACE THE EXISTING COMMERCIAL LOADING ZONE ON
SUTTER STREET WITH A PASSENGER LOADING ZONE.
PROJECT CONSTRUCTION IS ANTICIPATED TO LAST
APPROXIMATELY 24 MONTHS. THE PRESENTATION FOCUSES
PRIMARILY ON THE PRIMARY TOPICS BROUGHT FORTH BY THE APPELLANTS
GEOLOGY AND SOILS, CONSTRUCTION NOISE AND VIBRATION
AND HISTORIC PRESERVATION. THE APPELLANTS ALSO RAISE
QUESTIONS REGARDING CONSTRUCTION, AIR QUALITY,
FREIGHT LOADING AND SHADOW. AND THE DEPARTMENT HAS
ADDRESSED THESE TOPICS IN THE APPEAL RESPONSE AS I WILL
DISCUSS IN THIS PRESENTATION. THE APPELLANTS HAVE NOT MET THE
LEGAL BURDEN OF PROOF TO DEMONSTRATE THAT THE PROJECT
COULD HAVE A SIGNIFICANT AND UNAVOIDABLE IMPACT
AND STAFF RESPECT SPEC FULLY RECOMMENDS THAT THE BOARD
AFFIRMED THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S DECISION TO
APPROVE THE FMD TO BEGIN WITH. >> STAFF WOULD LIKE TO RESPOND
TO ONE OF THE MAIN CONCERNS RAISED BY THE APPELLANTS WHICH
IS THAT THE FMD DID NOT ADEQUATELY ANALYZE THE
GEOTECHNICAL IMPACTS OF ITS CONSTRUCTION ON NEARBY
BUILDINGS. THIS CONTENTION IS INCORRECT.
FOR ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW THE DEPARTMENT CONSIDERS THE
QUESTION OF WHETHER CONSTRUCTION OF A PROJECT COULD
HAVE A SUBSTANTIAL ADVERSE EFFECT ON SOILS OR GEOLOGIC
FEATURES ON THE PROJECT SITE AND ULTIMATELY WHETHER A
PROJECT COULD BE FEASIBLY CONSTRUCTED AND SUPPORTED BY
THE UNDERLYING SITE CONDITIONS. WITH RESPECT TO THIS QUESTION,
THE GEOTECHNICAL REPORT CONCLUDED THAT THE BUILDING IS
FEASIBLE FROM A GEOTECHNICAL STANDPOINT.
ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW TAKES INTO ACCOUNT THAT THE PROJECT WOULD
BE REQUIRED TO UNDERGO MORE DETAILED REVIEW BY THE BUILDING
DEPARTMENT AT A LATER STAGE. THIS IS NOT A DEFERRAL OF
MITIGATION OR STUDY AS CLAIMED BY THE APPELLANT'S TVA
TYPICALLY OCCURS TVA REVIEW TYPICALLY OCCURS AFTER THE
SCOPE PROCESS AND PROJECT APPROVALS BUT BEFORE
CONSTRUCTION PERMITS ARE ISSUED.
THE REVIEW INCLUDES AN ASSESSMENT OF THE PROJECT'S
PROPOSED FOUNDATION SYSTEM AND ITS APPROPRIATENESS FOR THE
STRUCTURE AND GROUND CONDITIONS ON THE SITE AS WELL AS THE
POTENTIAL EFFECTS OF CONSTRUCTION ACTIVITIES.
THE PREDICTED FOUNDATION SETTLEMENT AND THE PROJECT'S
PREDICTED LONG TERM INTERACTION WITH FOUNDATIONS OF EXISTING
ADJACENT AND NEARBY STRUCTURES .
ADDITIONALLY FOR TALL BUILDINGS SUCH AS THE PROJECT AN
INDEPENDENT ENGINEERING REVIEW OF THE GEOTECHNICAL
AND STRUCTURAL DESIGN BY A FOUR PERSON PANEL OF EXPERTS WOULD
BE REQUIRED. AS SUCH, THE PROJECT EFFECTS ON
NEARBY BUILDINGS WILL BE EVALUATED AND WILL ENSURE THAT
THE BUILDING CAN BE SAFELY CONSTRUCTED.
THROUGH THIS REGULATORY PROCESS THE CITY ENSURES THAT
SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS RELATED TO GEOLOGY AND SOILS DO NOT OCCUR
AND THEREFORE SEPARATE. SECOND MITIGATION IS NOT
REQUIRED. >> SEEK REVIEW IS BASED ON
ARCHITECTURAL PLANS WHICH ILLUSTRATE THE PROPOSED PROJECT
ELEMENTS AND ASSESS FEASIBILITY BUT DO NOT INCLUDE THE DETAILED
STRUCTURAL INFORMATION FOUND IN PERMIT LEVEL OR CONSTRUCTION
LEVEL PLANS. IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE THAT
PERMIT LEVEL PLANS ARE NOT EXPECTED NOR REQUIRED FOR
ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW AFTER ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW IS
COMPLETED AND ONCE A PROJECT IS APPROVED QUALIFIED STAFF
AND OTHER CITY DEPARTMENTS WILL CONDUCT DETAILED TECHNICAL
REVIEW AND THE PROJECT WILL BE REQUIRED TO UPDATE ITS
CONSTRUCTION DOCUMENTS AS NEEDED TO ENSURE COMPLIANCE
WITH STATE AND LOCAL BUILDING CODE.
THIS REVIEW IS MANDATORY AND PROJECT SPONSORS MUST
COMPLY. THE APPELLANTS HAVE NOT
DEMONSTRATED HOW A SIGNIFICANT IMPACT COULD OCCUR WITH THE
PROJECT'S REQUIRED COMPLIANCE WITH THE DVI PROCESS AND STATE
AND LOCAL CODE WITH RESPECT TO THE CONSTRUCTION NOISE.
>> THE APPELLANTS CONTEND THAT THE CONSTRUCTION NOISE ANALYSIS
WAS IMPROPERLY CALCULATED BUT HAS DETAILED IN THE
DEPARTMENT'S APPEAL RESPONSE THE APPELLANTS ANALYSIS IS
INADEQUATE AND MISLEADING BECAUSE IT CONFLATES TWO
DIFFERENT METHODOLOGIES AND DOES NOT FOLLOW THE GENERAL
ASSESSMENT METHODOLOGIES THAT THE ASSESS THAT THE APPELLANTS
CLAIM SHOULD BE UTILIZED. COMMERCIAL OFFICES ARE NOT
CONSIDERED SENSITIVE RECEPTORS UNLESS THE COMMERCIAL RECEPTOR
IS EXPOSED TO NOISE LEVELS OF 100DB OR HIGHER.
THE FIRM IN THE NOISE ANALYSIS CONFIRMED THAT THIS WOULD NOT
BE THE CASE. >> THE FMD PROPERLY ASSESSED
THE PROJECT'S CONSTRUCTION NOISE IMPACTS IN ACCORDANCE
WITH THE CITY'S EVALUATION GUIDELINES AND THE DEPARTMENT'S
ANALYSIS USES THE CORRECT NOISE ATTENUATION FACTOR
AND EQUIPMENT USAGE FACTOR. >> THE APPELLANTS ALSO CONTEND
THAT THE PRESENCE OF MID TO HIGH RISE BUILDINGS DOWNTOWN
WOULD LEAD TO A CANYONING EFFECT FOR SOUND SUCH THAT
CONSTRUCTION NOISE COULD BE FOCUSED, REFLECTED OR AMPLIFIED
. BASED IN PART ON THIS NOTION.
THE APPELLANTS CONTEND THAT THE NOISE ANALYSIS SHOULD USE EVEN
MORE CONSERVATIVE NOISE ATTENUATION FACTOR THAT DIFFERS
FROM THE GENERAL FTA METHODOLOGY.
HOWEVER, AS SHOWN IN THIS FIGURE WITH THE RED BEING THE
PROJECT SITE AND THE YELLOW BEING THE SENSITIVE RECEPTOR,
THE NEARBY BUILDINGS ARE ORIENTED IN SUCH A WAY THAT
CONSTRUCTION NOISE FROM THE PROJECT SITE WOULD LIKELY BE
REFLECTED AWAY FROM THE NEAREST SENSITIVE RECEPTOR AND IS
UNLIKELY TO BE AMPLIFIED. THE APPELLANTS ALSO DO NOT
PROVIDE DETAILED CALCULATIONS TO SUPPORT THIS CONTENTION
AND SUCH A CALCULATION WOULD REQUIRE ACCOUNTING FOR NUMEROUS
VARIABLES INCLUDING THE COMPOSITION OF NEARBY BUILDING
MATERIALS, THE LOCATION AND THE LOCATION OF THE CONSTRUCTION
SOUND SOURCE RELATIVE TO THE RECEPTOR THE ANGLE OF NEARBY
BUILDINGS THAT COULD AFFECT SOUND AND MORE.
THEREFORE THE APPELLANTS CONTENTION IS SPECULATIVE
AND DOES NOT SUPPORT A FAIR ARGUMENT.
THE APPELLANTS ALSO CONTEND THAT THE PROJECT WOULD RESULT
IN SIGNIFICANT CONSTRUCTION VIBRATION IMPACTS TO NEARBY
STRUCTURES BUT DID NOT PROVIDE ANY SPECIFIC EVIDENCE TO
SUPPORT THIS ASSERTION. CONSISTENT WITH SECURE WE
CONSERVATIVELY ANALYZED THE PROJECT'S IMPACTS
AND DETERMINED THAT THE PROJECT COULD HAVE A SIGNIFICANT IMPACT
BUT THAT MITIGATION WOULD REDUCE THE RISK TO A LESS THAN
SIGNIFICANT LEVEL. THIS CONCLUSION IS BASED ON
SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE AS DESCRIBED IN THE FIRM AND THE
VIBRATION MITIGATION WOULD REQUIRE A PROJECT SPECIFIC
VIBRATION MANAGEMENT AND MONITORING PLAN TO EMPLOY
ALL FEASIBLE MEANS TO AVOID DAMAGE TO NEARBY STRUCTURES
INCLUDING PROCEDURES TO ACTIVELY MONITOR VIBRATION
LEVELS AT THE CONSTRUCTION SITE.
IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE THAT CONTRARY TO THE APPELLANT'S
ASSERTION, THE CALTRANS VIBRATION STANDARDS ARE
GUIDELINES ASSESSING FOR ASSESSING POTENTIAL VIBRATION
DAMAGE AND NOT BRIGHTLINE THRESHOLDS.
THIS IS BECAUSE ALL BUILDINGS ARE CONSTRUCTED SLIGHTLY
DIFFERENTLY AND ARE SUPPORTED BY DIFFERENT UNDERLYING SOIL
CONDITIONS AND SURROUNDINGS. AS A RESULT, CONSTRUCTION
VIBRATION INTERACTS WITH BUILDINGS TO VARYING DEGREES
AND THERE IS NO BRIGHT LINE THRESHOLD ABOVE WHICH VIBRATION
IMPACTS ARE CERTAIN TO OCCUR. THEREFORE THE APPELLANT'S
CONTENTION THAT ANY EXCEEDANCE OF THE THRESHOLD WOULD RESULT
IN A SIGNIFICANT IMPACT IS INCORRECT.
>> FURTHERMORE, THE APPELLANT'S CONTENTION THAT CATASTROPHIC
IRREPARABLE DAMAGE COULD OCCUR EVEN WITH STOP WORK PROVISIONS
REQUIRED BY THE VIBRATION MONITORING PLAN IS SPECULATIVE
AND THE APPELLANTS HAVE NOT MET THE LEGAL BURDEN OF PROOF OF
PROVIDING SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE TO SUPPORT A FAIR ARGUMENT THAT
THE VIBRATION MITIGATION MEASURE WOULD BE INADEQUATE.
LASTLY, WE WOULD LIKE TO BRIEFLY TOUCH ON HISTORIC
PRESERVATION. THE DEPARTMENT'S PRESERVATION
ANALYSIS WAS BASED ON THE SUBJECT BUILDINGS HISTORIC
RESOURCE EVALUATION RESPONSE WHICH IDENTIFIED ALL ADJACENT
AND NEARBY HISTORIC RESOURCES INCLUDING THE CHANCERY BUILDING
IN 44 MONTGOMERY STREET. THESE BUILDINGS WERE ACCOUNTED
FOR IN THE PRESERVATION ANALYSIS.
THE HRC ALSO CLEARLY CONCLUDED THAT THE PROPERTY IS NOT PART
OF A DESIGNATED OR ELIGIBLE HISTORIC DISTRICT, NOTING THE
SUBJECT PROPERTY DOES NOT APPEAR TO BE PART OF A
SIGNIFICANT CONCENTRATION OF HISTORICALLY OR ARCHITECTURALLY
UNIFIED BUILDINGS SUCH THAT IT WOULD RISE TO A LEVEL OF AN
ELIGIBLE HISTORIC DISTRICT. >> FINALLY, THE PROJECT'S
CONSTRUCTION WOULD NOT DEMOLISH OR MATERIALLY IMPAIR THE
CHARACTER DEFINING FEATURES ON ADJACENT PROPERTIES SUCH THAT
THEIR HISTORIC STATUS COULD BE ALTERED.
THUS NO SIGNIFICANT IMPACT RELATED TO HISTORIC RESOURCES
WOULD OCCUR. IN CONCLUSION, THE EXAMINER
FULLY SUPPORTS THE FINDINGS THAT THE PROJECT WOULD NOT
RESULT IN SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS THAT COULD NOT BE REDUCED TO A
LESS INSIGNIFICANT LEVEL WITH IMPLEMENTATION OF MITIGATION
MEASURES. THESE FINDINGS ARE BASED ON
SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE IN THE RECORD AND THE APPELLANTS HAVE
NOT PROVIDED SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE BASED ON FACTS TO
SUPPORT A FAIR ARGUMENT TO REQUIRE THE PREPARATION OF ANY
ADDITIONAL STUDIES WOULD NOT YIELD DIFFERENT RESULTS FROM
WHAT HAS ALREADY BEEN DISCLOSED IN THE FMD AND THAT YOUR
PROCESS WOULD NOT ALTER THE MANY CONCLUSIONS NOR PROVIDE
ANY MEANINGFUL ANALYSIS BEYOND WHAT WAS ALREADY CONDUCTED
IN DMD. FOR THESE REASONS THE
DEPARTMENT RESPECTFULLY RECOMMENDS THAT THE BOARD
AFFIRMS THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S DECISION TO APPROVE THE FUNDING.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR ATTENTION.
I'M JOINED BY MY COLLEAGUES CHELSEA FORDHAM AND TANYA
SHANER. WE WERE ABLE TO ANSWER ANY
QUESTIONS. >> THANK YOU.
I DO NOT SEE ANY QUESTIONS FROM MY COLLEAGUES.
AND SO NOW WE'LL GO TO THE PROJECT SPONSOR FOR UP TO TEN
MINUTES. >> GOOD AFTERNOON MELINDA.
SERJEANT FOR RUBIN, JULIUS AND ROSE.
I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF THE PROJECT SPONSOR FRONTIER
DEVELOPMENT GROUP. THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAS
PROVIDED A THOROUGH TECHNICAL RESPONSE TO APPELLANT'S
CONCERNS, EXPLAINING WHY THE PROJECT HAS NO POTENTIAL FOR
SIGNIFICANT ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS.
STARTING OFF IT'S IMPORTANT TO UNDERSTAND THE STANDARD OF
REVIEW ON APPEAL OF MMD. THE KEY QUESTION IS WHETHER
APPELLANTS HAVE PROVIDED SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE OF A FAIR
ARGUMENT THAT THE PROJECT MAY HAVE A SIGNIFICANT IMPACT.
SEQUA IS VERY CLEAR THAT NOT ALL INFORMATION RISES TO THE
LEVEL OF SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE. SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE MUST BE
SUPPORTED BY FACTS IN THE RECORD.
ARGUMENT. SPECULATION ABOUT POTENTIAL
IMPACTS INACCURATE OR ERRONEOUS INFORMATION IS NOT SUBSTANTIAL
EVIDENCE. SIMPLY PROVIDING CONSULTANT
OPINIONS THAT ARE BASED ON SPECULATION OR THAT CONTAIN
INACCURATE OR MISLEADING INFORMATION DOES NOT MEET THIS
STANDARD. FURTHER, THE COMMISSION MUST
GIVE THE CITY THE BENEFIT DOUBT ON THE LEGITIMATE DISPUTED
ISSUES OF CREDIBILITY IN THE EVIDENCE PRESENTED.
APPELLANTS HAVE NOT MET THIS STANDARD.
THEIR APPEAL LETTERS AND SUPPORTING DOCUMENTS TOUCH
ON A BROAD RANGE OF TOPICS ESSENTIALLY RAISING EVERY
POSSIBLE CONCERN TO SEE IF ANYTHING WILL STICK.
BUT THEY DO NOT PROVIDE SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE UNDER
SEQUA. INSTEAD THEIR MATERIALS ARE
FILLED WITH CONJECTURE, OPINIONS, ERRONEOUS OR
MISLEADING STATEMENTS AND SPECULATION UNSUPPORTED BY
FACT. THIS IS NOT ENOUGH TO OVERTURN
THE MMD. BY CONTRAST, THE MMD IS
SUPPORTED BY SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE.
ITS 130 PAGE DOCUMENT WITH ADDENDA CONTAINING DETAILED
TECHNICAL STUDIES PREPARED BY QUALIFIED INDEPENDENT
CONSULTANTS APPLYING ESTABLISHED REVIEW STANDARDS
AND SUBJECT TO THOROUGH REVIEW BY DEPARTMENT STAFF.
PLAINTIFFS RESPONSE TO THIS APPEAL HAS WALKED THROUGH EACH
OF APPELLANT'S CONCERNS IN DETAIL.
THEY EXPLAINED WHY THEIR COMMENTS AND SUPPORTING
MATERIALS DO NOT CONTAIN SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE.
WE PROVIDED SIMILAR INFORMATION IN OUR BRIEF.
>> APPELLANTS CONCERNS WERE ALSO RAISED IN THEIR INITIAL
APPEALS TO THE 70IN THE PLANNING COMMISSION APRIL
AND WERE APPROPRIATELY REJECTED AT THAT TIME.
NOW WE'LL TOUCH BASE ON JUST A FEW OF THE TOPICS THAT WERE
RAISED. FIRST, APPELLANTS SPECULATE
THAT THE PROJECT COULD HAVE GEOTECHNICAL IMPACTS RELATED TO
SOIL SETTLEMENT, DE-WATERING OR LIQUEFACTION.
THESE CLAIMS HAVE NO FACTUAL BASIS.
THE MANDY APPROPRIATELY ANALYZES THE POTENTIAL FOR
IMPACTS TO SOIL OR GEOLOGIC FEATURES AND WHETHER A PROJECT
COULD BE FEASIBLY CONSTRUCTED BASED ON PRELIMINARY
GEOTECHNICAL INVESTIGATION REPORT.
THIS DOCUMENT WAS PREPARED BY A LICENSED CONSULTANT IN THIS
CASE LINEN THAT HAS MORE THAN FIVE DECADES OF EXPERTISE
AND EXPERIENCE IN THE FIELD. IN DETERMINING THAT NO
SIGNIFICANT IMPACT COULD OCCUR. THE MANDY ALSO PROPERLY
ACCOUNTS FOR THE EXISTENCE OF STRINGENT LOCAL AND STATE
BUILDING CODE REQUIREMENTS AND PRE-CONSTRUCTION REVIEW
PROCESSES FOR FOUNDATION AND STRUCTURAL DESIGN.
AMONG OTHER THINGS, THESE STANDARDS REQUIRE INDEPENDENT
STRUCTURAL AND GEOTECHNICAL DESIGN LEVEL REVIEW BY
QUALIFIED PROFESSIONALS. BASED ON CONSTRUCTION LEVEL
DRAWINGS AND CALCULATIONS THAT ARE DEVELOPED DURING BUILDING
PERMIT REVIEW, THE PROJECT MUST IMPLEMENT THESE REQUIREMENTS AS
A MATTER OF LAW. SEQUA IS CLEAR THAT LOCAL
AGENCIES MAY RELY ON COMPLIANCE WITH STATE AND LOCAL BUILDING
CODE REQUIREMENTS LIKE THESE IN DETERMINING POTENTIAL FOR
IMPACT. SO THE MANDATE IS CONSISTENT
WITH BOTH THE CITY'S STANDARD PROCESS FOR STRUCTURAL REVIEW
AND SEQUA STANDARDS. APPELLANTS PROVIDE NO
SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE THAT AN IMPACT MAY OCCUR AT THIS
PARTICULAR SITE. DESPITE THESE WELL-ESTABLISHED
REQUIREMENTS. SECONDLY, APPELLANTS CLAIM
WITHOUT SUPPORT THAT THE PROJECT MAY RESULT
IN CONSTRUCTION NOISE IMPACTS. THEY PROVIDE MULTIPLE LETTERS
FROM THEIR PRIVATE CONSULTANT WILSON EARING ATTACKING THE
AMENDED NOISE ANALYSIS. HOWEVER, THESE MATERIALS
CONTAIN INACCURATE AND MISLEADING INFORMATION THAT
DOES NOT RISE TO THE LEVEL OF SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE AS
DISCUSSED BY STAFF. WILSON CLAIMS AMONG OTHER
THINGS, THAT THE MONDI SHOULD HAVE APPLIED A USAGE FACTOR OF
ONE. UNDER THE FDA GENERAL
ASSESSMENT METHODOLOGY HOWEVER, A SUPPLEMENTAL ANALYSIS
PREPARED BY THE PROJECT'S NOISE CONSULTANT SHOWS THAT EVEN WITH
THE REQUESTED USAGE FACTOR APPLIED THE PROJECT STILL WOULD
NOT RESULT IN A SIGNIFICANT IMPACT.
SO THAT CONCERN IS MERITLESS. WILSON ALSO ATTEMPTS TO CHERRY
PICK BETWEEN REVIEW STANDARDS APPLIED IN DIFFERENT FDA
ASSESSMENT METHODOLOGIES WHILE IGNORING OTHER NUANCED FACTORS.
THEY SPECULATE THAT IF ONLY SPECIFIC HIGHLY CONSERVATIVE
REVIEW CRITERIA WERE APPLIED IN A VACUUM, THE PROJECT MIGHT
THEN EXCEED NOISE THRESHOLDS. THIS IS AN IMPROPER METHODOLOGY
DESIGNED TO GENERATE AN UNREALISTIC FORECAST OF IMPACTS
AND SIMPLY DOES NOT RISE TO THE LEVEL OF SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE
UNDER SEQUA. SIMILARLY, APPELLANTS PROVIDE
NO SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE TO SUPPORT THEIR CLAIMS THAT THE
PROJECT COULD RESULT IN SIGNIFICANT VIBRATION
IMPACTS. DESPITE APPLIED MITIGATIONS,
THE MANDY FINDS THAT NEIGHBORING BUILDINGS COULD BE
AFFECTED BY CONSTRUCTION VIBRATION BUT APPLIES
APPROPRIATE SITE SPECIFIC MONITORING AND VIBRATION
MEASURES THAT WOULD REDUCE THAT IMPACT TO LESS THAN
SIGNIFICANT. THE VIBRATION MITIGATIONS
ADOPTED ARE STANDARDS THAT HAVE BEEN APPLIED FOR OTHER
SIMILARLY SITUATED SITES NEAR HISTORIC RESOURCES ACROSS THE
CITY SUCCESSFULLY. AMONG OTHER ITEMS, THE
VIBRATION MITIGATION REQUIRES A PRE-CONSTRUCTION SURVEY TO
DOCUMENT THE CONDITION OF ADJACENT BUILDINGS.
PREPARATION OF A MONITORING PLAN BY A QUALIFIED CONSULTANT
THAT WILL BE SUBJECT TO STAFF REVIEW AND APPROVAL.
ESTABLISHING MAXIMUM ALLOWABLE VIBRATION THRESHOLDS
AND METHODS FOR VIBRATION MONITORING.
SUBMITTAL OF MONTHLY REPORTS OF ANY VIBRATION EXCEEDANCE
AND ACTIONS TO REDUCE VIBRATION SHOULD THAT OCCUR.
AND PERIODIC INSPECTIONS THROUGHOUT CONSTRUCTION WITH
ANY REQUIRED MEDIATIONS OVERSEEN BY A QUALIFIED
PRESERVATION PROFESSIONAL. APPELLANTS PROVIDE NO
SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE THAT SIGNIFICANT VIBRATION IMPACTS
COULD OCCUR DESPITE THESE DETAILED MEASURES.
FURTHER, APPELLANTS CLAIMS THAT THE MANDY IMPROPERLY DEFERS
VIBRATION MITIGATION ARE INCORRECT SEQUA EXPRESSLY
ALLOWS DETAILS OF PROJECT MITIGATION TO BE DEVELOPED
AFTER APPROVAL WHEN IT IS IMPRACTICAL OR INFEASIBLE TO
INCLUDE THEM DURING ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW.
AS LONG AS THE MANDY COMMITS ITSELF TO MITIGATION ACTIONS
ADOPTS PERFORMANCE STANDARDS THEY ACHIEVE AND IDENTIFIES THE
TYPES OF POTENTIAL ACTIONS THAT CAN BE FEASIBLY ACHIEVED BY
THOSE STANDARDS. THE PROJECT'S MITIGATION MEETS
THOSE CRITERIA. APPELLANTS ARE ALSO ARGUE THAT
THE PROJECT COULD HAVE SIGNIFICANT HISTORIC IMPACTS ON
HISTORIC RESOURCES. THEY PROVIDE A LETTER FROM KATY
PATTERSON CONSULTING CLAIMING THAT THE MANDY DID NOT
ACCURATELY DESCRIBE NEARBY RESOURCES AND FAILED TO ANALYZE
A THEORETICAL OR HISTORICAL DISTRICT IN THE SAME BLOCK.
BOTH CLAIMS ARE INCORRECT. THE MANDY AND SUPPORTING
MATERIALS THOROUGHLY DESCRIBE NEARBY RESOURCES AND INCLUDE A
FINDING THAT BUILDINGS ON THE SUBJECT BLOCK WOULD NOT QUALIFY
AS A HISTORIC DISTRICT. APPELLANTS PROVIDE NO EVIDENCE
SUGGESTING OTHERWISE. THE MANDY DOES PROVIDE
SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE THAT NO IMPACT HISTORIC RESOURCES WOULD
OCCUR INCLUDING DETAILED ANALYSIS RELATED TO GEOLOGY,
NOISE AND VIBRATION. OVERALL, APPELLANTS HAVE NOT
MET THEIR BURDEN TO OVERTURN THE MANDY BECAUSE THEY PROVIDE
NO SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE SUPPORTING A FAIR ARGUMENT OF
SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS. WE ASK THAT THE COMMISSION
UPHOLD THE MANDY. >> THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT. I DO NOT SEE COMMENTS OR
QUESTIONS FROM COLLEAGUES AND SO WE WILL NOW OPEN PUBLIC
COMMENTS. TWO SPEAKERS IN OPPOSITION TO
THE APPEAL AND IN SUPPORT OF THE PROJECT WHO WILL HAVE TWO
MINUTES EACH. >> MADAM CLERK, WELCOME TO OUR
FIRST SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON PRESIDENT
AND MEMBERS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
THANK YOU FOR GIVING ME THE OPPORTUNITY TO SPEAK TODAY.
MY NAME IS SUSAN MENDOZA AND I AM A FIELD REPRESENTATIVE FOR
THE NORCAL CARPENTERS UNION. I AM SPEAKING TODAY ON BEHALF
OF THE WORKING MEN AND WOMEN WHO HAVE FOR OVER 100 YEARS
BUILT AND MAINTAINED THIS BEAUTIFUL CITY.
I AM HERE IN OPPOSITION TO THE APPEAL AND IN FULL SUPPORT OF
THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S APPROVAL OF THE PROPOSED 570
MARKET STREET HOTEL DEVELOPMENT.
FOR LABOR THIS PROJECT REPRESENTS MORE THAN
CONSTRUCTION. IT REPRESENTS STEADY MIDDLE
CLASS JOBS THAT ALLOW OUR MEMBERS TO BUILD THE
COMMUNITIES THEY SERVE. EVERY MAJOR PROJECT LIKE THIS
KEEPS HUNDREDS OF SKILLED UNION WORKERS EMPLOYED DURING A TIME
WHEN WE DO NOT SEE SIGNIFICANT CONSTRUCTION ACTIVITY IN SAN
FRANCISCO. KEEP IN MIND THAT A COMMITMENT
TO USE A UNION GENERAL CONTRACTOR CREATES OPPORTUNITY
FOR FAMILIES SUSTAINING CAREERS THAT HELP STABILIZE SAN
FRANCISCO'S ECONOMY AT A TIME WHEN THE DOWNTOWN CORE URGENTLY
NEEDS INVESTMENT. THE PLANNING COMMISSION DID ITS
DUE DILIGENCE. THE ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW WAS
THOROUGH, TRANSPARENT AND GROUNDED IN SUBSTANTIAL
EVIDENCE. THE FINAL MANDY IDENTIFIES
IMPACTS AND REQUIRES MITIGATION MEASURES THAT OUR MEMBERS ARE
FULLY PREPARED TO MEET. THE APPEAL DOES NOT PRESENT NEW
INFORMATION OR ANY EVIDENCE OF SIGNIFICANT UNADDRESSED
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS. WHAT IT WOULD DO IS INTRODUCE
UNNECESSARY DELAYS IN JOBS AND UNDERMINE CONFIDENCE IN A
FAIR AND PREDICTABLE AND PREDICTABLE CYCLE PROCESS.
SAN FRANCISCO CANNOT AFFORD TO STALL RESPONSIBLE DEVELOPMENT
THAT BOTH PROTECTS THE ENVIRONMENT AND PUTS PEOPLE TO
WORK. THAT'S WHY I RESPECTFULLY URGE
YOU TO AFFIRM THE APPROVAL OF THE FINAL MTD.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME AND CONSIDERATION IN THIS
MATTER AND THANK YOU FOR STANDING WITH WORKING PEOPLE.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK AND IT'S A PLEASURE TO BE
IN FRONT OF THE STAFF AND THE DISTINGUISHED MEMBERS OF THE
FULL BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS RUDY GONZALES FROM
THE SAN FRANCISCO BUILDING AND CONSTRUCTION TRADES
COUNCIL. I REPRESENT 27 LOCALS HERE
IN THE CITY AND I WISH I COULD BECAUSE I RARELY TAKE A PASS AT
TUGGING AT YOUR HEARTSTRINGS. I WISH I COULD MAKE THIS ABOUT
UNION OR NONUNION OR HIGH ROAD JOBS OR LOW ROAD JOBS.
>> BUT THIS IS AS SUPERVISOR SOUDER SAID, A VERY TECHNICAL
BUT IMPORTANT STEP IN THE PROCESS AS IT RELATES TO
WHETHER OR NOT YOU BELIEVE THAT THERE IS SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE
HERE AND IF A IIR IS GOING TO BE THE RESULTS OF THAT.
>> SO FIRST UNDER SEQUOIA THE APPELLANTS HAVE TO PROVIDE YOU
WITH SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE SHOWING THAT THE PROJECT MAY
CAUSE A SIGNIFICANT ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT.
WE DON'T BELIEVE THEY'VE MET THAT BURDEN RESPECTFULLY.
THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S ANALYSIS IS THOROUGH.
IT USES ACCEPTED TECHNICAL STANDARDS AND CLEARLY
DEMONSTRATED THAT WITH MITIGATION WITH MITIGATION THAT
THIS PROJECT WILL NOT RESULT IN SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS.
I'M GOING TO TOUCH ON A COUPLE OF LITTLE SPOTS HERE ON THE
GEOLOGY AND CONSTRUCTION IMPACTS.
I THINK THAT'S BEEN RAISED SIGNIFICANTLY.
THE DEPARTMENT RELIED ON A QUALIFIED GEOTECH STUDY
REQUIRED COMPLIANCE WITH STRICT BUILDING CODES HERE IN THE CITY
AND MONITORING THE APPELLANT'S CLAIMS ABOUT CATASTROPHIC
SETTLEMENT OR DAMAGE OUR SPECULATIVE AND IMPORTANTLY NOT
SUPPORTED BY THE PROJECT SPECIFIC EVIDENCE.
ALTHOUGH THERE ARE REASONABLE CONSIDERATIONS FOR ANYONE TO
HAVE ON A NEIGHBORING PROJECT. I ALSO WANT TO TOUCH ON LOADING
TRANSPORTATION AND SHADOWS. THOSE ARE MATTERS THAT
TYPICALLY COME BEFORE THIS BODY.
THE DEPARTMENT CORRECTLY FOUND THAT NO SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS
WERE PRESENT. THE APPELLANTS OFFERED NO
CONTRARY DATA ON THOSE POINTS, ONLY PHOTOS AND SOMEWHAT
GENERALIZED CONCERNS ACROSS EVERY SINGLE TOPIC RAISED BY
THE APPELLANTS. THE PATTERNS THE SAME.
THE DEPARTMENT HAS PROVIDED EVIDENCE AND MITIGATION AND THE
APPELLANTS PROVIDE SPECULATION SECRET DOES NOT REQUIRE AN AIR
BASED ON SPECULATION FOR ALL THESE REASONS AND BECAUSE THE
PROJECT HAS BEEN RESPONSIBLY REVIEWED WITH ENFORCEABLE
MITIGATION I RESPECTFULLY REQUEST YOU AFFIRM THE PLANNING
COMMISSION'S ADOPTION OF THE MITIGATED NEGATIVE DECLARATION
AND DENY THE THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR IS MY NAME IS ON
AND SITTING HERE REPRESENTING UNITE HERE LOCAL TO THE HOTEL
WORKERS UNION IN THE CITY. I'M NOT GOING TO REPEAT A LOT
OF WHAT WAS JUST SAID ON I'M IN AGREEMENT WITH MY SIBLINGS
IN LABOR AND RUDY GONZALEZ WHO JUST SPOKE ABOUT WHAT IT'S NOT
TUGGING AT YOUR HEARTSTRINGS. WE CAN DO THAT AND THAT'S
IMPORTANT FOR US AND OUR MEMBERS.
BUT ON THE SPECIFIC MERITS OF THE APPEAL WE'RE URGING YOU
REJECT THE APPEAL AND SUPPORT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT'S FINAL
MITIGATED NEGATIVE DECLARATION. WE DO NOT BELIEVE THE
APPELLANTS HAVE PROVIDED THE SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE THAT
SIEGEL REQUIRES TO SHOW THIS PROJECT COULD CAUSE SIGNIFICANT
ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACTS AND IN REALLY EVERY CATEGORY AND RUDY
JUST WENT THROUGH A NUMBER OF THEM.
THE DEPARTMENT'S FINDINGS ARE GROUNDED IN EVIDENCE AND THE
APPEAL IS NOT SO WE URGE YOU STRONGLY TO AFFIRM THE FMD
AND DENY THE APPEAL. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO
PROVIDE PUBLIC COMMENT ON BEHALF OF THE APPELLANT EXCUSE
ME ON BEHALF OF THE PROJECT SPONSOR AGAINST THE APPELLANT?
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
>> PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED.
SO LAST WE'RE GOING TO INVITE THE APPELLANTS TO PRESENT A
REBUTTAL ARGUMENT. EACH OF THEM WILL GET TWO
MINUTES AND WE'LL START WITH MR. FLYNN.
>> THANK YOU, BRIAN FLYNN AGAIN FOR FOR MONTGOMERY.
>> I REALLY THINK WE JUST NEED THEIR BACKING UP AND WHAT I
STARTED THIS HEARING WITH WAS TALKING ABOUT THIS STANDARD
THIS FAIR ARGUMENT STANDARD WHERE IF YOU'VE GOT EXPERT
EVIDENCE IN THE RECORD SAYING THAT THERE MAY BE A SIGNIFICANT
IMPACT, IT IS NOT THE BOARD'S JOB TO BE WEIGHING THAT AGAINST
AGAINST CONTRARY EVIDENCE OR AGAINST WHAT OTHER EXPERTS
THINK. AND IF YOU GO THROUGH THE THE
PRESENTATION BY STAFF AND THE APPLICANT, A LOT OF THAT IS
JUST TRYING TO THROW OUR EXPERTS UNDER THE BUS.
THEY'RE TRYING TO SAY OUR EXPERTS ARE INACCURATE
AND THEREFORE SPECULATIVE AND YOU SHOULDN'T AND YOU
SHOULDN'T FOLLOW THEM. THAT IS A DISAGREEMENT ABOUT
HOW METHODOLOGY WAS DONE. >> DIFFERENCE IN HOW
CALCULATIONS WERE DONE BASED ON THE CONDITIONS FOR THIS
PROJECT. >> AGAIN, YOU KNOW, ACCORDING
TO THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT IS COMPLETELY REASONABLE TO ASSUME
THAT SOUND IS GOING TO ATTENUATE LIKE IT DOES IN AN
OPEN FIELD ON MARKET STREET IN THE FINANCIAL DISTRICT.
THAT IS NOT A REASONABLE ASSUMPTION.
BUT THAT'S NOT THE POINT HERE. WE'RE NOT JUST TRYING TO TAKE
DOWN THE PLAYING DEPARTMENT'S EXPERTS.
THE POINT IS THAT WE HAVE EXPERTS IN THE RECORD.
WE HAVE EXPERTS ON NOISE. WE HAVE EXPERTS ON HISTORICAL
RESOURCES. THE OTHER APPELLANT HAS EXPERT
ON GEOTECHNICAL RISKS THAT HAVE I AND THEY THESE ARE THESE ARE
CREDENTIALED EXPERTS. >> THEY I DON'T THINK THEIR
EXPERTISE IS BEING CALLED INTO QUESTION IN ANY WAY.
>> THEY HAVE DONE THEIR OWN REVIEW.
THEY HAVE DECIDED THAT THIS PROJECT MAY RESULT
IN SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS. SO THEREFORE MORE AND MORE IS
NOT THE PROPER LEVEL OF SKILL REVIEW FOR THIS PROJECT AND IT
HAS TO GO THROUGH THE AIR PROCESS VERY QUICKLY.
>> IN OTHER WORDS A PLANNING HAD INSINUATED THAT AN AIR WILL
JUST PRODUCE THE SAME RESULTS HERE.
THAT'S NOT THE POINT. YOU KNOW, IT IS A PROCEDURAL
VIOLATION OF SEQUOYAH TO PROCEED WITH AN AMENDED WHEN
YOU SHOULD HAVE DONE IN AIR THE AIR GIVES HEIGHTENED COMMENT
PROTECTIONS AND ALSO GIVES MORE PROTECTIONS TO THE CITY WHEN
THEY MAKE THEIR DECISION THAT YOU CAN THEN DEFER TO YOUR
EXPERTS AND NOT PAY ATTENTION TO OUR EXPERTS ON THIS AND OUR
EXPERTS HAVE ESTABLISHED THIS ACT.
>> SO AN AIR IS REQUIRED. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. AND AND NOW FROM THE SECOND
APPELLANT. >> GOOD AFTERNOON ANNA SHIM CO
FOR THE APPELLANT. >> WE ALSO HAVE SUBMITTED
CREDIBLE EVIDENCE FROM TWO EXPERTS ONE NOISE AND VIBRATION
AND ONE STRUCTURAL ENGINEER OPINING THE PROJECT MAY HAVE A
SIGNIFICANT MAY HAVE SIGNIFICANT IMPACTS.
THEREFORE AN AIR IS LEGALLY REQUIRED.
>> IT'S NOT YOUR JOB TO JUDGE WHICH EXPERT IS RIGHT.
>> AS TO VIBRATION WHILE THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT RESPONDED
THAT REAL TIME VIBRATION MONITORING CAN ADDRESS THE
ISSUE THE MITIGATION MEASURE ITSELF DOES NOT SPECIFICALLY
REQUIRE THAT AND IT SHOULD DO SO.
THE MITIGATION MEASURE IS SIMPLY FLAWED.
IT ANTICIPATES SIGNIFICANT AND UNAVOIDABLE IMPACTS
IN DAMAGE FROM CONSTRUCTION. >> IT ESTABLISHES MAXIMUM
LEVELS OF VIBRATION BUT THEN IT'S ONLY HONORED IN THE BREACH
AND THUS IMPACTS WILL OCCUR. >> AND THERE'S NO EVIDENCE THAT
THERE ARE MEANS TO ACHIEVE THE STATED PERFORMANCE STANDARD ON
CONSTRUCTION NOISE THE EMOND STATES THAT CONSTRUCTION NOISE
20FT AWAY WOULD BE UP TO 99 DBA.
>> THIS EXCEEDS BOTH FEDERAL AND STATE AGENCY HEALTH
STANDARDS. WHERE WORKERS ARE REQUIRED TO
WEAR HEARING PROTECTION WHEN NOISE IS OVER AN 80 DB 85 DBA
LEVEL. AS NOTED, THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT STATED THAT THE ON AIR PROCESS WOULD NOT SHOW ANY
DIFFERENT RESULTS THAT MAY AND MAY NOT BE TRUE.
>> HOWEVER, WE WOULD GET RID OF THE FICTION THAT A MITIGATED
NEGATIVE DECLARATION IS FORCED TO MAINTAIN THAT THERE ARE NO
SIGNIFICANT UNAVOIDABLE IMPACTS THAT THE DECISION MAKERS NEED
TO BALANCE AND WEIGH AND DECIDE WHETHER APPROVING THE PROJECT
IS WORTHY OF OVERCOMING THOSE IMPACTS.
WE HOPE THAT YOU WILL ORDER THAT AN AIR BE PREPARED.
>> AND WE THANK YOU FOR LISTENING.
>> >> ALL RIGHT. AND WITH THAT, THIS PUBLIC
HEARING HAS BEEN HELD AND IS NOW FILED.
>> SUPERVISOR SAUTER, THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND I WANT
TO THANK EVERYONE WHO PARTICIPATE PATED AND FOR MY
COLLEAGUES AS WELL. I WANT TO MAYBE SUMMARIZE WHAT
I'VE HEARD AND THEN I'LL MAKE A MOTION.
AS WE'VE SEEN IN THE PAST HOUR ,THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT HAS
EXPLAINED THAT THEY PREPARED A MITIGATED NEGATIVE DECLARATION
AND AMENDED AS YOU'VE HEARD IT REFERRED TO.
IT'S A 130 PAGE DOCUMENT IN THIS CASE WHICH IDENTIFIED
MITIGATION MEASURES THAT REDUCE ALL POTENTIAL IMPACTS TO LEVELS
BELOW THE LEVEL OF SIGNIFICANCE FOR EXAMPLE REDUCING ANY NOISE
VIBRATION AIR QUALITY, CULTURAL RESOURCE IMPACTS PLANNING
DEPARTMENT ALSO IDENTIFIED REGULATORY REQUIREMENTS THAT
WOULD APPLY AND WOULD ENSURE THAT THERE ARE NO IMPACTS FOR
EXAMPLE, THOSE RELATED TO GEOLOGY AND SOILS.
THIS REVIEW HAS BEEN DONE OVER SEVERAL YEARS AND THE PROJECT
IN THIS CASE WAS FIRST PROPOSED SIX YEARS AGO IN 2019.
FROM WHAT I'VE LEARNED I BELIEVE THAT THE APPELLANTS
HAVE NOT MET THEIR BURDEN UNDER SQUAT TO SHOW THAT THERE MAY BE
ANY IMPACTS NOT ALREADY ADEQUATELY ADDRESSED THROUGH
THE AMENDED. THEY HAVE NOT SATISFIED THE
FAIR ARGUMENT STANDARD BECAUSE THEIR ARGUMENTS ARE
SPECULATIVE. THEY'RE NOT BASED ON
SUBSTANTIAL EVIDENCE WHICH NEED TO BE BASED ON FACTS.
THE APPELLANTS MAY DISAGREE WITH THE DEPARTMENT'S FINDINGS
BUT THEIR ARGUMENTS ARE NOT SUPPORTED BY SUBSTANTIAL
EVIDENCE IN THIS CASE. EARLIER THIS YEAR I THINK IT'S
IMPORTANT TO NOTE THE PROJECT'S MMD WAS ALSO APPEALED TO THE
PLANNING COMMISSION WHERE THAT APPEAL WAS DENIED.
AND GIVEN ALL THIS I BELIEVE THE REMEDY IS ADEQUATE WELL
DONE IN THIS PROJECT. DOES NOT WARRANT FURTHER
ENVIRONMENTAL REVIEW. SO WITH THAT IN MIND I WOULD
LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION AND THAT MOTION WOULD BE TO APPROVE ITEM
39 AFFIRMING THE PLANNING COMMISSION'S APPROVAL OF THE
FINAL MITIGATED NEGATIVE DECLARATION AND TABLING ITEMS
40 AND 41. >> ALL RIGHT.
>> IS THERE A SECOND FOR THAT MOTION SECONDED BY MAHMUD?
AND IF THERE'S NO FURTHER DISCUSSION WE WILL VOTE ON THE
MOTION MADE BY SUPERVISOR SAUTER SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD TO AFFIRM THE FINAL MITIGATED NEGATIVE DECLARATION
AND APPROVING ITEM NUMBER 39 AND TABLING ITEMS NUMBER 40
AND 41. MADAM CLERK WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO APPROVE ITEM 39 AND TABLE 40
AND 41 SUPERVISOR DORSI DORSI I SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN.
ALL RIGHT GENTLEMEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR FOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I
AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EITHER ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION
ITEM NUMBER 39 AS APPROVED ITEMS 40 AND 41 ARE TABLED.
AND THAT CONCLUDES OUR 3 P.M. SPECIAL OUR SECOND 3 P.M.
SPECIAL ORDER. >> AND NOW WE WILL GO BACK TO I
BELIEVE MADAM CLERK. >> ITEM 35.
ITEM 35 THIS IS A MOTION TO APPOINT BARBARA ELLEN WALDEN
RESIDENCY REQUIREMENT WAIVED AND MONIQUE GUIDRY TO THE EARLY
CHILDHOOD COMMUNITY OVERSIGHT AND ADVISORY COMMITTEE.
TERMS ENDING OCTOBER EIGHT, 2027.
>> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM 35.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER
EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
MANDELL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUDER
SORTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN EITHER
ATTORNEYS WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 36 ITEM 36 THIS IS A MOTION TO APPOINT
CHANEL WILLIAMS JULIA DENTON YEO AND WILLIAM WILLIAM LEMMON
TO THE OUR CITY OUR HOME OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE TERMS
ENDING APRIL 22ND 2027 SUPERVISOR FIELDER THANK YOU
PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN. COLLEAGUES I HAVE THE UTMOST
RESPECT FOR MR. WILLIAM LEMMON WHO HAS BEEN NOMINATED FOR
EIGHT. I HAVE PERSONALLY BENEFITED
FROM HIS LEADERSHIP AT AT THE CASTRO COUNTRY CLUB.
>> AS SOMEONE WHO HAS TAKEN PART IN ACA MEETINGS THE PAST
FEW YEARS AS I HAVE FAMILY THAT CONTINUED TO RECKON WITH
ADDICTION AND DYSFUNCTIONAL FAMILY ISSUES, HOWEVER, I'D
LIKE TO HAVE A VOTE ON THIS SEAT SEPARATE FROM THE REST OF
THE SEATS AND EXPRESS MY CONCERN ABOUT WHAT IT MEANS.
THIS SEAT REQUIRES SOMEONE WITH EXPERIENCE IN HOMELESSNESS OR
MENTAL HEALTH ADVOCACY AND HIS VOTE TODAY WILL UNSEAT A LONG
TIME HOMELESSNESS ADVOCATE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, JENNIFER
FRIEDEN. BACH HAS COMMITTED THE LAST 34
YEARS TO ENDING MASS HOMELESSNESS BY ADDRESSING
STRUCTURAL CAUSES. HER WORK HAS BEEN DEVELOPING
CONSENSUS ON SOLUTIONS ON THE HOMELESS CRISIS CENTERED ON THE
EXPERIENCE AND EXPERTISE OF THOSE WHO HAVE SURVIVED OR
STILL LIVING WITHOUT HOUSING. SHE HAS DEVELOPED HISTORIC DATA
DRIVEN POLICIES WITH POLICYMAKERS ACROSS THE
POLITICAL SPECTRUM INCLUDING WRITING IN PASSING THE ORIGINAL
OUR CITY OUR HOME MEASURE WHICH ESTABLISHED THIS VERY
COMMITTEE. >> AND I'M DEEPLY CONCERNED
THAT HER REMOVAL IS RETALIATION FOR HER OUTSPOKEN SUPPORT OF
THE EMPIRICALLY PROVEN HOUSING FIRST MODEL THAT THIS MEASURE
SUPPORTS. BY TAXING THE WEALTHIEST
CORPORATIONS IN THE CITY ACROSS 26 RIGOROUS STUDIES DOING
HOUSING FIRST DECREASE HOMELESSNESS BY 88% OUR CITY
OUR HOME FUNDED PROGRAMS HAVE ADDED IN SUSTAINED MORE THAN
5298 TOTAL UNITS OF CAPACITY SINCE THE FUND'S INCEPTION
IN FISCAL YEAR 21 WITH A NET 807 UNITS OF CAPACITY ADDED
IN FISCAL YEAR 24 BETWEEN 2023 AND 2024 OVER 90 7% OF
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING RESIDENTS RETAIN THEIR HOUSING AS THE
CITY CONTINUED IMPLEMENTATION OF NEW PROGRAMING SINCE THE
LAUNCH OF THE FUND, THE NUMBER OF HOUSEHOLDS SERVED HAS GROWN
YEAR OVER YEAR 18,500 PEOPLE SERVED IN 2022, 27,000 IN 2023
AND 37,500 IN 2024. >> HER REMOVAL PORTENDS FURTHER
UNDERMINING OF THE CITY OUR HOME MEASURE WHICH HAS BEEN THE
FOREMOST EFFECTIVE SOLUTION FOR GETTING PEOPLE PERMANENT OFF
THE STREETS AND INTO HOUSING. HER APPLICATION TO BE
REAPPOINTED CAME WITH SEVERAL LETTERS AND EMAILS OF SUPPORT
FROM EXPERTS IN THE CITY'S HOMELESS ADVOCACY NETWORK.
>> IT IS BAFFLING TO ME THAT ONE OF THE MAIN ADVOCATES
BEHIND THIS MEASURE THAT CREATED THIS BODY IS BEING
REMOVED. HER REMOVAL IS VERY CONCERNING
FOR ANYONE INVESTED IN TRULY SOLVING HOMELESSNESS RATHER
THAN MOVING PEOPLE FROM ONE BLOCK TO ANOTHER.
SO WITH THAT ALL I'M ASKING FOR IS A VOTE TO SPECIFICALLY VOTE
ON SEAT EIGHT. SO I WILL MOVE TO DIVIDE THE
QUESTION. >> I THINK IT'S THE SOLE RIGHT
OF ANY MEMBER TO TO DIVIDE A QUESTION.
SO I DON'T THINK WE NEED TO VOTE ON THAT.
>> I THINK WE CAN. AND IF FURTHER COMMENTS ARE ON
SPECIFICALLY ON LEMON'S APPOINTMENT, PERHAPS WE OUGHT
TO TAKE WILLIAMS AND DE ANTONIO FIRST AND THEN WE CAN DISCUSS.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, I WOULD SUGGEST YOU TAKE THE DIVIDED
PORTION FIRST BECAUSE WHETHER IT WINS OR LOSES WHAT WE DO IS
WE FOLD IT BACK INTO THE REMAINDER OF THE ITEM.
>> OKAY? OKAY.
OKAY. ALL RIGHT.
SO WE ALL RIGHT. SO WE WILL CONTINUE TO DISCUSS.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN.
I AM INCREDIBLY PROUD TO SUPPORT BILLY LEMON'S
APPOINTMENT TO THE OUR CITY OUR HOME OVERSIGHT COMMITTEE.
HE IS AN EXTRAORDINARY LEADER FROM THE LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY
AS WELL AS FROM OUR RECOVERY COMMUNITY.
AND FOR REASONS I'LL EXPLAIN I THINK HIS PERSPECTIVE AND HIS
VOICE ARE DESPERATELY NEEDED IN OUR CITY RIGHT NOW.
MR. LEMON LEADS AN INSTITUTION THAT HAS PLAYED AND CONTINUES
TO PLAY A FOUNDATION ROLE IN MY OWN RECOVERY JOURNEY AND IT'S
NO EXAGGERATION FOR ME TO SAY THAT THE CASTRO COUNTRY CLUB HE
LEADS HAS HELPED TO SAVE MY LIFE AND I KNOW I AM AMONG
HUNDREDS AND PERHAPS THOUSANDS OF OTHERS IN THIS CITY WHO FEEL
THAT WAY. I HAVE SEEN THE SAVING GRACE
THIS INSTITUTION EXTENDS TO THOSE STRUGGLING WITH ADDICTION
AND ALCOHOLISM INCLUDING THOSE WHO ARE HOMELESS.
AND THAT IS PRECISELY BECAUSE OF THE INCLUSIVE, WELCOMING
AND COLLABORATIVE APPROACH THAT BILLY LEMON EMPLOYS IN HIS
LEADERSHIP OF THE CASTRO COUNTRY CLUB.
MR. LEMON LED THIS INSTITUTION OUT OF ITS DARKEST DAYS OF NEAR
CLOSURE SOME 15 YEARS AGO TO BECOME A THRIVING SOBER
COMMUNITY SPACE THAT I BELIEVE SHOULD BE A MODEL FOR MORE
RECOVERY COMMUNITY SPACES LIKE IT CITYWIDE IN THE FUTURE.
THE SEAT BEING CONTESTED HERE IS FOR AN INDIVIDUAL WITH
EXPERIENCE ADVOCATING ON HOMELESSNESS OR MENTAL HEALTH
ISSUES AND THERE IS NO MENTAL HEALTH ISSUE FACING OUR CITY
TODAY NOT ONE MORE CONSEQUENTIAL OR MORE IMPACTFUL
THAN SUBSTANCE USE DISORDERS AND ALCOHOL USE DISORDERS AT A
MOMENT WHEN WE ARE FINALLY BEGINNING TO MAKE REAL PROGRESS
ON DRUG FREE AND RECOVERY ORIENTED HOUSING OPTIONS AT THE
STATE LEVEL AND AT THE LOCAL LEVEL.
BILLY LEMON'S PERSPECTIVE AND VOICE ARE NEEDED ON THIS
COMMITTEE. HE IS A REMARKABLE LEADER
AND HE BRINGS EXACTLY THE EXPERIENCE AND EXPERTISE AS OUR
CITY NEEDS ON HOMELESSNESS AND MENTAL HEALTH SERVICES
RIGHT NOW. AS I SAID AT THE RULES
COMMITTEE HEARING WHERE THIS ITEM WAS CONSIDERED SOMETIMES
THERE ARE APPOINTMENTS WE MAKE TO BOARDS AND ADVISORY BODIES
THAT REFLECT NEEDED DIRECTIONAL CHANGE IN THE CITY RATHER THAN
A REJECTION OF ANY INDIVIDUAL. THE APPOINTMENTS THIS IS THIS I
THINK IS AN APPOINTMENT THAT SAYS MORE ABOUT THE CITY
AND WHERE IT NEEDS TO GO THAN THE CALIBER OF RIVAL APPLICANTS
WHO ARE ALSO VYING FOR THE POSITION.
AND I THINK THAT'S THE CASE HERE.
SO I HOPE BILLY LEMON WILL EARN THIS BOARD SUPPORT FOR THIS
POSITION. >> ALL RIGHT.
SUPERVISOR CHIN THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MENDOZA AND I THINK
THIS IS ABSOLUTELY A VERY TOUGH ONE.
AS I LOOKED AT THE VERY QUALIFIED INDIVIDUALS HERE BUT
I ALSO CONCUR THE SENTIMENT EXPRESSED BY SUPERVISOR FIELDER
GENEVIEVE AND BOG HAS DONE A LOT OF WORK AND REALLY KNOW THE
OUR CITY, OUR HOME MEASURE ITSELF REALLY HAD A CLEAR
UNDERSTANDING WHAT IT'S ABOUT. IF IT WEREN'T THROUGH THE
CONVERSATION DURING BUDGET PROCESS HAVING THOSE IN-DEPTH
CONVERSATION PRIOR TO THE BUDGET PROCESS WITH HER REALLY
HELP AT LEAST ME AS AN INDIVIDUAL REALLY HAVE A BETTER
UNDERSTANDING OF THE MEASURE AND REALLY HOW DO WE WANT TO
FUND DIFFERENT TYPE OF PROJECT AND PROGRAMING THAT IS REALLY
MEETING HOUSING FIRST POLICY WHICH I AM A FIRM BELIEVER OF.
>> SO WITH THAT BUT THIS IS ALSO A TOUGH ONE AND I WANT TO
ALSO COMMEND YOU KNOW, BILL LEMON FOR HIS COMMITMENT TO
WILLING TO SERVE. >> THIS IS BY THE WAY, A
VOLUNTEER POSITION. >> IT IS NOT PAID AND IN FACT
SPENT INDIVIDUALS WILLING WHO ARE WILLING TO SERVE SPEND A
LOT OF THEIR TIME TO HELP SOLVE A REALLY CRITICAL PROBLEM THAT
OUR CITY BEEN FACING FOR A LONG TIME.
SO I JUST AGAIN WANT TO EXPRESS MY GRATITUDE TO ALL THE
APPOINTEES THAT ARE MOVING FORWARD AND RECOMMENDED BY THE
RULES COMMITTEE. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR FILING
YOUR HAT IN THE RING. BUT AT THE SAME TIME TODAY I
WILL BE SUPPORTIVE OF AT LEAST THE FIRST ROUND OF WHAT
SUPERVISOR PHIL THERE HAS PROPOSED.
BUT I WANT TO COMMEND EVERYONE THAT IS APPOINTED TODAY OR AS
APPOINTEE BEING RECOMMENDED TODAY.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR YOUR SERVICE AND WILLING NESS TO
SERVE. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN THANK YOU PERSON MANAGEMENT.
I WOULD LIKE TO ECHO WHAT SUPERVISORS HAD TO SHARE.
I'M I THINK THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO SO LUCKY THAT WE
HAVE, YOU KNOW, VERY EXPERIENCED IN EXPERTISE IN IN
THE AREA AND ALSO VERY COMPASSIONATE PEOPLE WILLING TO
CONTINUE TO SERVE SAN FRANCISCO.
I LOOK FORWARD TO MEETING AT MR. LEMON BUT I ALSO HAD THE
OPPORTUNITY WITH THE BUDGET PROCESS HAVING JENNY COMING
INTO MY OFFICE, YOU KNOW, MULTIPLE TIMES THROUGH IT
AND DURING THE PROCESS TO COME AND EDUCATE ME ABOUT THE
EXPERTISE AND THE NEEDS OF THIS COMMUNITY WAS VERY HELPFUL
AND INFORMATIVE FOR ME TO MAKE DECISION.
SO IT'S A HOW I AM BUT I ALSO WANT TO SAY I, I WOULD I
APPRECIATE THAT THE WILLINGNESS TO CONTINUE TO SERVE SAN
FRANCISCO AND I ALSO BELIEVE THAT JENNY WITH 30 YEARS OF
SERVICES IN IN IN HOMELESSNESS AND ADVOCATING FOR THIS
COMMUNITY AND AND MY VERY OWN AS A NEW SUPERVISOR VERY OWN
VERY LIMITED INTERACTION WITH HER.
SHE IS VERY QUALIFIED AND I WILL BE SUPPORTING HER TOO.
>> THANKS. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL I JUST
WANT TO EXPRESS MY SUPPORT FOR FOR BILLY LEMON AND MY
CONVERSATIONS WITH HIM AND WITH OTHERS.
IT'S JUST EXCEEDINGLY CLEAR THAT, YOU KNOW, HE HAS A STRONG
HISTORY OF ADVOCACY AND HIS WORK IN RECOVERY FOR SUBSTANCE
USE DISORDER FOR MENTAL HEALTH IS INCREDIBLY IMPORTANT TO THE
FUTURE. WHEN WE LOOK AT OUR CITY RIGHT
NOW ESTIMATES RANGE UPWARDS OF 80% OF THE INDIVIDUALS ON OUR
STREETS TODAY ARE SUFFERING FROM SOME COMBINATION OF
SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER AND MENTAL HEALTH CHALLENGES
AND BILLY LEMON'S HISTORY OF ADVOCACY OF WORK AND SUCCESS
IN THAT WORK I THINK PROVIDES US WITH HOPE FOR THE FUTURE
AND IS SOMEONE WHO I AM EXCITED TO BE ABLE TO SUPPORT IN THIS
INCREDIBLY DIFFICULT WORK. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD I WAS
SUBBING SOME CLARIFICATION ON WHAT THE VOTE BECAUSE WE
ALREADY DIVIDED THE QUESTIONS THE VOTE AT HAND IS ABOUT BILLY
LEMON NOT OF THE OTHER CANDIDATE CRACKERS.
>> VOTE WILL BE ON MR. LEMON AS TO APPROVE THEM TO THE
COMMISSION. OKAY.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD I FROM A
SUPERVISOR WELL AND I WOULDN'T ADD TOO MUCH I DO JUST WANT TO
SAY ABOUT ABOUT BILLY LEMON THAT AFTER THE AFTER THE
COMMITTEE HEARING ON THIS HE CALLED ME BECAUSE HE WAS
CONCERNED. I THINK THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO
VERY MUCH WANT TO MAKE A CHANGE ON THIS BODY AND I'M ONE OF
THOSE FOLKS. >> BUT HE WANTED IT TO BE CLEAR
THAT HE IS NOT A PARTIZAN AND THAT HE AND ONE OF THE
THINGS THAT I THINK IS SO GREAT ABOUT HIM IS HIS INTEREST
AND WILLINGNESS AND WORKING WITH LOTS OF DIFFERENT KINDS OF
PEOPLE WHO MAY NOT AGREE ABOUT THE THINGS THAT WE FIGHT ABOUT
IN THIS BUILDING AND OUTSIDE THE BUILDING.
>> WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, COULD YOU CALL THE ROLL ON MR.
LEMON'S APPOINTMENTS ON THE DIVIDED PORTION REPRESENTED BY
WILLIAM LEMON ON HOLD UP QUICK QUESTION A YES IS WE ARE
SUPPORTING OR WOULD I JUST WANT TO KNOW YES.
>> YES IS HE GOES ON NO IS HE DOES NOT YES.
ON THE DIVIDED PORTION REPRESENT IT BY WILLIAM LEMON
SEAT EIGHT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR FIELDER
FIELDER NO SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN
I MEAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
SUPERVISE ARE CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO THERE
ARE SIX EYES AND FOUR NOSE WITH SUPERVISORS FIELDER WALTON CHAN
AND CHIN VOTING NO WELL IT WAS AN I OKAY MY APOLOGIES
SUPERVISOR WALTON THERE ARE SEVEN EYES AND THREE NOSE WITH
SUPERVISORS FIELDER CHIN AND CHIN VOTING NO THE MOTION
TO APPROVE MR. LEMON IS APPROVED AND NOW WE TAKE THE
REST. IS THAT RIGHT?
YES. YES.
ALL RIGHT. NOT ONLY CAN YOU PLEASE CALL
THE ROLL ON THE REMAINDER OF THE DIVIDED QUESTION ON THE
REMAINDER THIS IS REPRESENTED BY CHANEL WILLIAMS FOR C TWO
AND JULIA DE ANTONIO FOR SEAT SIX SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
EYES SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HIGH MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MOTION IS APPROVED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO
TO COMMITTEE REPORTS YES WE HAVE OUR COMMITTEE REPORTS
TODAY ITEMS 42 AND 43 WERE CONSIDERED BY THE RULES
COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY NOVEMBER 17TH.
WE'RE RECOMMENDING IT AS COMMITTEE REPORTS.
ITEM 42 IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
TO CREATE THE FILLMORE ENTERTAINMENT ZONE ON FILLMORE
STREET BETWEEN SUTTER AND MCALLISTER STREETS
AND O'FARRELL STREET BETWEEN STEINER AND FILLMORE STREETS
AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION AND I THINK WE
CAN TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE
CALL ITEM 43 I DON'T 43 WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED WITH THE
NEW TITLE TO CONFIRM THE APPOINTEE.
ITEM 43 CONFIRMS THE CONTROLLERS APPOINTMENT OF
ALEXANDRA SHEPHERD AS INSPECTOR GENERAL FOR AN INDEFINITE TERM
AND AGAIN SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. AND MADAME CLERK, LET'S GO TO A
ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS. >> FIRST MEMBER UP TO INTRODUCE
NEW BUSINESS IS SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUBMIT THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR FIELDER SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
>> COLLEAGUES TODAY I WOULD LIKE TO INTRODUCE AND IN
MEMORIAM TO HONOR THE LIFE OF ALICE WONG A GIANT IN THE
DISABILITY JUSTICE COMMUNITY AND A PROLIFIC WRITER WHOSE
WORK CONTINUES TO IMPACT THE LIVES OF MILLIONS.
>> ALICE PASSED AWAY LAST WEEK ON NOVEMBER 14TH AT UCSF.
>> SHE WAS ONLY 51 AND THOUGH HER LIFE WAS SHAPED BY A
PROGRESSIVE NEUROMUSCULAR CONDITION, SHE PUSHED PAST
EVERY LIMIT ANYONE EVER PLACED ON HER.
>> WHEN DOCTORS TOLD HER AS A YOUNG GIRL THAT SHE MAY NOT
LIVE TO 18, SHE DID WHAT SHE ALWAYS DID.
>> SHE PROVED THEM WRONG AND BUILT A LIFE FULL OF
PURPOSE. SHE WAS BORN IN INDIANAPOLIS TO
IMMIGRANT PARENTS FROM HONG KONG AND SHE CARRIED HER
HERITAGE WITH HER WHEN SHE CAME TO SAN FRANCISCO FOR GRADUATE
SCHOOL AT UCSF. >> THE CITY BECAME HER HOME
AND SHE POURED HERSELF INTO THE FIGHT FOR INCLUSIVITY
AND JUSTICE. >> ALICE'S ADVOCACY LED HER TO
FOUND THE DISABILITY VISIBILITY PROJECT WHICH STARTED AS A
GRASSROOTS EFFORT TO COLLECT STORIES WITHIN THE DISABILITY
COMMUNITY. AND GREW INTO A NATIONAL FORCE.
>> SHE SHIFTED CULTURE BY INSISTING THAT DISABLED PEOPLE
TELL THEIR OWN STORIES AND BE CENTERED IN EVERY CONVERSATION
ABOUT POLICY AND IDENTITY. >> THROUGH HER BOOKS INCLUDING
HER 2022 MEMOIR YEAR OF THE TIGER, SHE GAVE THE WORLD A
CLEARER PICTURE OF DISABILITY ONE THAT IS MULTIFACETED
AND DEEPLY HUMAN. >> SHE FOUGHT FOR ACCESS
IN EVERY SENSE OF THE WORD. SHE SEES NATIONAL ATTENTION
THROUGH HER UNWAVERING SUPPORT OF HUMAN RIGHTS AND LIBERATION
OF PALESTINIANS THROUGH TRIPS FOR SMES FOR GAZA ENLISTED THE
SUPPORT OF COMMUNITY THROUGH ACCESS LOVE AND REMAINS
STEADFAST IN INSISTING REPRESENTED AND ACROSS
PLATFORMS THE SAME PLATFORMS THAT OPEN DOORS FOR
DISABILITIES ABLED WRITERS SUCH AS HERSELF.
>> ALICE UNDERSTOOD THAT IN USING HER VOICE SHE COULD
UPLIFT AND SET THE EXAMPLE FOR OTHERS WHO FELT VOICELESS.
>> THIS IS THE TYPE OF LEADER THAT SHE WAS.
>> HER LIFE'S WORK WON NATIONAL RECOGNITION INCLUDING BEING
NAMED A 2023 MACARTHUR GENIUS FELLOW.
>> BUT ANYONE WHO KNEW HER WILL TELL YOU THAT THE PUBLIC
ACCOLADES WERE ONLY FOOTNOTES IN HER SAGA.
>> ALICE BUILT RELATIONSHIPS. >> SHE MENTORED YOUNG
ACTIVISTS. SHE SUPPORTED INCLUSIVE SPACES
THAT JOY AND HUMOR COULD THRIVE.
>> SHE BELIEVED DEEPLY IN THE BONDS WE CREATE WITH EACH OTHER
WHICH SHE HERSELF DESCRIBED AS A WEB OF CONNECTIVE TISSUE THAT
KEEPS OUR ANCESTORS ALIVE AMONG US.
>> DURING MY LAST VISIT WITH HER WE TALKED ABOUT PEDESTRIAN
SAFETY AND RAISED CROSSWALKS. WE RANKED OUR FAVORITE STAR
WARS FILMS AND SHARED OUR FAVORITE CHARACTERS.
>> WE NERD IT OUT. >> EVEN THOUGH I DIDN'T MEET
HER UNTIL EARLIER THIS YEAR, SHE REPEATEDLY ENCOURAGED ME TO
SEEK SUPPORT IN MY ARTISTIC COMMUNITY HERE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> I SEE NOW THAT THAT WASN'T A
SIMPLE RECOMMENDATION TO FILL SMALL TALK BUT AN EXTENSION OF
HER GREATER LIFE'S MISSION TO ALWAYS BE CONNECTING OTHERS.
I WILL DEEPLY MISS OUR CONVERSATIONS.
>> TODAY WE FEEL THE WEIGHT OF HER LOSS NOT JUST AS A CITY BUT
AS A COMMUNITY OF INDIVIDUALS WHO ARE MOVED BY HER PROFOUND
NESS, BY HER HUMOR AND BY HER STUBBORN BELIEF IN THE INNATE
GOODNESS OF HUMANKIND. >> HER LEGACY LIVES ON IN THE
MOVEMENT. SHE IGNITED THE VOICES SHE
SPOTLIGHT. THE LEADERS SHE MENTORED
AND THE WORLD SHE INSISTED WE COULD CREATE TOGETHER.
>> WORLD I HOPE COLLEAGUES WE CAN WORK TOWARD IN HER HONOR.
>> ALICE THANK YOU FOR EVERYTHING YOU GAVE THE CITY.
>> WE HONOR YOU BY CONTINUING THE FIGHT YOU LED BY TELLING
THE STORIES YOU INSISTED HAD TO BE TOLD AND BY SEEKING A FUTURE
THAT IS ACCESSIBLE TO ALL WILL HONOR YOU BY BUILDING
FRIENDSHIP AND REMEMBERING NO MATTER THE CHALLENGES THAT
WE'RE ALL CONNECTED. >> AND THIS TIME I'D LIKE TO
UPLIFT ALICE'S FINAL WORDS TO THE PUBLIC IN THIS CHAMBER.
>> ALICE WROTE HI EVERYONE. IT LOOKS LIKE I RAN OUT OF
TIME. >> I HAVE SO MANY DREAMS THAT I
WANTED TO FULFILL AND PLANS TO CREATE NEW STORIES FOR YOU.
>> THERE ARE A FEW IN PROGRESS THAT MIGHT COME TO FRUITION
IN A FEW YEARS IF THINGS WORK OUT.
>> I DID NOT EVER IMAGINE I WOULD LIVE TO THIS AGE AND END
UP A WRITER, EDITOR, ACTIVISTS AND MORE.
AS A KID RIDDLED WITH INSECURITY AND INTERNALIZED
EMBOLISM I COULD NOT SEE A PATH FORWARD.
>> IT WAS THANKS TO FRIENDSHIPS AND SOME GREAT TEACHERS WHO
BELIEVED IN ME THAT I WAS ABLE TO FIGHT MY WAY OUT OF
MISERABLE SITUATIONS AND TO A PLACE WHERE I FINALLY FELT
COMFORTABLE IN MY OWN SKIN. WE NEED MORE STORIES ABOUT US
AND OUR CULTURE. >> YOU ALL.
WE ALL DESERVE EVERYTHING AND MORE IN SUCH A HOSTILE,
ABLEST ENVIRONMENT. OUR WISDOM IS INCISIVE
AND UNFLINCHING. I'M HONORED TO BE YOUR ANCESTOR
AND BELIEVE DISABLED ORACLES LIKE US WILL LIGHT THE WAYS TO
THE FUTURE. >> DON'T LET THE GRIND YOU
DOWN. I LOVE YOU ALL.
REST IN POWER, ALICE AND MAY THE FORCE BE WITH YOU.
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU, SIR, FOR THAT.
YOUR MEN HAVE SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES, I'M ASKING THAT WE
ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF MARY KAY
AND GARCIA WHO DIED OCTOBER 13TH, OCTOBER 13TH AT THE AGE
OF 76 AFTER A BRIEF AND COURAGEOUS BATTLE WITH
PANCREATIC CANCER. MARY KAY WAS BORN IN SAGINAW,
MICHIGAN IN 1948. SHE HAD A DIFFICULT CHILDHOOD
LOSING HER FATHER AT THE AGE OF 12 AND WATCHING HER MOTHER
NAVIGATE LIFE AS A WIDOWED PARENT WITH LIMITED EDUCATION
AND RESOURCES. THESE EARLY EXPERIENCES SHAPED
MARY KAY'S RESILIENCE, INDEPENDENCE AND DEEP
COMPASSION FOR OTHERS. SHE SHE SOUGHT ADVENTURE
WHEREVER SHE COULD. >> AS A YOUNG WOMAN SHE TOOK A
JOB WITH DELTA AIRLINES ALLOWING HER TO TRAVEL TO NEW
YORK CITY, SAN FRANCISCO AND THE BAHAMAS OFTEN TAKING
DAY TRIPS JUST FOR THE JOY OF SEEING THE WORLD.
IN THE EARLY 1970S, MARY KAY BECAME A SINGLE MOM TO OUR
FORMER COLLEAGUE JOEL AND KATIA.
THE 1970S WAS THE ERA OF WOMEN'S LIBERATION AND THE
FIGHT TO RATIFY THE EQUAL RIGHTS AMENDMENT.
>> MARY KAY AND HER MOTHER EMBODIED THE MOVEMENT SPIRIT
QUIETLY BUT POWERFULLY AS THEY RAISED JOEL.
MARY KAY SUPPORTED THE FAMILY BY CLEANING HOMES AND OFFICE
BUILDINGS, OFTEN BRINGING ALONG HER SON AND HER MOTHER TO HELP
HELP HER CLEAN. WHEN JOEL WAS TEN AN OLD ENOUGH
TO STAY HOME ALONE, MARY KAY RETURNED TO SCHOOL WITH THE
GOAL OF USING HER EDUCATION TO SERVE VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES.
SHE ATTENDED NIGHT CLASSES AT THE COMMUNITY COLLEGE ONE CLASS
AT A TIME AND AFTER 11 YEARS EARNED HER BACHELOR'S DEGREE.
SHE WENT ON TO WORK FOR 25 YEARS AS A LICENSED SOCIAL
WORKER FOR SENIORS WITH MENTAL HEALTH CONDITIONS.
KNOWN FOR TAKING HER CLIENTS ON SMALL BUT MEANINGFUL OUTINGS
FROM TRIPS TO THE ZOO TO LUNCH AT THE LOCAL TACO BELL, MARY
KAY WAS THE ONLY MEMBER OF A LARGE EXTENDED ITALIAN CATHOLIC
FAMILY TO CONVERT TO JEHOVAH'S WITNESSES.
NOT AN EASY CHOICE BUT SHE SPENT 50 YEARS KNOCKING ON
DOORS TO SPREAD HER FAITH. WHEN SHE WASN'T ABLE TO WALK
DOOR TO DOOR ANYMORE, SHE WROTE LETTERS.
>> THERE WERE UNSENT LETTERS IN HER PURSE WHEN SHE DIED.
YET HAVING A GAY SON MEANT HER BELIEFS AS A JEHOVAH'S WITNESS
REQUIRED DIFFICULT CHOICES. MARY KAY BALANCED HER RELIGIOUS
CONVICTIONS WITH DEEP LOVE FOR HER FAMILY.
SHE WELCOMED HER SONS HUSBAND LIONEL INTO HER LIFE AND HOME
AND IN HER FINAL DAYS EXPRESSED HER LOVE AND GRATITUDE TO BOTH
OF THEM. AFTER RETIRING, MARY KAY MOVED
FROM MICHIGAN TO VACAVILLE, CALIFORNIA TO BE CLOSE TO JOEL
AND LIONEL. SHE LOVED EXPLORING CALIFORNIA
ON ROAD TRIPS WITH FRIENDS. SHE ALSO LOVED SHAKESPEARE
SUNSETS, MOUNTAINS, DOGS AND COOKING FOR OTHERS.
HER LASAGNA, OATMEAL, SCOTCH COOKIES WHICH I THINK SOME OF
US MAY HAVE HAD AND CROCKPOT STEWS WERE FAN FAVORITES.
>> MARY KAY DIED PEACEFULLY SURROUNDED BY LOVE WITH HER SON
HOLDING HER HAND. WE SEND OUR CONDOLENCES TO JOEL
AND HIS HUSBAND LIONEL, WHOM. >> REST IN PEACE.
MARY KING GADO. >> MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A
BLESSING. THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. WOULD YOU LIKE ME AT OUR OFFICE
TO PREPARE THAT ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS? >> YES.
WE'LL DO THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION .
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR SAUTER. THANK YOU.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I INITIATED A DRAFTING REQUEST WITH THE CITY
ATTORNEY'S OFFICE FOR SERIES OF LEGISLATION THAT WILL COMPRISE
THE SAN FRANCISCO CLEAN STREETS ACT.
THIS LEGISLATIVE PACKAGE WILL RESULT IN CLEANER STREETS.
BY UPDATING THE PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO IMPROVE HOW OUR
DEPARTMENTS DELIVER SERVICES, IT WILL ALSO STRENGTHEN
ACCOUNTABILITY MEASURES TO MAKE SURE OUR DOLLARS ARE BEING USED
AS EFFICIENTLY AS POSSIBLE. >> WE'RE BRINGING FORWARD THE
SERIES OF CHANGES DIRECTLY INFORMED BY TALKS WITH
MERCHANTS, NEIGHBORS, PUBLIC WORKS STAFF ALL OF WHOM ARE
COMMITTED TO STEMMING ILLEGAL DUMPING, MINIMIZING CONFUSION
FOR RATEPAYERS AND MAINTAINING CLEANER STREETS.
THROUGH THIS LEGISLATIVE FRAMEWORK WE WILL PURSUE A
NUMBER OF CODE CHANGES AND THESE CHANGES MAY INCLUDE
CREATING A TIERED ENFORCEMENT RESPONSE SO THAT WE FREE UP DPW
ENFORCEMENT RESOURCES FOR THE MOST SERIOUS ISSUES.
THIS WOULD ALLOW US, FOR EXAMPLE, TO PRIORITIZE ILLEGAL
DUMPING ENFORCEMENT OVERWRITING UP A TICKET FOR A NEIGHBOR WHO
FORGETS TO BRING THEIR BEAN IN BY 6 P.M..
BEING SMARTER ABOUT ENFORCEMENT FOR REPEAT OFFENDERS WHO
ILLEGALLY DUMP TRASH ON OUR STREETS BY INTRODUCING TIERED
FINES AND ESTABLISHING THE AUTHORITY TO DENY OR SUSPEND
BUSINESS REGISTRATION PERMITS AND LICENSES OR FOR UNPAID
FINES. REQUIRING LOCKED TRASH CANS FOR
REPEAT VIOLATIONS SO THAT WE CUT DOWN ON SCAVENGING
AND OVERTURNED BINS. AND IN A SMALL BUT ILLUMINATING
EXAMPLE. WE WILL CLARIFY THE LANGUAGE WE
USE IN PUBLIC WORKS CODE TO BE FRIENDLIER FOR EVERYDAY USERS.
FOR EXAMPLE, DOES ANYONE KNOW WHAT THE WORD PURCHASABLE
MEANS? AND I DIDN'T KNOW THIS EITHER
BUT OUR PUBLIC WORKS CODE HAS RULES ABOUT THIS TYPE OF WASTE
THAT WE EXPECT EVERYONE TO FOLLOW.
SO WE'LL CLARIFY THAT WHAT IT MEANS IN OUR PUBLIC WORKS CODE
LIKE EVERY OTHER NEARLY EVERY OTHER CITY DOES SO THAT
EVERYDAY USERS CAN KNOW WHAT IT ACTUALLY MEANS.
FOR THOSE WONDERING PURCHASABLE IS A WASTE CATEGORY THAT
INCLUDES ORGANIC MATTER THAT DECAYS QUICKLY SUCH AS FOOD
SCRAPS, SPOILED FOOD LEAVES, GRASS CLIPPINGS, ANIMAL
CARCASSES AND USED DIAPERS. FINALLY WE WILL REQUIRE A
COMPREHEND MASSIVE CITYWIDE EVALUATION OF STREET CLEANING
ROUTES EVERY TEN YEARS. THIS WAS A RECOMMENDATION OF
THE RECENT BILL IN THE OCTOBER 29TH PERFORMANCE AUDIT OF THE
MANAGEMENT OF STREET CLEANING AND THIS REPORT FOUND THAT
MECHANICAL STREET SWEEPING IN SAN FRANCISCO IS NOT
EVALUATED ON A REGULAR BASIS TO DETERMINE OPTIMIZED ROUTES,
SCHEDULING FREQUENCY AND LABOR NEEDS.
EXCUSE ME TO DETERMINE ROUTE SCHEDULING FREQUENCY OR LABOR
NEEDS AND THESE ROUTES HAVE NOT BEEN FUNDAMENTALLY CHANGED
SINCE LAST OPTIMIZATION EFFORTS TOOK PLACE WAY BACK
IN SEPTEMBER 28TH AND WE CERTAINLY FEEL THE PAIN OF THIS
IN DISTRICT THREE WHERE MOST OF RUSSIAN HILL, HILL AND NORTH
BEACH DO NOT HAVE REGULAR STREET SWEEPING PRACTICALLY THE
ONLY NEIGHBORHOODS IN THIS ENTIRE CITY WITHOUT THAT
SERVICE NEIGHBORHOOD WHO NEIGHBORS WHO WANT THAT SERVICE
WHICH IS OF COURSE A FAIR EXPECTATION ARE CONSTANTLY
BEING TOLD THEY CAN NOT HAVE IT BECAUSE OF OBJECTIONS THAT ROSE
AROSE TO IT IN THE 1980S. SO IS MY HOPE THAT THIS NEW
REQUIREMENT OF A REGULAR COMPREHENSIVE CITYWIDE
EVALUATION OF STREET CLEANING ROUTES WILL MAKE SURE IT IS NOT
ANOTHER 50 YEARS BEFORE WE EXPAND STREET SWEEPING AGAIN.
I'M PROUD OF THE WORK THAT OUR OFFICE HAS DONE BEGINNING THIS
YEAR TO DELIVER CLEANER STREETS.
WE'VE SECURED NEW TRASHCANS AND HILL AND RUSSIAN HILL.
WE RESTORED CRITICAL POWER WASHING PROGRAMS IN CHINATOWN,
HELP BUSINESSES ADOPT LOCKED TRASH CANS, HELD MERCHANT
FORUMS ON ILLEGAL DUMPING AND WE HAVE MANY MORE
INITIATIVES ON THE WAY BY PURSUING A NUMBER OF THE NEW
REFORMS THAT I MENTIONED IN OUR CLEAN STREETS ACT.
WE ARE DOUBLING DOWN ON OUR WORK TO MAKE SURE THAT SAN
FRANCISCO'S STREETS, SIDEWALKS AND PUBLIC SPACES CONTINUE TO
BE CLEANER FOR ALL. THIS WORK IS CRITICAL EVERY DAY
FOR OUR RESIDENTS AND SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS AND I THINK IT
TAKES ON ANOTHER LEVEL OF IMPORTANCE IN THE YEAR AHEAD AS
WE WELCOME VISITORS FOR THE SUPER BOWL, THE WORLD CUP
FESTIVITIES AND MANY MORE ACTIVITIES.
>> AND THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER.
SUPERVISOR CHERYL SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
>> COLLEAGUES, I HAVE IN MEMORIAM AND HEARING
ANNOUNCEMENT. FIRST I WANT TO HONOR
AND CELEBRATE THE LIFE OF REGINALD REGGIE CUMMINGS.
A SON, A FATHER, A BROTHER, A COUSIN, A FRIEND AND A TRUE
PILLAR OF COMMUNITY. REGGIE WAS BORN ON MARCH 12TH
IN 1965 AND GREW UP IN BAYVIEW A PLACE HE SPOKE OF WITH DEEP
PRIDE. HE ATTENDED EXCELSIOR
ELEMENTARY PELTON MIDDLE SCHOOL AND LINCOLN HIGH SCHOOL WHERE
HE FORMED FRIENDSHIPS THAT WILL LAST A LIFETIME.
>> TO KNOW REGGIE WAS TO TRULY LOVE HIM.
HE WASN'T JUST WELCOMED INTO PEOPLE'S LIVES.
HE WAS WELCOMED INTO THEIR FAMILIES.
HE BECAME THAT DEPENDABLE PRESENCE, THAT FAMILIAR FACE.
THE PERSON YOU KNEW YOU COULD ALWAYS CALL.
REGGIE LOVED HIS COMMUNITY AND HIS COMMUNITY LOVED HIM
RIGHT BACK. YOU COULD SEE IT IN THE WAY HE
CARRIED HIMSELF AND THE NOSTALGIA THAT FILLED HIS VOICE
WHEN HE TALKED ABOUT GROWING UP HERE AND THE JOY HE FOUND
IN THE THINGS HE LOVED. OLD SCHOOL CARS ESPECIALLY
ANYTHING BLUE WITH HIS CHERISHED 1967 FOUR FOUR TWO
CUTLASS OLDSMOBILE LEADING THE WAY PROFESSIONALLY.
REGGIE WAS A DEDICATED AND HE WAS HARDWORKING.
HE SPENT MANY YEARS AT THE MOSCONI CENTER BEFORE BEGINNING
HIS CAREER WITH RECOLOGY IN 2007.
HE WORKED WITH PRIDE ALWAYS SHOWING UP, ALWAYS GIVING HIS
BEST. BUT ABOVE ALL IT WAS REGGIE'S
PRESENCE THAT MADE HIM UNFORGETTABLE.
HE HAD A SMILE THAT COULD LIGHT UP ANY ROOM.
HE WAS GENUINE, WARM AND FULL OF LIFE.
HE HAD A REMARKABLE GIFT FOR MAKING PEOPLE FEEL SEEN, VALUED
AND APPRECIATED. REGGIE ENJOYED THE SIMPLE JOYS
THAT MAKE LIFE RICH PLAYING DOMINOES, ATTENDING COOKOUTS
AND CAR SHOWS, CHEERING AT SPORTING EVENTS, TRAVELING
AND GOING TO CONCERTS. >> HE LOVED GOOD FOOD, GOOD
MUSIC, GOOD TIMES AND BEING SURROUNDED BY THE PEOPLE WHO
MATTERED MOST ESPECIALLY LITTLE REGGIE WHO MEANT THE WORLD TO
HIM. TO SO MANY.
REGGIE WAS MORE THAN A FRIEND. HE WAS A BROTHER, A MENTOR, A
STEADY SOURCE OF STRENGTH, A FAVORITE COUSIN AND A PERSON
WHO'S KIND OF STAYED WITH YOU LONG AFTER THE CONVERSATION WAS
OVER. REGGIE LEAVES BEHIND A LEGACY
OF COMPASSION GENEROSITY AND COMMUNITY A LEGACY THAT
WILL CONTINUE TO LIVE ON THROUGH THE COUNTLESS LIVES HE
TOUCHED. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M ALSO
INTRODUCING A HEARING CONCERNING WHY THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE, THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORTIVE
HOUSING, THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT, MTA, NASA
OF PORT ARE TRYING TO TURN BAYVIEW INTO A CONTAINMENT ZONE
. I'VE SAID THIS BEFORE.
DISTRICT TEN HAS STEPPED UP TIME AND TIME AGAIN BUT THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE AND CITY DEPARTMENTS CONTINUE TO MAKE
UNILATERAL DECISIONS THAT OVERLOAD OUR NEIGHBORHOODS,
SHELTERS, SAFE SLEEPING SITES, VEHICLE TRIAGE CENTERS
AND EMERGENCY RESPONSE FACILITIES ARE ALL CONCENTRATED
IN CERTAIN AREAS WHILE OUR CITY DEPARTMENTS ARE REFUSING TO
DISTRIBUTE RESPONSIBILITY ACROSS THE CITY.
>> THE MAYOR AND HIS NAMED CITY DEPARTMENTS ARE MOVING AHEAD
WITH PLANS, NOTIFICATIONS AND SITING DECISIONS WITHOUT
MEANINGFUL ENGAGEMENT FROM RESIDENTS OR LOCAL LEADERSHIP.
>> THESE AFTER THE FACT ANNOUNCEMENTS SIGNAL THAT
AGENCIES SEE DISTRICT TEN AS A DEFAULT DUMPING GROUND INSTEAD
OF A COMMUNITY DESERVING SHARED GOVERNANCE.
WE ARE CALLING FOR A COMPREHENSIVE REPORT FROM EACH
DEPARTMENT THE MAYOR'S OFFICE, THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS
AND SUPPORTIVE HOUSING, DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT, MTA AND THE SAN FRANCISCO PORT DETAILING EVERY
SHELTER BED NAVIGATION CENTER SAFE SLEEPING SITE TRIAGE
CENTER VEHICLE SITE COMMUNITY CABIN PROGRAM AND RELATED
SERVICE IN SAN FRANCISCO AND PARTICULARLY IN DISTRICT
TEN. THE PUBLIC DESERVES CLEAR
ANSWERS OF WHERE THESE SERVICES ARE LOCATED.
THE CAPACITIES OF EACH SITE AND THE CRITERIA USED TO SELECT
THEIR LOCATIONS BY EACH DEPARTMENT.
CITY DEPARTMENTS MUST PLAN THEIR DECISION MUST EXPLAIN
THEIR DECISION MAKING, THEIR COMMUNICATION FAILURES AND WHAT
SAFEGUARDS THEY WILL PUT IN PLACE TO PREVENT FURTHER
UNILATERAL ACTIONS. THE PEOPLE OF THE CITY THE
PEOPLE OF DISTRICT TEN DESERVE HONESTY, RESPECT AND A PLAN
THAT DISTRIBUTES RESPONSIBILITY CITYWIDE.
RATHER THAN TREATING OUR COMMUNITY AS A CONTAINMENT ZONE
THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON. SUPERVISOR CHAN THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR CHIN. SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. THERE ARE NO MORE NAMES ON THE
ROSTER. THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION
OF NEW BUSINESS. LET'S GO TO PUBLIC COMMENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES
YOUR GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT. PLEASE LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT
HAND SIDE OF THE CHAMBER. >> YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MAYORAL
APPEARANCE TODAY OR THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED.
ITEMS 46 THROUGH 49 ON THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE CALENDAR OR OTHER GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON THE
PUBLISHED AGENDA. >> ALL OTHER AGENDA CONTENT
WILL HAVE BEEN REPORTED OUT TO THE BOARD BY AN APPROPRIATE
COMMITTEE WHERE THE PUBLIC COMMENT REQUIREMENT WAS
SATISFIED. >> WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES AND WE'LL START WITH MR. ACE WASHINGTON.
>> WELCOME. WELL THANK YOU.
LADIES MANDELMAN, THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
IT GIVES ME GREAT HONOR TO STAND HERE FOR YOU ALL.
YOU MAY NOT KNOW IT AND YOU HAD ALL THESE RECOMMENDATIONS FOR
PEOPLE. WHAT COULD YOU SHINE A LIGHT
RIGHT THERE ON THAT THERE? I'M HERE TO SAY THE Y'ALL KNOW
WHAT HAPPENED 46 YEARS AGO RIGHT HERE IN THE CITY
AND COUNTY SAN FRANCISCO. IT BRINGS ME TO TEARS.
AND THEY'RE HAVING A CELEBRATION NOW A REMEMBRANCE
AT THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN CULTURE CENTER AT 6:00 TO TALK ABOUT
THE SAME ISSUE THAT I'M TOLD. OH, CAN YOU YEAH, JIM THERE IS
THAT DEVIL JIM JONES IN THIS CITY WAS NOT RESPONSIBLE.
THEY HAD SOMETHING TO DO WITH IT BECAUSE THE MAYOR AT THAT
TIME APPOINTED HIM TO THE PUBLIC SAN FRANCISCO HOUSING
AUTHORITY COMMISSION IN WHICH HE TOOK UP THE PROJECTS IN THE
FILLMORE AND TOOK OVER 900 PEOPLE TO GUYANA AND FORCED
THEM TO DRINK THAT KOOL-AID. >> AND I'M APPALLED THAT THIS
MAYOR IS NOT RECOGNIZING THIS. SO FROM HERE ON OUT NEXT YEAR
WE SHOULD REMEMBER ALL OF THOSE BLACK CHILDREN OVER THREE
HUNDRED DIED. >> DO YOU KNOW HOW MANY
FAMILIES THAT COULD HAVE BEEN IN OUR COMMUNITY?
MY NAME IS DAVID AUSTIN. >> YOU'RE CRYING THAT THOSE
FAMILIES SOME OF IT I KNOW HAD GONE AWAY.
>> SO ANYWAY, I'M HERE TO SAY I'M ACE ON THE CASE THE
FILLMORE CORRIDOR AMBASSADOR BUT I JUST WANTED TO BRING IT
TO THE ATTENTION OF THE SUPERVISORS.
Y'ALL WASN'T AROUND. YOU'RE NOT RESPONSIBLE.
BUT I WANT YOU ALL TO REMEMBER NOVEMBER THE 18TH WHEN A LOT OF
OUR BLACK FAMILIES DIED OVER IN GUYANA OR THIS DEVIL HERE.
MY NAME IS LISA MOON THE CASE. >> THANK YOU FOR LISTENING.
THANK YOU ALL. >> THANK YOU ACE WASHINGTON FOR
YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS EDGAR RYAN SILVA
AND THIS COMMENT IS IN REGARDS TO MAYOR LARRY'S NEW STREET
VENDING LAWS. >> AS A RECENT USF GRADUATE
AND THE SON OF TWO FILIPINO LOVING IMMIGRANTS, I CARE
DEEPLY ABOUT ENSURING THAT IMMIGRANT VENDORS HAVE A FAIR
PATHWAY INTO THE LEGAL ECONOMY .
>> I SUPPORT THE CITY'S GOAL OF KEEPING OUR STREETS SAFE, CLEAN
AND FREE FROM THE RESALE OF STOLEN RETAIL GOODS.
BUT AS ENFORCEMENT INCREASES WE MUST STAY EQUALLY COMMITTED TO
FAIRNESS FOR IMMIGRANT VENDORS AND IMPACTED COMMUNITIES.
STATE SIDEWALKS VENDING LAWS EMPHASIZE SUPPORTIVE
NON-PUNITIVE APPROACHES INCLUDING OUTREACH EDUCATION
AND PATHWAYS TO COMPLIANCE BEFORE ESCALATING ENFORCEMENT.
SAN FRANCISCO SHOULD FULLY EMBRACE THAT SPIRIT.
MANY RECENT IMMIGRANTS FACE LANGUAGE BARRIERS DOCUMENTATION
AND CHALLENGES AND FINANCIAL HARDSHIP THAT MAKE THE
PERMITTING PROCESS FAR MORE DIFFICULT THAN IT APPEARS.
IMMIGRANT VENDORS CONTRIBUTE TO THE CULTURE AND ECONOMY OF
NEIGHBORHOODS LIKE THE MISSION AND SOMA DISTRICT.
>> AND THEY DESERVE A CLEAR ACCESSIBLE PATHWAY INTO THE
LEGAL MARKET. ENFORCEMENT ALONE WON'T CREATE
OPPORTUNITY BUT ENFORCE MENT PAIRED WITH REAL SUPPORT WILL.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> BOARD PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS
OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS RICHARD PETERSON.
I AM A LICENSED FORTUNE TELLER IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. >> I FORESEE A CITY A CITYWIDE
BATTLE BETWEEN THE EAST AND THE WEST KIND OF A CITY CIVIL WAR
IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THERE WILL BE CIVIL WAR. IT STARTED EAST VERSUS WEST.
A DOWNTOWN SCHEME TO PAY FOR MUNI.
THE BAY VERSUS THE BEACH AT THE CENTER OF THE DIVISION IS THE
THORNY ISSUE OF PARCEL TAXES. WITHOUT INPUT FROM HOME OWNERS
THE MAYOR THE MAYOR'S SCHEME TO OVERTAX WEST SIDE PROPERTY
OWNERS TO SHORE UP FAILED EAST SIDE PROPERTY DEVELOPER
SPECULATORS. THE FIRST THE FIRST MISSILE WAS
LAUNCHED BY THE MAYOR OCCASIONALLY OVER HIS
OCEANSIDE HOMESTEAD. KIDS WANT A FAIR DEAL.
THEY WANT A PLACE AT THE TABLE .
>> THE MAYOR SET THE POLICY AND FORMULA FOR CALCULATION OF
THE AMOUNT A PARCEL TAX IS DUE. WE WILL COMPARE A PORTION OF
THE MILLENNIUM M TOWER OR SAY BARRON'S LUXURIOUS APARTMENT
WITH THE HOMESTEAD OF A TYPICAL CITY AS TYPICAL HILL BUNGALOW
ON THE WEST SIDE. AND THE BIG QUESTION REMAINS
WHAT ARE THE EXEMPTIONS AND WHAT ARE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> FOLLOW JOSE I CAN'T SEE VERY WELL.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO.
I'M HERE TO COMMENT ABOUT THE TRANSGENDER AWARENESS MONTH
RESOLUTION THAT YOU ALL UNANIMOUSLY SPONSORED.
THIS IS PERFORMATIVE. THIS IS HOLLOW AND MEANINGLESS.
>> I KNOW I KNOW THAT FOR A FACT.
CURRENTLY THE TRANSGENDER SANCTUARY CITY STATUS OF SAN
FRANCISCO IS A RESOLUTION. IT HAS NO TEETH.
IF YOU REALLY WANTED TO DO SOMETHING FOR THE TRANS
COMMUNITY YOU CAN TURN IT INTO AN ORDINANCE SO WE CAN ACTUALLY
HAVE REAL PROTECTIONS AND GET REAL HELP AND SERVICES FROM SAN
FRANCISCO. >> BUT UNTIL THAT HAPPENS WITH
THE ROLLBACK IN PROTECTIONS AND RIGHTS AND THE DEGRADED
STANDARD OF LIVING THAT TRANS PEOPLE HAVE BEEN EXPERIENCING
OVER THIS PAST YEAR HENCE WHY 9% NOW OF THE HOMELESS
POPULATION IS TRANSGENDER. I CALL SAN FRANCISCO A TRAP FOR
TRANS PEOPLE. IT'S NOT A REAL SANCTUARY CITY.
YOU COULD ALSO IF YOU WANTED TO HELP REINSTATES TRANSGENDER
CULTURAL COMPETENCY TRAINING FOR SAN FRANCISCO CITY
AND COUNTY EMPLOYEES. IT WAS A LITTLE OVER A YEAR AGO
THAT THE BOARD VOTED TO SETTLE AGAINST THE GIFT PROGRAM WHICH
WAS HELPING FINANCIALLY HELPING VERY POOR TRANS PEOPLE
SPECIFICALLY BLACK AND LATINO TRANS PEOPLE.
HOWEVER, THE MAJORITY OF THE BOARD VOTED AGAINST BLACK
AND LATINO AND TRANS PEOPLE SO THAT THEY CAN NEVER GET A BASIC
INCOME FROM SAN FRANCISCO AGAIN.
THAT'S REALLY UP. >> YOU ALL DID REAL HARM.
>> I KNOW THIS. I KNOW THE PEOPLE YOU HARMED.
>> I THINK THIS WHOLE BOARD SHOULD BE BANNED FROM TRANS
EVENTS AND SO YOU SHOW UP WITH SOMETHING TANGIBLE INSTEAD OF
SOME PIECE OF PAPER THAT DOESN'T DO ANYTHING FOR TRANS
PEOPLE. NOT JUST THE ONE PERSON I
CALLED OUT LAST WEEK. >> UM, YOU KNOW WHAT ELSE?
>> YOU JUST YOU'RE FAILING US. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND OFFICER SAN CISCO.
I'M GONNA GIVE OUR THANKSGIVING ACKNOWLEDGMENT TO THE FOLKS AT
THE PRESIDENTIAL PALACE INCLUDING DIRECTOR SHARONDA,
ERINN, KIKI MOORE, MARIANNE ANDRE COY AND KEVIN HUNTER.
I THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. >> WELCOME THE NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS AND MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC.
MY NAME IS RAVINA RAHA. I'M A RESIDENT OF DISTRICT NINE
BERNAL HEIGHTS AND I'M ALSO A COMMISSIONER ON THE COMMISSION
ON THE STATUS FOR WOMEN. THANK YOU FOR TAKING UP THE
RESOLUTION RECOGNIZING SICK AWARENESS AND APPRECIATION
MONTH IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> MY HUSBAND AND I ARE PROUD SICK AMERICANS AND WE CHOSE TO
RAISE OUR TWO SONS RAZA SINGH AND SARTAJ SINGH RIGHT HERE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. THEY WEAR THEIR LONG HAIR,
THEIR PARKAS AND THEIR TURBANS WITH PRIDE.
AND IN THIS CITY, ESPECIALLY IN OUR COMMUNITY IN DISTRICT
NINE, THEY FEEL CELEBRATED, SAFE AND SEEN.
THAT SENSE OF BELONGING IS SOMETHING WE DO NOT TAKE FOR
GRANTED. SAN FRANCISCO HAS ALWAYS BEEN
PART OF SIKH AMERICAN HISTORY. >> OVER A CENTURY AGO SIKH
IMMIGRANTS ENTERED THE U.S. THROUGH THIS CITY AND ANGEL
ISLAND. THEY FACED DISCRIMINATION BUT
THEY ALSO BUILT STRONG, RESILIENT COMMUNITIES ROOTED
IN EQUALITY, SERVICE AND RESILIENCE.
ALSO THE BAY AREA IS THE BIRTHPLACE OF THE MOTHER
MOVEMENT, ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT DIASPORA LED FREEDOM
MOVEMENTS OF THE 20TH CENTURY. >> TODAY SIX SAN FRANCISCANS
SIX AND SAN FRANCISCANS CONTRIBUTE ACROSS EVERY SECTOR
HEALTH CARE WORKERS, SMALL BUSINESS OWNERS, TEACHERS,
TECHNOLOGISTS, CABDRIVERS, ARTISTS AND PUBLIC SERVANTS.
>> THE TRADITION OF SEVA OR SELFLESS SERVICE CONTINUES
THROUGH DISASTER RELIEF EFFORTS COMMUNITY FOOD, FOOD PROGRAMS
AND ADVOCACY FOR CIVIL RIGHTS. BUT THIS RECOGNITION MATTERS
BECAUSE SICK CHILDREN ARE NOT CELEBRATED EVERYWHERE.
OUR FRIENDS WHO LIVE ONLY 30 MINUTES FROM HERE HAVE A SON MY
SON'S AGE WHO IS BEING CALLED A TERRORIST ON A REGULAR BASIS.
>> THAT IS A REALITY FOR MANY SICK KIDS ACROSS THE COUNTRY
AND IT'S PRECISELY WHY YOUR ACTION TODAY IS SO MEANINGFUL.
THANK YOU FOR NAMING THIS SICK AWARENESS AND APPRECIATION
MONTH. THANK YOU TO SAN FRANCISCO FOR
DOING WHAT IT DOES BEST AFFIRMING VISIBILITY, INCLUSION
AND BELONGING. THANK YOU SO MUCH TODAY ON
BEHALF OF MY FAMILY AND ESPECIALLY ON BEHALF OF
ROSA AND SARA THAT THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU, COMMISSIONER.
DR. RAHUL. WELCOME.
>> THANK YOU. MY NAME IS PUNEET GOLD HERE
IN SUPPORT OF ITEM 47 THE RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE
NOVEMBER AS SICK AWARENESS AND APPRECIATION MONTH.
I SERVE AS THE SENIOR MANAGER OF STATE POLICY FOR THE SIKH
COALITION, THE NATION'S LARGEST SICK CIVIL RIGHTS ORGANIZATION
AND AM THE PROUD DAUGHTER OF PUNJABI IMMIGRANTS MYSELF.
>> SAN FRANCISCO HOLDS A VERY SPECIAL PLACE IN OUR SICK
AMERICAN HISTORY FROM THE FIRST PUNJABI IMMIGRANTS WHO LANDED
ON ANGEL ISLAND OVER 125 YEARS AGO TO THE LATE DR. NARINDER
SINGH KABBANI, A PHYSICIST, A SICK AND A PIONEER OF FIBER OF
FIBER OPTICS WHO HELPED RESHAPE GLOBAL COMMUNICATION.
HIS BRILLIANCE AND HIS CONTRIBUTIONS TO SAN FRANCISCO
AND OUR WORLD IS A REMINDER THAT THE SIKH CONTRIBUTIONS
IN AMERICA ARE VAST HISTORIC AND OFTEN GO UNTOLD.
FOUR 6TH NOVEMBER CARRIES PROFOUND MEANING AS A MONTH OF
REMEMBRANCE AND RIGHTEOUS STRUGGLE.
>> THIS MONTH MARKS THE 350TH SHAHEED OR MARTYRDOM OF OUR
NINTH SIKH GURU GURU TEG BAHAR INSIDE JI.
NICKNAMED SPACE TO EACH OTHER OR THE SHIELD OF THE WORLD WHO
GAVE HIS LIFE SO THAT PEOPLE BEYOND JUST HIS OWN SICK
FOLLOWERS COULD FREELY PRACTICE THEIR FAITH.
HIS SACRIFICE IS ONE OF THE GREAT ACTS OF RELIGIOUS FREEDOM
IN THIS WORLD AND FOR MANY SIKH FAMILIES INCLUDING SURVIVORS
AND DESCENDANTS OF THE 1984 ANTI-SIKH GENOCIDE WHO NOW CALL
CALIFORNIA HOME. >> RECOGNITION LIKE THIS
MATTERS DEEPLY. >> THEY AFFIRM THAT THEIR
TRAUMA AND THEIR SACRIFICE HAS NOT BEEN FORGOTTEN, THAT THEIR
RESILIENCE IS HONORED AND THAT THIS CITY STANDS WITH THEM
IN ACKNOWLEDGING THEIR LIVED HISTORY.
>> LASTLY, THIS YEAR ALSO MARKS THE 30TH OR 30 YEARS SINCE THE
MARTYRDOM OF SIKH HUMAN RIGHTS ACTIVISTS BY JUST ONE SINGH
CAULDER, WHO UNCOVERED THE EXTRAJUDICIAL KILLINGS
AND SECRET CREMATIONS OF THOUSANDS OF INDIVIDUAL US BY
THE INDIAN POLICE. >> DURING THE 80S AND 90S.
IN ONE OF HIS FINAL SPEECHES JUST ONCE IN QATAR RETOLD THE
FABLE OF THE VERY FIRST SUNSET WHEN HUMANITY TREMBLED AS
DARKNESS SWALLOWED THE EARTH AND HOW A SINGLE LANTERN
CHALLENGED. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
. ALL RIGHT.
WELCOME. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, MR.
PRESIDENT AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS NEPALI GILL AND I'M HERE ON BEHALF OF THE SIKH
COALITION, THE NATION'S LARGEST CIVIL RIGHTS ORGANIZATION.
AND I'M ALSO HERE AS A SAN FRANCISCO RESIDENT.
I'M HERE TO SPEAK IN STRONG SUPPORT OF ITEM 47, THE
RESOLUTION RECOGNIZING SICK AWARENESS AND APPRECIATION
MONTH IN THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THE SIKH COMMUNITY HAS BEEN PART OF CALIFORNIA'S STORY FOR
MORE THAN A CENTURY. SIX HAVE CONTRIBUTED TO THE
FABRIC OF OUR NEIGHBORHOODS AND SMALL BUSINESSES TODAY.
SIX CONTINUE TO PLAY AN ESSENTIAL ROLE ACROSS OUR CITY,
ESPECIALLY IN FIELDS LIKE TRANSPORTATION WHERE SICK TRUCK
DRIVERS KEEP CALIFORNIA'S ECONOMY MOVING.
>> HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, SIX ARE BUSINESS OWNERS
PROFESSIONALS, WORKERS, STUDENTS AND NEIGHBORS.
WE ARE PROUD TO CALL THE CITY HOME.
>> OUR GURDWARAS SERVE NOT ONLY AS PLACES OF WORSHIP BUT AS
CENTERS OF SERVICE OFFERING FREE MEALS, MUTUAL AID
AND COMMUNITIES SUPPORT TO ANYONE WHO NEEDS IT REGARDLESS
OF THEIR BACKGROUND. >> THESE VALUES OF EQUALITY,
DIGNITY AND SEVA SELFLESS SERVICE ALIGN DEEPLY WITH THE
VALUES SAN FRANCISCO STRIVES TO UPHOLD.
GIVEN THE RECENT BIAS IN INCIDENTS
AND MISUNDERSTANDING ABOUT SIKH IDENTITY NATIONWIDE
RECOGNITIONS LIKE THIS ARE MORE IMPORTANT NOW THAN EVER.
THEY HELP ENSURE THAT THE HISTORY, CONTRIBUTIONS
AND LIVED EXPERIENCES OF SICK AMERICANS ARE SEEN, UNDERSTOOD
AND VALUED. BY ADOPTING THIS RESOLUTION,
SAN FRANCISCO SENDS A POWERFUL MESSAGE THAT DIVERSITY IS A
STRENGTH AND THAT THE CITY STANDS WITH COMMUNITIES WHO
HAVE LONG CONTRIBUTED TO ITS SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC FABRIC.
>> I URGE YOU TO PASS THIS RESOLUTION AND TO CONTINUE
SUPPORTING EFFORTS THAT UPLIFT AND PROTECT ALL OF SAN
FRANCISCO'S DIVERSE COMMUNITIES.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR TIME AND YOUR LEADERSHIP AND A
SPECIAL THANK YOU TO SUPERVISOR MAHMUD FOR INTRODUCING THIS
RESOLUTION. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKERS. >> PRESIDENT MANDOLIN
SUPERVISORS MY NAME IS KELLY DEARMAN.
I'M THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF SAN FRANCISCO'S DEPARTMENT OF
DISABILITY AND AGING SERVICES AND I'M HERE WITH MY COLLEAGUE
ELIJAH LADAN WHO IS THE DIRECTOR OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
OFFICE OF DISABILITY AND ACCESSIBILITY.
SO WE COULD NOT LET THE MOMENT PASS WITHOUT SAYING SOMETHING
ABOUT ALICE AND SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR VERY BEAUTIFUL WORDS.
WE WERE HEARTBROKEN TO LEARN OF THE POSSIBLE PASSING OF
DISABILITY ACTIVIST AND ICON ALICE WONG.
SHE WAS SO GENEROUS WITH HER TIME AND DONATED HER EXPERTISE
TO OUR AGENCY. SHE WAS ON THE ADVISORY COUNCIL
FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO DISABILITY CULTURAL CENTER
AND SPOKE AT THE GRAND OPENING EVENT.
SHE ALSO RECENTLY DONATED HER TIME TO TO BE A FEATURED GUEST
AT SAN FRANCISCO'S HUMAN SERVICES AGENCY'S NATIONAL
DISABILITY EMPLOYMENT AWARENESS MONTH.
AND THAT WAS AN EVENT FOR OUR EMPLOYEES WHERE SHE REFLECTED
ON ABEL ISM AND CREATING A MORE INCLUSIVE WORKPLACE AND MORE
THAN A COLLEAGUE SHE WAS A MENTOR AND A REALLY GOOD FRIEND
TO ME. >> ALICE WAS A FORCE FOR
CHANGE. >> HER WORK EMBODIED THE VALUES
AS SUPERVISOR OF MOBILITY POINTED OUT OF ACCESS AS LOVE A
CAMPAIGN THAT SHE CO-CREATED WITH TWO OTHER INCREDIBLE
DISABILITY ACTIVISTS. >> ACCESS IS LOVE CONTINUES TO
INSPIRE US AS WE WORK TO PROVIDE EQUITABLE
AND ACCESSIBLE PROGRAMS AND SERVICES TO PEOPLE WITH
DISABILITIES AND OLDER ADULTS OF ALL AGES AND BACKGROUNDS
THROUGHOUT OUR CITY AS WELL AS VISITORS TO OUR CITY.
>> WE ARE OVERWHELMED BY THE OUTPOURING OF LOVE
AND DISABILITY SOLIDARITY THAT HAS COME OUT SINCE ALICE'S
PASSING. >> I'M GOING TO SAY THAT
PERSONALLY ALICE WAS AN AUNTIE TO MY CHILDREN AND ONE OF MY
BEST FRIENDS AND ONE OF THE VALUES THAT SHE DEEPLY LEANED
INTO DEEPLY WAS DISABLED JOY ONE OF THE LAST CONVERSATIONS I
HAD WITH ALICE WAS AROUND HOLIDAY PLAZA AND SHE WAS SO
EXCITED ABOUT THE TRANSFER MISSION OF TURNING HOLIDAY
PLAZA INTO AN ACCESSIBLE ROUTE A ROUTE THAT COULD BE
CELEBRATED BY ALL BUT ESPECIALLY THE DISABILITY
COMMUNITY THAT DID NOT HAVE ACCESS TO IT.
I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE SUPERVISOR MAHMUD FOR YOUR
LEADERSHIP. THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR ELEVATING
ALICE'S VOICE. THANK YOU TO ALL THE
SUPERVISORS FOR COMMENDING ALICE AS WELL AS OUR OTHER
HONORARIUMS HONOREES IN JULY. WE ARE SO GRATEFUL FOR HER WORK
,FOR HER GENEROSITY AND HER LOVE AND MAKE HER LEGACY LIVE
ON THROUGH OUR ACTIONS. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> THANK YOU. DIRECTOR GERMAN.
>> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> HI. MY NAME IS DR. THERESA PALMER.
I LIVE IN DISTRICT FIVE. I'M A GERIATRICIAN AND I WORKED
FOR 15 YEARS AT LAGUNA HONDA AND I'VE BEEN BOMBING Y'ALL
WITH EMAILS ABOUT THIS ISSUE. >> THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
MUST CONVENE A HEARING ON HOW TO PREVENT TRANSFER OUT OF
COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCANS WHO NEED SKILLED NURSING FACILITY
CARE EITHER TEMPORARY OR ONGOING.
>> IN 2022 THE PUBLIC SAFETY AND NEIGHBORHOOD SERVICES
COMMITTEE WORKED ON AND THE FULL BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
PASSED ORDINANCE 7722 WHICH REQUIRES THE ACUTE CARE
HOSPITALS TO REPORT TO THE PUBLIC HEALTH DEPARTMENT
AND SAN FRANCISCO THE NUMBER TRANSFER THE NUMBER OF PATIENTS
TRANSFERRED TO OUT OF COUNTY SKILLED NURSING FACILITIES.
>> THIS WAS PREVENTED. THE CURRENT NUMBERS FOR 2024
WAS PRESENTED TO THE HEALTH COMMISSION LAST JULY AND THEY
SHOW THAT AT LEAST 1500 SAN FRANCISCANS WERE SENT OUT OF
COUNTY AWAY FROM THEIR LOVED ONES, AWAY FROM THEIR SUPPORT
SYSTEMS TO OFTEN SUBSTANDARD NURSING HOMES OUTSIDE OF THE
COUNTY. AT THE SAME TIME LAGUNA HONDA
HOSPITAL DESPITE OPEN BEDS IS NOW REJECTING OR DISCOURAGING
MANY QUALIFIED APPLICANTS WHO ARE BEING DISCHARGED FROM
PARENTS CISCO HOSPITALS. >> THIS IS A MULTI FACETED
PROBLEM. I'M ASKING FOR SUPPORT TO HOLD
A HEARING. I'M NOT QUITE SURE HOW IT
WORKS. IT MIGHT START WITH THE
SUPERVISORS AT THE PUBLIC SAFETY AND NEIGHBORHOOD SERVICE
COMMITTEE. SUPERVISOR DAWSEY ALSO SERVES
ON THE HEALTH SERVICES STIM BOARD WHERE MANY CITY RETIREES
ARE CONCERNED ABOUT THIS BECAUSE THEY MAY HAVE THE QUOTE
UNQUOTE WRONG INSURANCE TO GET INTO LAGUNA HONDA.
>> THE. >> THANK YOU, TERESA PALMER
THANK YOU, DR. PALMER. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
THANK YOU AND GOOD AFTERNOON. I WANT TO.
MY NAME IS TINA MARTIN AND I ACTUALLY CAME HERE FOR TWO
PURPOSES IN ADDITION TO HONORING ALICE WONG.
I WANTED TO SPEAK ABOUT THE A FRIEND OF MINE THAT SHE'S HERE
TO SPEAK FOR HERSELF. SHE DEALT WITH A HELPING A
FRIEND AND FOUND OUT THAT THE SYSTEM WAS SUCH THAT SOMEONE
WHO HAD A HOME IN SAN FRANCISCO WOULD BE SENT OUT OF COUNTY TO
A SUBSTANDARD NURSING FACILITY. SO THAT WAS ONE OF THE REASONS
THAT I CAME. BUT SHE CAN SPEAK FOR HERSELF.
I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT WE HAVE SOME VERY BRAVE PEOPLE TRYING
THEIR BEST TO HELP OTHERS OF THEIR AGE WHICH IS ADVANCED
AND WE'RE GETTING THESE BLOCKS AND WE REALLY DO NEED TO HAVE A
HEARING. PLEASE DO CONVENE A HEARING
AND TERESA PALMER IS ANOTHER PERSON I WANTED TO MENTION
TODAY. I DIDN'T KNOW I WAS GOING TO
HAVE A CHANCE TO MEET HER AND SHE SPOKE RIGHT BEFORE I
DID SO SHE'S SOMEBODY WHO REALLY KNOWS THE SYSTEM
EXTREMELY WELL. SHE'S A CHAMPION FOR THOSE OF
US WHO ARE GETTING OLDER AND FRAILER AND CARE ABOUT
PEOPLE WHO ARE FIT THAT DESCRIPTION AND SHE COULD HELP
YOU CHOOSE PEOPLE TO BE ON THIS PANEL OF TO HEAR IF WHEN YOU
HAVE THE HEARING WHEN YOU CONVENE A HEARING TO SEE HOW WE
CAN MANAGE NOT TO SEND SAN FRANCISCANS FROM SAN FRANCISCO
TO SUBSTANDARD NURSING FACILITIES OUTSIDE OF SAN
FRANCISCO COUNTY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
I'M JANET FOWLER. I AM THE FRIEND.
WHEN I ARRIVED AT MY FRIEND'S HOME ON AUGUST 27TH TO TAKE HER
TO AN APPOINTMENT, I FOUND HER UNABLE EVEN TO STAND.
>> I CALLED 911 TO HAVE HER TAKEN TO DAVIS HOSPITAL AND IN
SPITE OF THE PENDING HOLIDAY I FELT THAT SHE WOULD BE SAFE
BECAUSE SHE NEEDED CARE. SHE NEEDED ACUTE CARE.
>> IN THE MEANTIME I LEARNED THAT LAGUNA HONDA HAD BEDS
AVAILABLE. IT WAS PERFECT SINCE IT HAS ALL
LEVELS OF CARE. >> BUT SHE WAS NOT SAFE.
SHE'D BEEN TRANSFERRED TO MISSION BERNAL CAMPUS AND THEN
PROMPTLY DUMPED AT AN UNDERSTAFFED HOME IN OAKLAND.
BLUE SHIELD AND MEDICARE ADVANTAGE OUR CITY RETIREE B.S.
INSURANCE HAD A VERY SHORT LIST OF NURSING HOMES AND NONE
IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> TWO WEEKS AFTER BEING DUMPED
IN THE OAKLAND NURSING HOME, I FOUND MY FRIEND CLOSE TO DEATH
SEVERELY, SEVERELY DEHYDRATED WITH A THICK TONGUE COVERED
WITH WHITE FILM AND FULL OF CRACKS AND BUMPS.
>> BY HER BEDSIDE THE WATER THAT SHE HAD CRAVED WAS IN A
CUP THAT SHE COULDN'T REACH REACH.
I SAW AGONY IN HER FACE. I INSISTED THAT 911 BE 911 BE
CALLED TO TAKE HER TO A HOSPITAL WITH ACUTE CARE.
LATER I LEARNED ABOUT THE IRREVERSIBLE DAMAGE THAT HAD
OCCURRED AT THE NURSING HOME. >> IN MY INTERACTION WITH THE
STAFF THERE I LEARNED THAT THEY WERE ALL GOOD PEOPLE WHO JUST
DIDN'T UNDERSTAND THE PART THEY HAD PLAYED IN WHAT HAD HAPPENED
TO MY FRIEND. WE ARE ALL LIKE THEY ARE.
WE DON'T UNDERSTAND THE PART WE ARE PLAYING THAT ALLOWS US
CRUELTY TO CONTINUE. THE FRAIL AND ELDERLY NEED TO
BE EASILY REACHED AND KEPT SAFE BY FAMILY OR FRIENDS AND NOT
AND BY NOT FIXING THIS. >> WE EVEN THOUGH WE ARE GOOD
PEOPLE ARE PLAYING A PART IN THE TRAGIC AND CRUEL DEATHS
OF OUR ELDERLY AND FRAGILE RESIDENTS.
I THINK THERESA PALMER, THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS ATTENTION
TO THIS ISSUE. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
GOOD EVENING SUPERVISORS MARK SOLOMON MY SISTER IN LAW DIED
FROM NURSING HOME CARE AND IT .
OKAY. JAMES BALDWIN SAID NOT
EVERYTHING THAT HIS FACE CAN BE CHANGED BUT NOTHING CAN BE
CHANGED UNTIL IT IS FACED. TO THE BOARD SUPERVISOR CHAN
REMARKED YESTERDAY THAT ONE STANDARD CITYWIDE FOR
PROTESTING RENT CONTROL BUILDINGS WAS DIVISIVE.
LIKE TO ADDRESS THAT WHAT'S DIVISIVE IS EVERY YEAR THAT
THIS BOARD PASSES A BUDGET THAT REINFORCES COLONIAL POWER
RELATIONSHIPS THE EAST SIDE RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS
GENERATE MORE TAXES, BUSINESS SALES AND PROPERTY THAN THE
PERIPHERAL NEIGHBORHOODS DOLLARS THAT ARE EXTRACTED TO
KEEP THOSE NEIGHBORHOODS CLEAN AND SAFE.
WE ARE MADE TO TAKE CONTAINMENT, PUBLIC SQUALOR
UNDESIRABLE LAND USES DRUG TREATMENT NEXT OUR ELEMENTARY
SCHOOL FOR INSTANCE. THIS IS FOR THE COLONIAL
RIFFRAFF. THE D9 SOUP FOR DECADES HAS
BEEN A TECHNICIAN FOR DIRECTING FUNDING TO A HANDFUL OF
POLITICALLY CONNECTED CITY FUNDING NONPROFITS THE CHARITY
NONPROFITS THAT ARE THE COLONIAL ADMINISTRATORS THE
UNION OFFICE FOR DECADES HAS AID AND ABETTED NONPROFIT
RACKETEERING EXTORTION FOR PLAZA 16 AND THE SALE SPACE
PROJECT INTIMIDATION, COLLUSION AND RIGGING.
THESE ARE STRUCTURAL PROBLEMS, NOT INDIVIDUALS.
THE D9 SOUP WAS RESPONSIVE TO MADE IT TODAY WHEN THEY ASKED
FOR $5 MILLION FOR AN ADMINISTRATIVE PALACE.
LUIS GRANADOS MAKES 363 KATE MARA.
SAM MOSS MAKES 275 K AT MISSION HOUSING LABELING PULLS IN THREE
L, ONE K AND SHAW MAKES 3 TO 70 K A TENDERLOIN HOUSING THIS IS
A 2023 MS. FRIEDEN BLOCK FOR INSTANCE HAS BEEN AN
ADMINISTRATOR ON HOMELESSNESS. SHE SUCCEEDED IN WEDGING THE
VOTERS AWAY FROM PROGRESSIVES BECAUSE THEY'VE MESSED IT UP SO
MUCH. I MEAN GOVERNMENT CONSIDERS IS
COLONIAL ADMINISTRATORS ARE STAKEHOLDERS BUT RESIDENTS ARE
NOWHERE TO BE FOUND IN THE POLITICAL CALCULUS.
>> WE ARE DEPRIVED OF HONEST GOVERNMENT SERVICES WITH US
ARRANGEMENT TO SUPERVISOR CHAN BETTER PROTECTIONS ON THE WEST
AND NORTH SIDES THAN THAN THE EAST SIDE IS WHAT'S DIVISIVE.
WE NEED TO END THE DIVISIVENESS IS TO GET THE COLONIAL JACKBOOT
OFF THE NECK OF THE TENDERLOIN BAYVIEW SOMA MISSION
AND HUNTERS POINT BY TREATING OUR NEIGHBORHOODS AS FIRST
CLASS NEIGHBORHOODS AND MAKING REPARATIONS FOR PAST HARMS.
>> THANK YOU, MR. WARFIELD. >> ARE YOU COMING UP TO THE
PODIUM? >> YES.
>> PETER WARFIELD, EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR LIBRARY USERS
ASSOCIATION, P.O. BOX 170544 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA
94117-0544 SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC LIBRARY IS I THINK IN SOME
SERIOUS TROUBLE WITH RESPECT TO ITS SERVICE TO THE PUBLIC.
IT HAD FOR DECADES A SLUR, A MISSION STATEMENT.
THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC LIBRARY IS DEDICATED TO FREE
AND EQUAL ACCESS TO INFORMATION KNOWLEDGE, INDEPENDENT LEARNING
AND THE JOYS OF READING FOR ITS DIVERSE COMMUNITY THAT HAS BEEN
REPLACED RELATIVELY RECENTLY WITH QUOTE S.F. FEEL CONNECTS
OUR DIVERSE COMMUNITIES TO LEARNING OPPORTUN UNITIES
AND EACH OTHER. MAYBE YOU COULD EXPLAIN WHAT
THAT MEANS BUT IT CERTAINLY LEAVES OUT FREE AND EQUAL MORE
AND MORE THE LIBRARY HAS BEEN PUTTING BARRIERS TO ACCESS FOR
THE WHOLE RANGE OF VULNERABLE POPULATIONS
AND DISPROPORTIONATELY LIKELY DISPROPORTIONATELY AFFECTING
MINORITIES OLDER PEOPLE, NON-NATIVE ENGLISH SPEAKERS,
POORER PEOPLE AND THE DISABLED .
MORE AND MORE VIRTUAL MEETINGS INSTEAD OF IN-PERSON MORE
AND MORE ELECTRONIC MEDIA AND THE LIBRARY DOES NOT FOR
EVERYTHING THAT THEY HAVE PROVIDE THE MEANS LIKE A KINDLE
OR A COMPUTER THAT CAN PLAY A DVD OR A CD WHICH IS ACCESS
THAT'S NEEDED TO DEAL WITH THE ELECTRONIC MATERIALS AND THE
USED TO HAVE VCR PLAYERS THAT USED TO HAVE RECORD PLAYERS
AND SO ON MORE AND MORE THE LIBRARY UNFORTUNATELY IS UNCON
ADDITIONALLY TOUTING TECH AND NOW ESPECIALLY I THERE'S A
WHOLE PROGRAM OF ONE CITY ONE BOOK WITH A I ALMOST NOTHING
WITH REGARD TO SPECIFICS ABOUT THE TERRIBLE DOWNSIDES
AND AFFECTING MAKING SERIOUS PROBLEMS SOCIAL IMPACT SERIOUS
DRAWS OF ELECTRICITY WATER AND LAND THANK YOU FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. DO WE HAVE ANY OTHER
INDIVIDUALS WHO WOULD LIKE TO PROVIDE PUBLIC COMMENT, MR.
PRESIDENT? >> ALL RIGHT.
AND PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSE AND WE WILL GO TO OUR R FOR
ASSIGNMENT WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 46
THROUGH 49 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION BUT WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A
RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TODAY ALTERNATIVELY A MEMBER
MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TO GO TO
COMMITTEE SUPERVISOR MELGAR 40 NINE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD 747
PLACE 47 ALL RIGHT SO ON THE REMAINING BALANCE THE ITEMS
MADAM CLERK THAT IS 46 AND 48 CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON
ITEM FOR SIX AND 48? SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MENDELSON I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I THERE ARE TEN I WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK CAN YOU
PLEASE CALL ITEM 47 ITEM 47 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO
RECOGNIZE THE MONTH OF NOVEMBER 2025 AS SICK AWARENESS
AND APPRECIATION MONTH IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. >> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
COLLEAGUES IN 1899 THE SAN FRANCISCO CHRONICLE REPORTED
THE ARRIVAL OF FOUR SICK MEN THE FIRST RECORDED SOUTH ASIAN
PIONEERS TO ENTER CALIFORNIA THROUGH SAN FRANCISCO MARKING
THE BEGINNING OF A VIBRANT AND RESILIENT SICK AMERICAN
COMMUNITY HERE ON THE WEST COAST, SICK PIONEERS WORKED
IN LUMBER MILLS AND ON RAILROAD CONSTRUCTION BEFORE BECOMING
SOME OF CALIFORNIA'S MOST INNOVATIVE AND PRODUCTIVE
FARMERS HELPING TO TRANSFORM THE STATE'S CENTRAL VALLEY INTO
ONE OF THE WORLD'S MOST ABUNDANT AGRICULTURAL REGIONS.
>> AS THE FIFTH LARGEST RELIGION IN THE WORLD, SIKHISM
HAS NEARLY 30 MILLION FOLLOWERS, INCLUDING
APPROXIMATELY 375,000 IN CALIFORNIA ALONE.
DESPITE THIS HISTORY LEGISLATION TO AUTHORIZE SIX
AND OTHER SOUTH ASIAN IMMIGRANTS TO NATURALIZED AS
UNITED STATES CITIZENS WASN'T ENACTED UNTIL 1946,
UNDERSCORING THE BARRIERS FACED BY EARLY SIKH AMERICANS WHO
NONETHELESS PERSEVERED AND CONTRIBUTED MEANINGFULLY TO
THEIR ADOPTED HOMELAND. >> IMPORTANTLY, THE GOVERNOR OR
A REVOLUTION PARTY FOUND ITS BASE IN SAN FRANCISCO IN 1913
ACTING AS A HOME TO PROGRESSIVE THOUGHT AND A CROSSROADS OF
GLOBAL IDEAS, ACTIVISM AND DISSENT WHERE FREEDOM OF
SPEECH AND POLITICAL EXPRESSION ALLOWED BRITISH INDIAN
REVOLUTIONARIES TO ORGANIZE OPENLY FOR INDEPENDENCE
AND EQUALITY. FROM ITS BASE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THE OTHER PARTY PUBLISHED ANOTHER.
THE FIRST PUNJABI LANGUAGE NEWSPAPER IN THE UNITED STATES
WHOSE WORDS REACHED COMMUNITIES ACROSS ASIA, AFRICA AND THE
PACIFIC ADVANCING A VISION OF REVOLUTION AND FREEDOM FOR ALL
THAT CONNECTED MOVEMENTS FOR JUSTICE AROUND THE WORLD.
>> THE SIKH AMERICAN COMMUNITY CONTINUES TO ENRICH SAN
FRANCISCO THROUGH CONTRIBUTIONS IN BUSINESS, EDUCATION,
TECHNOLOGY, MEDICINE AND PUBLIC SERVICE REFLECTING THE CITY'S
COMMITMENT TO DIVERSITY, EQUITY AND SHARED PROGRESS.
SIX HAVE REMAINED AMONG THE MOST FREQUENTLY TARGETED FAITH
GROUPS, UNDERSCORING THE NEED FOR EDUCATION AND SOLIDARITY TO
FOSTER UNDERSTANDING AND INCLUSION.
AND SPEAKING FROM PERSONAL EXPERIENCE, I WANTED TO COMMENT
IN SOME OF THE PUBLIC COMMENT THAT WAS RAISED ABOUT THE
CONTINUED ATTACKS AND DISCRIMINATION OF THE SIKH
COMMUNITY ESPECIALLY AS I SAW PERSONALLY AFTER 911.
UNFORTUNATELY A LOT OF THE SIKH COMMUNITY WAS TARGETED BECAUSE
A LOT OF THE PEOPLE WHO WERE UNEDUCATED THOUGHT THAT THEY
WERE MUSLIM. AND AS A MUSLIM-AMERICAN SEEING
ANOTHER MEMBER OF THE COMMUNITY BE TARGETED DUE TO
DISCRIMINATION AND PREJUDICE IS SOMETHING I HAVE REMEMBERED
SINCE I WAS A TEENAGER AND WE HAVE TO REMEMBER IN THAT
CONTEXT THAT WHEN ONE GROUP IS TARGETED OFTEN MANY GROUPS ARE
TARGETED AT THE SAME TIME. >> SO COLLEAGUES ITEM 47
RECOGNIZES THE MONTH OF NOVEMBER 2025 AS SICK AWARENESS
AND APPRECIATION MONTH REPRESENTING A COMMITMENT TO
ENSURING THAT ALL PEOPLE OF FAITH INCLUDING THE SIKH
COMMUNITY CAN PRACTICE THEIR RELIGION FREELY AND FEARLESSLY
AND STANDS UNITED AGAINST ALL FORMS OF HATE DISCRIMINATION
AND INTOLERANCE WHILE UPHOLDING THE CITY'S ENDURING VALUES OF
EQUITY, DIGNITY AND BELONGING FOR ALL RESIDENTS.
THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED AND THEN MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU CALL ITEM
49? >> ITEM 49 THIS IS A RESOLUTION
TO DECLARE NOVEMBER 17TH 2025 AS WORLD PREMATURITY AWARENESS
DAY IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND TO URGE
INTERAGENCY EFFORTS TO CLOSE GAPS IN BIRTH DISPARITIES.
>> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT.
COLLEAGUES, I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR WALTON SAUDER
FIELDER AND CHEN FOR THEIR CO-SPONSORSHIP DECLARING
NOVEMBER 17TH, 2025 AS WORLD PREMATURITY AWARENESS DAY
IN SAN FRANCISCO. >> THIS RESOLUTION REPRESENTS
AN INTERNATIONAL HEALTH CAMPAIGN THAT URGES FOR
INCREASING INVESTMENTS TO PREVENT PRETERM BIRTHS
AND SUPPORT BIRTH GIVERS AND BABIES WITH ACCESSIBLE LIFE
SAVING HEALTH CARE PRETERM BIRTH OCCURS BEFORE 37
COMPLETED WEEKS OF PREGNANCY AND THESE BABIES ARE MORE
SUSCEPTIBLE TO DIFFICULT BREATHING LONG TERM
DISABILITIES AND CHRONIC ILLNESSES.
>> SAN FRANCISCO HAS ONE OF THE WORST BIRTH DISPARITIES
IN CALIFORNIA WITH ONE IN EVERY 12 BABIES BORN PRETERM WITH
BLACK PACIFIC ISLANDERS NATIVE AMERICANS AND LATIN A PREGNANT
PEOPLE EXPERIENCING DISPROPORTIONATELY HIGHER RATES
OF PRETERM BIRTH THAN THEIR WHITE COUNTERPARTS.
NO BIRTH GIVER REGARDLESS OF RACE OR INCOME SHOULD FACE
PREVENTABLE LIFE THREATENING RISK DURING CHILDBIRTH WHEN
MEDICAL PROFESSIONALS POSSESS THE KNOWLEDGE AND THE RESOURCES
TO ADDRESS COMPLICATIONS THAT CAN RESULT IN FATALITIES FOR
THE PARENT AND THE CHILD, THIS RESOLUTION SEEKS IMMEDIATE
ACTION IN INCREASED INVESTMENT IN STRONGER, MORE RESILIENT
HEALTH SYSTEMS TO SAVE LIVES, IMPROVE HEALTH AND PROMOTE THE
RIGHTS AND OPPORTUNITIES FOR WOMEN AND CHILDREN.
THIS WEEK I ENCOURAGE ALL SAN FRANCISCANS TO TAKE A MOMENT TO
HONOR OUR HEALTH CARE WORKERS MIDWIVES, BIRTH DOULAS AND THE
BIRTH GIVERS WHOSE STRENGTH AND RESILIENCE BRING NEW LIFE
TO OUR COMMUNITY. THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR SUPPORT
. THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR I
THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
MADAM CLERK DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS AND TO
REPORT MR. PRESIDENT THEN CAN YOU READ THE IN MEMORIAM?
>> TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE
FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR WALTON
FOR THE LATE MR. REGINALD CUMMINGS ON BEHALF OF
SUPERVISOR MAHMUD FOR THE LATE MISS ALICE WONG ON BEHALF OF
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN TO BE PREPARED ON BEHALF OF THE FULL
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR MS. MARY KAY AND GAUDIO AND I THINK
THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA.
MADAM CLERK IS THERE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US
TODAY? >> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS
FOR TODAY. THANK YOU AND WE ARE ADJOURNED